<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The traueiler of Ierome Turler deuided into two bookes. The first conteining a notable discourse of the maner, and order of traueiling ouersea, or into straunge and forrein countreys. The second comprehending an excellent description of the most delicious realme of Naples in Italy. A woorke very pleasaunt for all persons to reade, and right profitable and necessarie vnto all such as are minded to traueyll.</title>
            <title>De peregrinatione et agro Neapolitano libri II. English</title>
            <author>Turler, Jerome, 1550-1602.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1575</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 223 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 105 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14029</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24336</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118699</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853906</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853906</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19307</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14029)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19307)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 552:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The traueiler of Ierome Turler deuided into two bookes. The first conteining a notable discourse of the maner, and order of traueiling ouersea, or into straunge and forrein countreys. The second comprehending an excellent description of the most delicious realme of Naples in Italy. A woorke very pleasaunt for all persons to reade, and right profitable and necessarie vnto all such as are minded to traueyll.</title>
                  <title>De peregrinatione et agro Neapolitano libri II. English</title>
                  <author>Turler, Jerome, 1550-1602.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 192 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By William How, for Abraham Veale,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1575.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: De peregrinatione et agro Neapolitano libri II.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Italy --  Description and travel --  1501-1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19307:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19307:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE TRAVEILER of Ierome Turler, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into two Bookes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt conteining a <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table diſcourſe of the maner, and</hi> order of traueiling ouerſea, or into ſtraunge and forrein Countreys.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond comprehending</hi> an excellent deſcription of the <hi>moſt delicious Realme of</hi> Naples in Italy.</p>
            <p>A <hi>woorke very pleaſaunt for all</hi> perſons to reade, and right <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable and neceſſarie vnto all</hi> ſuch as are minded to Traueyll.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London <hi>by William How, for</hi> Abraham Veale. 1575.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19307:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19307:2"/>
            <head>To the Right honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>and renowmed Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, the Lord George, Hugh</hi> and Vitus, brethren, of the auncient <hi>houſe of the</hi> Schonburges. <hi>Lordes of Glaucha, and Waldenburge:</hi> Ierome Turler <hi>ſendeth gréeting.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Yght</hi> hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and renou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Barons, it is nobly written by <hi>Iſocrates,</hi> that chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren oughte too keepe their fathers Friends as dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: as they woulde their owne inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And your father of worthy me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, loued my father deerely, &amp; hee liued togither with your Grandfather many yeeres in the Courte of Duke George the noble Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi> and he was borne in the dayes of your Greatgrandfather of <hi>Austine Turler</hi> his father, who was then Conſull of
<pb facs="tcp:19307:3"/> 
               <hi>Leſnick,</hi> which towne is vnder your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction at this day, and whereof my Vncle is nowe at this preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſull, one whom yee knowe ryghtwell. Wherefore, I haue often deuiſed with my ſelf, by what meanes I might like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe continue this frendship, or rather teſtefie my dutie towards you &amp; your familie, and if it could bee, how to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large the ſame, but hetherto I coulde finde no good opportunitie, for that yee were of ſo ſmal yeeres that wanted rather inſtruction in diſcretion, and good manners: then to bee occupied in debating of graue matters, and alſo yee had ſuch inſtructers, and ſchoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſters, that if yee followed their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumentes there should redownd great honour to your ſelues, and great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie to your ſubiectes. Albeit then it be ſo, that ye haue no neede of myne admonicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either to the ſtudie of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue &amp; godlineſſe, or towards the attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of good artes &amp; learning: yet the ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a mans dutie is wont to be acceptable to good natures, &amp; ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:19307:3"/> eſpecially ſuch as are of Nobilitie, and deſcended of the greateſt parentage. Thus ſtaying my ſelf vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: I ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnto ye this booke which I haue written in the behalf of ſuch as are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſierous to traueill, and to ſee forreine Cuntries, &amp; ſpecially of ſtudents. For ſince Experience is the greateſt parte of humane wiſedome, and the ſame is increaſed by traueil: I ſuppoſe there is no man will deney, but that a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may become the wiſer by traueiling. How beit if in any thing: ſurely in this moſt diligent circumſpection is very requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, by reaſon of the daungers that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelues vnto traueilers, and the weakeneſſe of mans iudgment, which vnleſſe it be then confirmed by vſe &amp; experience, and holpen by the counſel of others: it will ſoone be brought into errour. Here is moreouer to be added, that the youth and flourishing yeeres are moſte commonly employd in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueill, which of their owne courſe and condicion are inclined vnto vice, and much more erneſtly imbrace the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:19307:4"/> if it be entiſed thereto, which manica time and often chaunceth in trauey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: wherfore, mee thinkes they do a good deede, and well deſerue of al me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that gyue preceptes of traueyling. Which thing, althoughe I perceyue that ſome haue doone: yet haue they doone it heere and there in ſundrie Bookes, and not in any one certeine place. And being a neceſſarie thing to haue all ſuch matter in a readineſſe as may well and profitably be ſaid of one thing: I haue therefore handled that argument according to the definitiue Methode, as they ſpeake in the ſchooles, and haue comprehended al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, as I iudge, in one Booke, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is neceſſarie for any to know con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the due taking in hand of tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueill, and the proſperous perfourming of the ſame. I haue alſo adioyned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this diſcourſe another booke, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I haue applied thoſe preceptes of mine, vnto ſuch things as ſeemed vnto me worthy the ſeing and obſeruing in the Realme of <hi>Naples,</hi> which beeinge
<pb facs="tcp:19307:4"/> none other thing then an example of ſuch documentes as wee haue ſet down in the firſt Booke: I haue therefore made the title vnto all the whole wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, <hi>Of Traueill, and of the Realme of Naples,</hi> becauſe no man shall thinke that I haue coupled contrary thinges togither. For although in deede it bee one thing to intreate of the Realme of <hi>Naples,</hi> and another thing to giue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes vnto ſuch as meane to traueill: yet ſince traueiling conſiſteth of view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; diligent conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of things, and preceptes are lightned by exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples: there is no iuſt impediment to the contrarie, but that I maye ioyne theſe twaine togither. And as I haue alſo admonished in the booke: I truſt that this my labour will bee the more acceptable vnto ſome, for the ſame cauſe. For if they shall want preceptes they shall finde them heere in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and if they do require an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple agreeable to preceptes, they haue heere ſuche a one beefore their eyes which may both inſtruct their mindes
<pb facs="tcp:19307:5"/> and alſo inflame them vnto the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge of moſt bewtifull ſightes, and Antiquitie. Receiue in good parte, Right honorable and renoumed Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons, this ſimple gifte from mee, and therin my dutie and ſeruice towardes ye and your familie. Which if it shall pleaſe you to do: I wil do min indeuor to omit nothing which I may thinke to tende vnto the commendation and ornament of your houſe: and that my good will may be knowen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you hereafter, by ſome tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueill of more graue ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Fare yee well.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19307:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Contentes of the Chapters contained</hi> in this preſent <hi>woorke.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <head>In the firſte Booke.</head>
               <item>OF the Definition of Traueill, with a propoſition thereto annexed. Chap. 1</item>
               <item>What Perſons are meete or vnmeete to traueil, and alſo of the cauſes of traueill. Chapter. 2.</item>
               <item>Howe a man ought to Traueill, and of the effect and commoditie of Traueill. Chap. 3</item>
               <item>Of the properties of the foure principall Nacions of Europe, and how a man ſhall know, whether he haue profited by traueill, or not. Chap. 4</item>
               <item>What thinges are to be conſidered in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueillinge. Chap. 5.</item>
               <item>How wee ought to make a choyce of ſuche thinges as wee ſee, or learne in traueil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linge: and of the Traueillers Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges. Chap. 6</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:19307:6"/>
               <item>Examples of notable men that haue tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilled. Chap. 7.</item>
               <item>Of ſuch matter as is commonly obiected againſt traueillers, with a confutacion thereof. Chap 8</item>
               <item>An anſwere to the principall Queſtion, with a notable commendacion of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueill thereto anexed. Chap. 9</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>¶ <hi>In the ſecond</hi> Booke.</head>
               <item>THe Argument and Contentes of the ſeconde Booke, with the intent, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe of the ſame breefly expreſſed. Chap. 1</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Portus Baianus,</hi> commonly called <hi>La Peſcina mirabile,</hi> a wounderfull Fiſhponde. Chap. 2</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Centum cellae,</hi> commonly called <hi>Cento cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erelle,</hi> an hundred Chambers. Chap. 3</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mons Canita,</hi> the Hill Canita. Chap. 4</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lacus Auerni,</hi> the Lake Auernus. Chap. 5.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ciceroes Academie,</hi> Villedge, and hoat Bathes. Chap. 6</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cumae,</hi> the citie Cuma. Chap. 7</item>
               <item>Baines. Chap. 8.</item>
               <item>A Well or Fowntaine in the Sea, and the way called <hi>Attellana.</hi> Chap. 9</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:19307:6"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Forum Vulcani,</hi> Vulcanes Merket place. Chap. 10</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Puteolis,</hi> the Citie Puteolis. Chapt. 11</item>
               <item>An Hill ariſinge out of the grounde. Chap. 12.</item>
               <item>The Hill <hi>Pauſilypus.</hi> Chap. 13.</item>
               <item>The Citie of <hi>Naples</hi> Chap. 14</item>
               <item>Gardeines. Chap. 15.</item>
               <item>Welles, and Streetes. Chap. 16</item>
               <item>The Merket place, and Churches. Chap. 17.</item>
               <item>Storehouſes, Caſtles and Armories. Chap. 18.</item>
               <item>Antiquities, the Vniuerſitie, and peculyar properties of the Citie, and People of <hi>Naples.</hi> Chap. 19.</item>
               <item>The Kinges Pittes or Pondes, and the Hill <hi>Veſuuius</hi> called now <hi>Summi,</hi> and of others. Chap. 20.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_authors_and_books">
            <pb facs="tcp:19307:7"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>Names of the</hi> Auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours and Bookes, that are cited in <hi>this Woorke.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>ANtonius de Roſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, <hi>a Lawier.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Athenaeus.</item>
               <item>Beroſus.</item>
               <item>Bible.</item>
               <item>Blondus.</item>
               <item>Brisſionius, <hi>a lawier.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cato de Originibus.</item>
               <item>Cicero.</item>
               <item>Ciriacus Anconitanus</item>
               <item>Claudianus.</item>
               <item>Clemens Alexandri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</item>
               <item>Copernicus.</item>
               <item>Dion Caſsius Nicaeus.</item>
               <item>Dioniſius Halicar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſseus.</item>
               <item>Eraſmi adagia.</item>
               <item>Euripides.</item>
               <item>Feſtus Pomponius.</item>
               <item>Fort. quaestiones.</item>
               <item>Franciſcus Senenſis</item>
               <item>Furius Coriolanus.</item>
               <item>Homerus.</item>
               <item>Horatius.</item>
               <item>Ius Canonicum.</item>
               <item>Ius Ciuile.</item>
               <item>Iuuenalis.</item>
               <item>Landus Hortenſius.</item>
               <item>Leander Bononien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis.</item>
               <item>Leges xii. tabula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</item>
               <item>Leuinus Lemnius.</item>
               <item>Liuius.</item>
               <item>Ouidius.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:19307:7"/>
               <item> Plato.</item>
               <item>Plautus.</item>
               <item>Plinius ſecundus.</item>
               <item>Plinius nat. hiſt. ſcriptor.</item>
               <item>Plutarchus.</item>
               <item>Polibius.</item>
               <item>Pomponius Laetus.</item>
               <item>Propertius.</item>
               <item>Senecae.</item>
               <item>Seruius Sulpitius.</item>
               <item>Silius Italicus.</item>
               <item>Simon Portius.</item>
               <item>Strabo.</item>
               <item>Triumphus Neapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litanus.</item>
               <item>Thucydides.</item>
               <item>Varro de ling. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina.</item>
               <item>Vegetius.</item>
               <item>Virgilius.</item>
               <item>Vorthuſius.</item>
               <item>Vitruuius.</item>
               <item>Volaterranus.</item>
               <item>Xenophon.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:19307:8"/>
            <head>¶ <hi>At</hi> Bononie, <hi>the firſte</hi> Stone from the Citie, in the villedge of Marke <hi>Antonie de L'auolta, a</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natour, ſtandeth this Monument to bee ſéene.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Alia Loelia Criſpis,</hi> neither Man, nor Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, nor Mungrell, neither Maide, nor younge Woman, nor old Wife, neither Chaſt, nor a Harlot, nor Honest, <hi>But all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dyinge neither by Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,
<pb facs="tcp:19307:8"/> nor Sworde, nor Poyſon, <hi>But by all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lying neither in the open Ayre, nor in the Water, nor in the Earth, <hi>But euery where:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lucius Agatho Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi> vnto her neyther Husband, nor Louer, nor Kinſeman, neither Sorowfull, nor Glad, nor Weeping: this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument beeyng neyther Heape, nor Piller, nor
<pb facs="tcp:19307:9"/> Sepulcher, <hi>But all.</hi> He knoweth and yet hee cannot tell, for whom hee hath erected.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19307:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>OF THE DEFI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition of Trauaile, with</hi> a propoſition therto anex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ <hi>The firſt Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His worde Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regrinus</hi> which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a ſtraunger or tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiler, in the Latine tongue in ſundrye ages hath had ſundry ſignifications. For as <hi>Varro,</hi> and <hi>Feſtus Pomponius</hi> doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auntient <hi>Romans</hi> called an ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie by the name of <hi>Peregrinus</hi> a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: and an enemie whom they cal now at this preſent <hi>Hoſtis,</hi> they tearmed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Perduellis:</hi> in which ſignificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was thus written in the lawes of the xij ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles: <hi>If you haue appoynted anye daie with a ſtraunger you muste needes come.</hi> But that worde grewe out of the ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of a ſtraunger, and continued ſo long in ſignifying one that was our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie, or tooke armes againſt vs, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till it fell to a more gentle vſe, the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19307:10"/> calling all ſuch only by the name of Straungers as were not frée of the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> as beeing perhaps La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines borne, or altogither Aliens: and in this ſignification it is vſed at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent. So that this worde <hi>Peregrinari</hi> to traueile, deſcendeth from the worde <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragrare</hi> to wander, which ſignifieth to traueyle in ſtraunge and forreine Cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treyes, to wander in places aſwell vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne as knowne out of a mans own Cuntrey, or Citie. Which may well be perceiued by the teſtimonie of <hi>Plautus,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Plautus.</note> where he ſayth: <hi>I am a Straunger,</hi> that is to ſaye, borne in a forreine lande, <hi>I knowe not Sauria. &amp;c.</hi> And likewiſe it appeareth in <hi>Cicero: which Citizens,</hi> (ſayth hée) <hi>are better then Straungers, &amp;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Cicero.</note> 
                  <hi>our owne Countreymen, then aliens,</hi> that is to ſaye, then thoſe that come he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to dwell, from other places. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hence it commeth, that wée call ſtrange trées, and ſtraunge birdes, which eyſher were brought vnto vs from other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or elſe were neuer ſeene amongſt vs béefore. Likewiſe, ſtraunge ſeruing of God with vnaccuſtomed rites and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19307:10"/> maners which eyther wée haue boro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other places for religions <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ake, or elſe are by vs lykewiſe celebrated &amp; executed not after our owne cuſtome, but after ſome rare and ſtraunge order. After this maner that wee now ſpeake of, the ſeruice and Sacrifice of the noble and great mother of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gods (who was called <hi>Cybala,</hi> and <hi>Rhea,</hi> and by many others names moe) alſo of <hi>Ceres,</hi> and <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> might well bée called of the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſtraunge, eyther for that they were far ſet, namely out of <hi>Phrigia, Greece,</hi> and <hi>Epidaurus:</hi> eyther for that, looke howe they were vſed in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, euen ſo were they in <hi>Rome</hi> alſo. Moreouer, there is mencion made in the Ciuile lawe of a ſtraunge <hi>Praetor,</hi> and likewiſe in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Canon law of ſtrange iudgementes. In <hi>Iuſtinians Code</hi> this <note place="margin">The Code</note> woorde <hi>Peregrinus</hi> a ſtraunger, is ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for one that is brought away to another place, ſometime for one that wandre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> abroade hauing no certeyne place of abode, wherein I haue noted this much, bicauſe I woulde gladly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte nothing that myght apperteyne
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19307:11"/> to the ſignification of that woord wherof wée preſently entreate. All which mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters béeing omitted, this is an auncient queſtion, <hi>whether traueyling do a man</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> common <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ueſtion.</note> 
                  <hi>more good or harme?</hi> which ſeeyng that it lieth more in the power of Fortune then in our owne good will and induſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, it may ſéeme that it is but a vayne matter to mooue any ſuch queſtion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But in very déede the truth of the thing ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth otherwyſe. For thoſe that traueyl, all doo not commit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to ſtraunge and forreyne Cuntryes, to the entent <note place="margin">E</note> to conſume there their time in idleneſſe, to bée ſubiect as a mocking ſtocke vnto Fortune: but they haue ſometimes iuſt cauſes that mooue them, and ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed <note place="margin">C</note> ende in reſpecte wherof they take in hande theyr traueyll. Wherefore, wée muſt diſtinguiſhe this kind of tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyll which hath ſome certeyne ende propoſed, from that which is taken in hande onely for Idleneſſe ſake: Howbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it this laſt kinde cannot iuſtly bée called by the name of Idleneſſe, ſince it hath ſome ſmall delight, yet not tending at all to any ende, adioyning vnto it. For
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19307:11"/> true delight and pleaſure, is ſought for in reſpect of ſome ende, and whereas is no end, there alſo can bée no pleaſure: for in all kinde of trauailing there is certen paine &amp; labour contained, which repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth againſt idleneſſe tending vnto ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue not to vice, inſomuch that if wée doe vprightly weigh the thing: we ſhal then finde, that, <hi>Traueill is nothing elſe but a paine taking to ſee and ſearche forreine landes, not to bee taken in hande by all ſorts of perſons, or vnaduiſedly, but ſuch as are meete thereto, eyther to the ende that they may attayne to ſuche artes and knowledge as they are deſirous to learne or exerciſe: or elſe to ſee, learne, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to marke ſuche things in ſtrange Countries, as they shall haue neede to vſe in the common trade of lyfe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they maye profite themſelues, their friendes, and Countrey if neede require.</hi> This definition who ſo marketh well, hée ſhall eaſely make anſwere to the queſtion erewhile propounded. For hée ſhall not onelye diſcerne traueyll from ſluggiſh Idleneſſe, whileſt he pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19307:12"/> this worde, <hi>Payne,</hi> for the generall ſignification which the Logicians do cal <hi>Genus,</hi> but alſo comprehendeth manie other thinges, which the Rethoritians, and Logicians doe vſually handle by <hi>Theſis</hi> and <hi>Hipotheſis,</hi> definite and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definite queſtions, whollye ſettinge downe béefore our eyes whatſoeuer ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteineth to this preſent queſtion. And whereas all kinde of paynes are not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in traueilyng, therefore haue I cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it, <hi>the payne to ſee and ſerch,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I adde theſe wordes, <hi>Foraine Lands,</hi> that I may diſtinguiſhe it from ſmall and ſhort iourneis, which enie man ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in hande for pleaſures ſake in his owne cuntrey. But let vs now procéede in order to the reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19307:12"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>What Perſons are meete or vnmeete to</hi> Traueil, and alſo of the <hi>cauſes of Traueill.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>
                  <hi>Chapter.</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>NAture teacheth vs, that Infants, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged perſons, &amp; ſuch as haue weake bodies, are of al others leſſe meet to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueill. And although it oftentimes chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth through the iniquitie of the tyme, or ſome common calamitie thereto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraining, that perſons of ſuch age and condicion are enforced to traueill: yet are they vnméet for it, not being able to abide thoſe paynes that accuſtomablye befal to traueillers. Like as <hi>Iacob</hi> mée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge with his brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> excuſeth himſelfe from traueylynge by reaſon of his young Children, who if they were weryed but with one dayes traueill, wold die w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the paines of ſo long a iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. And as touching old folke by proofe it is euident, that they are nothing méet to traueill: ſince ould age of it ſelfe is ſuppoſed to be an heuy burthen. Which the Poet <hi>Ouid</hi> hath done vs to vndeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19307:13"/> in the 4. Booke <hi>De Triſtibus,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> viii. <hi>Elege.</hi> And lykewiſe the noble Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et <hi>Homer,</hi> hath a notable ſayinge of one ſore laden with yéeres, which Verſes may thus be engliſhed.</p>
               <l>Such one art thou, who hauinge was he themſelues, and fead their fill:</l>
               <l>Strait couch them downe to sleepe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this is the vſe of Ouldmen still.</l>
               <p>Ther is alſo ſome difference to be had in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſexe in reſpect of <hi>Decorum</hi> or cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, &amp; publique honeſty: howbeit the ſame is not euery where accordinglye obſerued. For the Dutch Wéemen, and <note place="margin">Dutch wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> thoſe that inhabit the Ilands of <hi>Sealand,</hi> doe not only occupy buying &amp; ſelling at home, more dilygently then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> men doe: but they traueil alſo vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furthermoſt partes of the world to trafacque and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupy Merchaindize. And for ſo doynge they are neuer a whit the more diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, eſpecially amonge their owne cuntrye folke. But in other regions of this our <hi>Europe,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame cuſtome is not obſerued, as it was not alſo vſuall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt our auntie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fathers in foretime: as it playnely appeareth by example of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19307:13"/> 
                  <hi>Medea,</hi> who when ſhée aſcended into y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Caſtle and Temple of <hi>Corinthe,</hi> inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoringe by all meanes to perſwade the Matrones and kepers of the ſame tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that they ſhould ſuſpect no éeuell, in that ſhee had bene ſo longe abſent from her owne cuntrey, forſomuch as many haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendably béehaued themſelues being out of their owne natiue ſoyles: they gaue her no anſwer at all, that ſhée might vnderſtand, that the wide wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring of Wéemen cannot want ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <note place="margin">Weeme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Traueil.</note> &amp; bringeth ſome toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of diſhoneſtie. Whereupon the Tragicall and Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Poets, when they bringe in any far traueiling Woman, for the moſt parte they feine her to be incontinent. Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blably, frantique and furious Perſons are vnfit to traueill. For ſéeinge that they are diſtracte of their right wittes, they are accompted alſo vnméet to deale in all ciuile affaires. There bée lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe manie thinges moe, that ſtay ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drye from trauellinge, that whoſo ſhall bée frée and voyd of them: then they are not forbidden to take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> labor in hand, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in their youth, or at mans ſtate
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19307:14"/> For theſe ages are not onely fit to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure Labours, but thoſe things whiche we ſée, heare, and learne at thoſe dayes are ſooneſt fired in memory and longeſt continue. Which being ſo: it may then ſéeme ſtraunge, that <hi>Plato,</hi> an excellent <note place="margin">Mato.</note> Philoſopher, and a moſte dyligent ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher out of all thinges, hath eſpeciallye apoynted that tearme of mans lyfe vnto traueill, whiche is betwéene fiftye and thréeſcore. For ſince at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time al the ſtrength of mans body beginneth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creace, it ſéemeth very ridiculous for the age that then is weakned, and drawing apace to death to bée oppoynted vnto youthly labours, and as the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is, to heape one miſchiefe vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But I lyke of <hi>Platoes</hi> opinion well enough. For hée forbiddeth not but that younger men alſo may traueill, being not otherwiſe poſſible but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> men wyll pas and repaſſe the ſeas, and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to, which he alſo affirmeth. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſuch as haue time and leaſure, and are deſierous to ſée the trades and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of other peoples, bee wyll not haue prohibited by enie laws to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19307:14"/> bicauſe that a deſolate Citie, and ſuch an one as knoweth not what is good or bad in forein countreys, is verie far from perfection. And whereas hee hath apointed that terme of yéeres to be emploid in traueill: the reaſon is this, for that hée would haue that time eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallye to bée béeſtowed in learninge of maners and ſearchinge other know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. For ſince at thoſe yéeres mans iudgement is moſte perfect: hée is the better able to diſcerne and iudge of mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, then in his youth, or old age, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the one is rather enclined to vice then vertue and is ruled by affection, the other beginneth to fail in memory, and cannot well vſe the iudgement of the ſences. And although hée forbidde not young men to traueill, wherby they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo may ſumdeale profite in maners and knowledge: notwithſtandinge foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as that age is but of weake iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, hee co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitteth that care to men of ryper yéeres, not ſo much for priuat, as for common co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modytie. For he willeth them at their retourne home, diligently to reporte vnto the Senate whatſoeuer
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19307:15"/> notable thing and worthy of memorye they haue ſéene in forreine cuntries, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concerning lawes, or bringing vp, or appertaininge to knowledge, that if it might happen the ſame to be liked of, it might be receiued into the common wealth. And lyke as there bee many thinges that may hinder a man from traueiling although he woulde neuer ſo faine: ſo may there alſo bee diuers and ſundry cauſes why a man ought to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueill, and thoſe likewiſe ſumtimes ſuch whereof a man neuer thought before. For ſome men are naturally enforced to traueill, or rather to wander abroad after the maner of <hi>Cilenius,</hi> as thoſe in whoſe natyuitie the moone is placed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Mercurie</hi> in the nineth houſe, eſpecially in a moouable ſigne, or ſoome other lyke iudgemente in this matter: and other ſome grow into that nature by cuſtom. And others agayne traueill for gaines, and commoditie, as Merchantes: ſome for vertues ſake, as thoſe that apply the ſtudie of good Arts: howbeit theſe alſo reape gayne and commoditie of traueill at their due time &amp; ſeaſon. For, Gain is
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19307:15"/> two fold, the one honeſt, which is ioyned vnto vertue and honor, &amp; that which the ſtudents and profeſſours of good arts do attayne. Likewiſe ſouldyeurs which a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> content with their pay, as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſaith: and Merchantes if they deſire to waxe ritch after no diſhoneſt ſort. The other kind of gaine is diſhoneſt, which repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nature and vertue, ſuch as they do practize which giue themſelus wholy to robbing and ſpoyling, who being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindfull of the law of armes, and of the Oth which ſouldiours take: do not ſpare nor abſtaine from their friendes goods. That kind of gain alſo which is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hatefull among men, as vſurers, and others that heap vp wealth by right or wrong with ſuch gredines and auarice, that as the Poet ſaith, they run to the furtheſt Indians, and all to eſchew po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie, leauing nothing vnaſſaied wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they may raiſe to themſelues ſome gain. Which occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as I ſuppoſe, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Cicero,</hi> to diſtinguiſhe filthye artes from other, and to iudge nothing to bee profitable, which was not alſo honeſt.</p>
               <p>But principally wee muſt weigh and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19307:16"/> examine vnto what ende wée take our traueill vpon vs. For ſince all thing is done for ſome ende, it were taken in hand in vaine, vnleſſe it were alſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected vnto ſome certen ſcope. But as the Philoſophers doe diſtinguiſhe, of endes &amp; purpoſes: ſome bée ſéemely and lawful: other not ſéemely, or wandring. Moreouer, of thoſe that bée ſéemely, one is tearmed principall and laſt of all, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> when wée haue attained then wée at reſt and ſéeke for none farther: an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other is leſſe principall or meane, which again is diſtinguiſhed into ſubordinate, and not ſubordinate, but by any meanes hapning. Let this varietie of endes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bee conſidered, and one of them ſeuerallye examyned from another, bycauſe this conſideration bringeth great profite with it. For not onely na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture requireth vs ſo too doo, but alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and diligence, which are to bée ſought in all things that wée do. For the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall ende is more profitable then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and there is more labour required in attaining him, then the reſidue. So then it is a thing importing more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19307:16"/> and it requireth alſo more traueill, to go into <hi>Italy,</hi> &amp; to returne home againe paſſing well furniſhed with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Phiſicke or Lawe, then it dothe to vnderſtande how the <hi>Venetians</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne their common wealth, or what is done at <hi>Rome</hi> vppon their <hi>Saturnalia</hi> feaſt dayes. <hi>Fridericus Furius Coerio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanus</hi> whom I vſed familiarly during my continuance at <hi>Louane,</hi> telleth an excellent Hiſtorie in a certen Booke of his, and bicauſe it teacheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame which wee declare in this place: I will not <note place="margin">Note.</note> ſpare to recite it. A certen gentleman of <hi>Naples</hi> requeſted of his kinſman which was a noble man and had the tuition of him, that hée might haue licence to go ſée forreine Cuntries, vnto whom hys kinſman promiſed hée ſhoulde, if firſt hée would traueill to <hi>Rome</hi> which was not farre of, and there abide a certeyne time. The younge gentleman obeying his commaundement went thither, and afterwarde returned home, ſtill calling vpon his kinſman that he might goe a greater iourney. But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his kinſman perceyued that hée had taken no profite
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19307:17"/> by that traueill: ſaid vnto him, Sonne, <note place="margin">The Sum of Trauei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge.</note> you haue ſéene Medowes, Plaines, Hilles, Valleis, Earables, Woods, Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, Fields, Springs, Riuers, Trées, Thickets, Villages, Caſtles, Cities, Beaſtes, Bathes, Galleries, Coloſſeis, Churches, Pallaices, Pillers, Images, Buildinges, Downefalles, Towers, Amphitheatres, Triumphall Arches, Baines, Stéeples, Vniuerſities, Schooles, Gardeins, Conduites, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Knaues, Ritche and Poore, Learned and Ignoraunt, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer may elſe be found within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the whole world: abide therfore nowe henceforwarde at home, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent your ſelfe. Thus that moſt pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente Prince, did briefly recite whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer might bée ſaide in ſuch a matter, and wittely ſet downe the right order and rule to traueill ouer the worlde, wherby hée might reprooue the abuſe of traueiling. Notwithſtanding a man maye by one labour attaine to diuerſe endes. As for example, by traueiling into <hi>Italy,</hi> he may get the knowledge of Phiſicke or Lawe, and vnderſtand alſo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19307:17"/> the gouernment of the ſtate of <hi>Venice.</hi> Which when it happeneth in this wiſe, certen alſo it is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the commoditie which inſueth theron muſt néedes be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Wée muſt alſo take heede that the commoditie bee good and honeſt which wée receyue by our traueyll. For theſe two poyntes are not in vayne knit togyther by wyſe men, and many tymes there is an ouerſight éeuen in common wealthes, vnder couler of profite, and commoditie. And the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of honeſtie is ſuch, that it preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the bewtie of profite. So that they which ſeperate honeſtie from profite: they alwayes obtayne not their true ende, nor yet reape that commoditie which they ought to doe. But for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as in all humane affayres, wée muſt conſider to what ende, and for what commoditie they are taken in hande: then ought wée moſt eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly too bée myndefull thereof in traueill. For who ſo traueyleth in any other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte, hée ſpendeth his time in vayne, conſumeth his goodes to no purpoſe, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damageth
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19307:18"/> the health of his bodye, and daungereth his life, caſting himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a thouſand perilles, nothing profiting himſelfe or others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ <hi>How a man ought to Traueill, and of the</hi> ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and commoditie of Traueill.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 3. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ende of our traueill being deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and hauing in our minde the hope of great profite which ſhall enſue to vs thereby, a man muſt ſo prouide for euerie thynge, that aboue all hée haue regarde to hys health, whether it bée of bodye, or ſoule. For hée that doth not ſo, but dependeth al vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Fortune, be ſhal make God his enemy, hurt his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and expoſe himſelf to a thouſand daungers. For immediatly he hath ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as it were, a window vnto infinite miſchieues, &amp; hath gotten a moſt large <note place="margin">The feare of God.</note> fielde to offend in. But who ſo commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19307:18"/> hymſelſelfe vnto Gods kéepyng, ſhall bée ſaued through his protection, as ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſte.</hi> And although many éeuilles and daungers lye in his waye: notwythſtanding hée ſhall not bée moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Hée ſhall alſo brydle hys affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: ſince the cheifeſt meanes to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde ſinne, is to auoide the occaſion of ſinne, wherein hée muſt employ great diligence, and preuent many imminent daungers by hys wiſedome. So <hi>Tobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hée ſent his ſunne forth into <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tobias.</note> exhorted hym aboue all thinge to feare God, as the chiefeſt guide of his iourney, and all his affaires. Poetes feygne, that <hi>Aeneas</hi> was couered in a cloude by <hi>Venus,</hi> and diuerſe other men alſo by other Goddes, thereby eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng not onely the ſight of men, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſundrye perilles that they might haue incurred, thereby to declare that they bée ſafe from daungers, that are coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the might and power of God. Which thing likewiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcripture teſtifieth in many places ſaying: <hi>They wente foorthe and the Lorde was with</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:19307:19"/> 
                  <hi>them:</hi> and againe, <hi>the Lorde dothe know thy iourney, and thy Lorde thy God hath remained with thee, and thou hast wanted nothinge.</hi> The nexte care is, that hée haue regarde of hys body, that <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> doely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>lth.</note> is to ſaye, to kéepe it ſounde and in good health. How this may hée doone, preceptes of Phiſitious do declare, and as farre as I am able to ſay in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: it conſiſteth in the due vſe of the ſixe things not naturall, as they tearme them, that is to witte, the Aier, Meate and Drinke, Fulneſſe and emptineſſe, Exerciſe and reſte, Sléepe and Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and finally, Accidentes and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the minde. For hée that is of a weake conſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of body, cannot wel entende thoſe things for which hée hath traueiled. And therfore he ought to haue a more diligent regarde hereto, for that the chaunge of Ayer, of Diet, &amp; cuſtome, doth eaſely bring with it ſome ſickneſſe, although the payne and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of the iourney do ſupply no cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to at all. There be alſo two other things to hée marked by a Traueiller, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19307:19"/> to applie himſelfe to the manners of other, and alſo to looke to his owne buſineſſe with diligence: whereof the one is very hard for him to doo that hath no rule of himſelfe, the other requtreth rather iudgement then will. Howbeit hée muſt néedes doe them both if hée will do well. For who ſo meaneth to liue in a ſtraunge lande after his owne faſhion, maketh himſelfe a mocking-ſtocke vnto other, and neuer amendeth his owne barbarous &amp; corrupt maners, althoughe hée ſee daily innumerable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of vertues. Hée ſhall ſoone ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine loſſe of his buſineſſe that dealeth therin neclige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly. It is after one maner that wée liue at home, and another that wée line abroade, and ſome nations are more gyuen to craſte and deceite then others, which many haue tryed to their great paine. Wherefore wée muſt lyue warely among forreine nations, and take hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de wée offende them in no caſe, being mindfull of the Gréeke prouerbe, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, meaning that we muſt <note place="margin">Note.</note> applye our ſelues to the Manner and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19307:20"/> Cuntrie, and yet haue regarde to our owne affayres, hauing alwayes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect vnto honeſtie. In <hi>Clemens Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus</hi> is cited this verſe of <hi>Heracli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> thus to bée Engliſhed.</p>
               <l>Many Cuntries tis good to ſee,</l>
               <l>Preſeruing ſtill our honestie.</l>
               <p>In which, as the ſame <hi>Clemens</hi> ſaith, is propoſed an example of a Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call life, where he ſaith y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld go ſée manye forreine nacions for knowledge ſake, but not to enſue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vices of ſtrange Cuntreyes, that is to ſaye, hée admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth vs to vndertake many iournies for intent to learne, ſtill retaynynge the integritie of our maners, and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions. <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eware <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rruption.</note> For although ſome cuntries cary a certen ſuſpicion of luſt and licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: yet neuer to haue beheld any parte therof, but alwaies continently to haue liued in the ſame, is no ſmall praiſe and glory. Let vs not therfore leaue any to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of our owne fylthines in Forreyne Regions, nor let vs learne there any vile crime to bring home with vs into our owne cuntrey, but let vs inſue ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19307:20"/> and exerciſe godlyneſſe in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces whereſoeuer wée béecome. Which who ſo doth, through the power of God ſhall not onely eſcape the cruell <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Charybdis,</hi> and contemne the moſt ſwéete ſower alluringe Songes of the <hi>Syrenes:</hi> but lyke a moſt experte Pilot <note place="margin">Syrenes Songes.</note> that paſſeth vnder Sayle in the midſt of the ſea, ſhall as much as may bée auoide all quickſandes and perillous Rockes, the ſworne Enemies of them that paſſe by the déepe. Thys alſo a Traueiler muſte diligentlye prouide for, that hée lacke not his chiefe neceſſaryes, which the Logicians terme, <hi>Deſtinata,</hi> thynges apperteyning to his purpoſe, as vnto ſtudye béelonge Bookes, and Teachers: vnto Warfare, Harneys, Weapons, Horſes, Captaines, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> ſuche other lyke. So then, lyke as a ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our cannot attayne his ende if hée lacke hys Weapons: neyther can a ſtudent if hée lacke Bookes, &amp; if other alſo lacke other thinges neceſſarye for their vſe, accordynge to the diuerſitie of theyr ſtate, and callynge. Finallye, thou
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19307:21"/> muſt indeuour by all meanes poſſible, to attaine to thy purpoſe and ende the ryght waye and order, omitting all vnneceſſarie circumſtaunces. For ſo ſhalt thou take leſſe paynes, and all thing ſhalbée doone wyth more ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and better iudgement. For the <note place="margin">The great force of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in all things.</note> ſame truely is of ſo great force in all worldly and humane affayres, that vnleſſe a man vſe ſome good and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable order in performyng them: hée laboureth in vayne, or to lyttle pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. Wherfore, ſome haue written how a man ſhall béehaue himſelfe in War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, &amp; of the whole order of warfare, as hath <hi>Vegetius:</hi> ſome haue taught how we ſhould béehaue our ſelues in the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Phiſick or Law, or in other artes and Sciences, whereby a man may in ſhorter time attaine vnto them, &amp; reape fruite and commodie out of them.</p>
               <p>The commoditie and profit of trauei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is diſperſed throughout and in all things of the world, and there is no hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane action or trade to be founde, but it may bée bettered and holpen by traueil.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19307:21"/> And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I may ſay nothing of vile artes, are not all artes and trades according to the diuerſitie of them, better exerciſed in one place then another? is not this thinge beſt handled in ſuch a place, and that in another? which if a man be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to learne, it were beſt for him to traueill thither, rather then lerne them at home of others whiche haue not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly learned them themſelues. So in <hi>Germanie, Italie, Fraunce</hi> and <hi>Spayne,</hi> the art of Printing is much vſed, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Getes</hi> it is not knowne. And not onely cuntreys far diſtant hence, do practize other artes: but alſo thoſe that be néere vnto vs. As the Arte of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is as much frequented in <hi>England</hi> as in <hi>Germanie,</hi> and <hi>Fraunce:</hi> in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> it is nothing ſo, and yet <hi>Ireland</hi> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth néere vnto <hi>England,</hi> and vnder obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Quéene. The Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ar excellent archers, but the <hi>Irish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> bee better, and more experte in ſwimming, excellinge all other nacions of <hi>Europe</hi> in running and diuing vnder water. How much good, traueill doth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19307:22"/> to a Carpenter, <hi>Vitruuius</hi> teacheth: how much to a Souldiour <hi>Vegetius</hi> ſheweth: how much to a Paynter or Keruer, the horſes made by <hi>Fideas</hi> and <hi>Praxiteles,</hi> ſtanding yet at this preſent in the Church of <hi>Romulus</hi> at <hi>Rome</hi> do teſtifie, with other <hi>Colloſſi,</hi> Statues, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, and Pictures, which there is no woorkeman beholdeth, but he wondreth at them, and departeth away more cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he came. I wil ſpeake nothing of Merchandize, which is altogether, as it were nouriſhed by traueill, and not occupyed ſomuch for honeſty ſake: as for commodytie and lucre. Let vs ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uey the ſtudies of humanyty which are comprehended vnder the name of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, &amp; wée ſhall finde that in aunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent times they were partly inuented &amp; deriued from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Egiptians</hi> vnto other na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; afterward brought into <hi>Europe,</hi> continuing alſo along while in <hi>Greece,</hi> from whence they arriued in <hi>Italy,</hi> and from thence were diſpearſed abroad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to other Regions of <hi>Europe,</hi> as it were into <hi>Colonies,</hi> &amp; places of lyberties w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in themſelues. And who wyldeny y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19307:22"/> is enie profite receyued by Philoſophy, or that ſumtime it flouriſhed in <hi>Greece</hi> in ſuch ſort: that from al places men tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilled into that cuntry to be inſtructed therein, as it had bene to ſome faier, or mercate? which <hi>Plutarch</hi> wel ſignified, ſaying, that there were no men at all, if there wer not a ſea wherby they might paſſe into <hi>Greece.</hi> For that graue &amp; wiſe Philoſopher, iudged that none could bée <note place="margin">Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers are onely men.</note> called by the name of men, vnleſſe they were inſtructed in Philoſophye, for as much as wyt, and verteous furniture of the minde, maketh men, not the forme or figure of the Body. But now this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of wittes is quite taken away from <hi>Greece</hi> together with the empire, and it is to be feared, leſt ſhortly alſo it be taken from other places whether as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtudy of lyberall Arts are extended, &amp; in ſtéed therof y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old barbarouſnes come in place after awhile. Touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g hiſtoris, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> woorks of Poets, what ſhall I néede to giue any admonicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? In whoſe books there be ſome ſuchthinge, which nether by eloquence of words, or conſtruction
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19307:23"/> can bee expreſſed, neithe by dilygence of interpretours expounded, but that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they require to bée ſéene with the eye. As when in <hi>Virgill</hi> mencion is made of certayne pictures, very lyuely expreſſinge the lineamentes of nature, which <hi>Aeneas</hi> béeheld in <hi>Didos</hi> Temple ſéeming to containe in them verye mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of mind, affections, and true teares indéede: the Poet therupon ſayinge:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Great grief bringes teares, and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal haps, make mortal harts to rue.</hi> That is to ſay, a man wold ſuppoſe, that thoſe Images and Pictures had wept indéed, and that thoſe paincted and counterfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bodies, were mooued with compaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on one of them towards another. Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries reporte, that <hi>Zenſis</hi> &amp; <hi>Parraſius</hi> the Painters, fell in contention for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, at what time the one of them painted Grapes ſo liuely that hee decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Birdes with them: the other pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Shéet ſo woorkemanly that be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued him that had deceaued the birds. So lykewiſe <hi>Prothogenes,</hi> and <hi>Apelles</hi> lines deſerned to bee looked vpon, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19307:23"/> 
                  <hi>Cicero</hi> ſo highly commended the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeite of <hi>Ephigenia</hi> drawne by the Painter <hi>Timantes</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſuppoſed that one example to bée ſufficient fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which all Oratours and Poetes might take a preſident and patern to obſerue <hi>Deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> and cumlyneſſe in expreſſinge af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. The lyke is to bee iudged of Antiquitie. For what deſcription of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place can bée ſo euident, or what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretacion ſo plaine and perſpicuous, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> béeholding of the thing it ſelf doth far excéede it? And lyke as if wée reade enie thing that is obſcure and intricate, wée vnderſtande it muche better if wee béeholde ſome tokens and remnauntes of it, then wée can conceiue by the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueill of interpretours, or learne by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye ſemblable coniecture: ſo lykewiſe the knowledge of the Antiquitie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is no leſſe pleaſant and profitable, which of it ſelf is able alone to ſtirre vp honeſt wittes, and nouriſheth the ſlu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of good learning. <hi>Tullie</hi> glorieth in a certen place, that he founde out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher of <hi>Archimedes</hi> the <hi>Geometri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:19307:24"/> by the engrauing of a Sphere an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Cylinder, which he ſayeth hée ſhewed vnto his cuntrimen of <hi>Arpinum,</hi> which ſepulcher was ouergrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with buſhes and briars, and much defaced, for that it was long ſince he died. And nothing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferrior vnto theſe, haue bin founde alſo not much before our age, at which a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may no leſſe wonder. Hereof a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent witnes is <hi>Raphaell Volaterranus,</hi> writing, that in his time in the way cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Via Appia</hi> nigh <hi>Rome,</hi> there was <note place="margin">A noble buriall.</note> digged vp the body of a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, embaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> precious oyntme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, whole, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corrupted, layd vp in a Coffin, and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with a Marble Stone, hauinge bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene her féete (as he ſayth) a burning Candle whom the liquor of the oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment nouriſhed, but ſuddenly went out as ſoone as the Marble coueringe was remooued: adding moreouer, that diuers ſuppoſed that it was the body of <hi>Tullio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, Tullies</hi> Daughter whom he loued <note place="margin">Culliola.</note> dearely. Witneſſeth alſo the lyberalitie of Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> the fift, at whoſe time lyued one <hi>Cyriacus Anconitanus,</hi> a
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19307:24"/> wonderfull ſearcher of Antiquities, not only concerning his owne cuntrey of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talie,</hi> but almoſt of all <hi>Europe,</hi> and of a great part of <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> whereby hée tooke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of an Antiquarie, leau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge an euerlaſtinge renowme of his name vnto poſteritie. Who vpon a time, when one demaunded of hym, why hee beſtowed ſo muche labour in ſearch of ſuch matters: anſwered, that he would gladly raiſe ſome dead man to lyfe: rightly weighing how that many things are decaid and forgotten through proces of time, which might be reſtored by dyligence of traueilynge, and by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie of learned men, preſerued from iniurie of obliuion. Yea, what ſhall we ſay more, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhuld now haue no Coſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mography at all, which contayneth the diſcription of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whole world, nor Topo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphy, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehendeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> priuate places: vnles it were graunted vnto vs through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> benefite of trauelinge? The auntient Coſmogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers were of opinion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the earth was vnhabitable vnder the Equinoctiall,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19307:25"/> as alſo that part of the worlde, whiche ſtretcheth out beyond the polare circles towards y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Poles. Which two poſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of theirs to be falſe: partly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Nauigaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <note place="margin">The pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e of Nauiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> of the Portingales, do teach vs: and partly alſo thoſe Regions whom the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuation of the North Pole argueth to to lye without the arcticke circle, as are <hi>Gronla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dia</hi> and <hi>Willappia,</hi> with other Ilandes lying neere to the froſen Sea, Wherin the Portingall Nauigacions haue not alonely done much good, but in other thinges alſo. For where as the auncient Writers by the difference of Noonetide ſhadowes, haue called ſome men <hi>Periſcij</hi> that is to ſaye, tourninge ſhadowed, ſome <hi>Amphiſcij</hi> double ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed, ſome <hi>Heteroſcij</hi> ſingle ſhadow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: this haue they founde by their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigations to be true, and vnto the thrée partes of the world, haue found out and adioyned a fourth, namelye <hi>America,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>merica.</note> which for the vnknowne bigneſſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they think to be an other world, bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides many moe Ilandes vnknowne béefore. Whereby we are the leſſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19307:25"/> to wounder at the <hi>Antipodes,</hi> or <hi>Antichthones,</hi> that is to ſay, thoſe who, as <hi>Cicero</hi> hath interpreted, doo tread ſtep for ſtep directly againſt vs. For the Geometricall reaſon, ſayth <hi>Coperni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> proueth that <hi>America</hi> lyeth directly on the otherſyde agaynſt <hi>India Gange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tica:</hi> the lyke iudgement is alſo to bee giuen of other regions of the Worlde. Likewiſe, there is no man doubteth but that traueill was the firſte cauſe of the findinge out of Aſtronomie, ſince by it, firſte of all the eleuation of the Poles was found out, and by that varietie of <hi>Horizons,</hi> &amp; by them both the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayes and nightes. But al theſe thinges beinge omitted, let vs retourne to nature, &amp; vnto grauer ſtudies. There is no man, I thinke that wyl deny, but that the ſearchinge out of the nature of <note place="margin">The ſtudye of Nature.</note> thinges is moſt profitable, the ſame is performed by no meanes more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, then by traueill. As for example ſake, Peaches which grow in that cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey from which they tooke their name, are Poyſon: but in <hi>Germanie</hi> they
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19307:26"/> are accoumpted amonge delicates and banqueting diſhes, which ar both found by traueill. So likewiſe the Hemlocke that groweth in Germanie, hath not the ſame force which that hath that grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in <hi>Italie.</hi> Our Cuntrye of Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie knoweth not the Date Tree: <note place="margin">The Date tree.</note> howbeit it groweth in <hi>Italie,</hi> but for the moſte parte withoute frute: and in <hi>Africa</hi> they abounde in ſuch ſort: that they make both meat and drink of the fruit. And to be ſhort, other thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs grow in other places, which in one place are of more force &amp; vertue then in another, and they alſo of ſundry and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers kindes, whoſe properties and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyties who ſo is ignoraunt of: is not worthy the name of a Phyloſopher, much leſſe of a Phyſicion, who ought to be vnſkilfull of nothinge appertayning to the nature and diuerſitie of thinges, places, and men. Yea, there bée fruits of ſundrye Trées, who amonge the aunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent writters are called after the names of them that founde them, that is to ſaye, of thoſe that firſte brought them
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19307:26"/> out of forreine lands and planted them in their owne. As ar <hi>Manlians</hi> of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Macians</hi> of <hi>Macius, Claudians</hi> of <hi>Claudius,</hi> as <hi>Plinie</hi> hath noted, and alſo <hi>Appians</hi> or <hi>Melapians</hi> in ſmell and bignes lyke Quin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s, becauſe <hi>Appi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Claudia.</hi> graffed the ſame firſte vpon a Quince. In lyke maner ſaieth <hi>Plinie, Decumian</hi> Peares and <hi>Dobellian,</hi> and <hi>Pompeian</hi> called teat or Dugge Peares, haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobeled their founders and firſte plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, with many other fruites moe well nigh innum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rable. So <hi>Lucius vitellius</hi> béeing <hi>Cenſor,</hi> brought the Nut <hi>Piſtick</hi> firſt into Italy, and by the aucthoritie of <hi>Athenaeus</hi> and <hi>Plinie,</hi> wée know that <hi>Lucullus</hi> being generall of the Romane Armye, after that hée had vanquiſhed <hi>Mithridates</hi> and obtayned the vpper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hande: was the firrſt that euer brought <note place="margin">The Che<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie tree.</note> the Cherietree out of <hi>Ceraſus</hi> a certen place and libertie of <hi>Pontus</hi> called nowe <hi>Zephano,</hi> into Italy, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge alſo the Fruite thereof <hi>Cera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> a Cherie, although ſome bee of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19307:27"/> another opinion. It is alſo euydent out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame <hi>Athenaeus,</hi> that <hi>Citrions</hi> wer neuer ſéene nor taſted of within the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of <hi>Plutarches</hi> Grandfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Neither yet were they common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye eat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Plinies</hi> and <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> time, but onely eſtéemed and regarded for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eir pleaſant ſmell.</p>
               <p>Traueill is alſo profitable vnto the <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tudy of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e Law.</note> ſtudie of the Lawe, for that the lawe is more dilygently reade in one place then in another, wherin alſo are ſome things of ſuch ſorte, that eyther for the ouldnes of them, or for lack of vſing of them: are almoſt vnknowne how they were vſed in foretimes, vnleſſe a man ſée them practized before his face. For ſo haue I my ſelfe ſéene in <hi>Padua</hi> in the <hi>Praetors</hi> Pallace, the handlinge of theſe two poynts, <hi>Lapis turpitudinis,</hi> and <hi>Ceſſio bonorum,</hi> whereof mencion is made in the gloſſe vpon the Ciuille Lawe: with ſundry other of that kinde, which <hi>Briſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionius</hi> hath noted in his books which he wroate of antiquitie of the lawe. It is alſo a great parte of wiſdome, to know
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19307:27"/> the nature and maners of men, &amp; how to liue with with euery body. Therfore whoſo traueilleth with diſcretion, and conferreth ſtrange kingdomes with his owne natiue ſoyle, béeſides the many<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde commodities which I haue hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to recited: hée ſhall moreouer bringe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way this with him, the better to be able to diſcerne what is good and bad in his owne Cuntrey, he ſhall alſo know how to correct and amend eeuel maners, and to furniſh himſelf and others with bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Hée ſhall alſo haue more ſkyll how to entertain ſtrangers, and vnderſtand the maners of men more perfectly, and according to his affayres and dealinges with them, applie himſelf vnto them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the circumſtance of time and place ſhal require. He ſhal know more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer the eaſines or hardneſſe of oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nytie touchinge the méeteſt times, and fitteſt places, wherein to ſay or to doo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nything, none ſhall deceiue him in miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reporting of any thing, neither ſhall hée depende vpon other mens iudgement. For in that reſpect there be many very
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19307:28"/> bolde and importunate, eſpecially if ther be none to controulle them: as there be lykewiſe ſome Aucthours to be founde, who ether for the great loue they bare to their cuntrye, or for goodwyll and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of them to whom they write, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doo aduaunce or extenuate ſome thinges, that they excéede the credite of an hiſtory, and are altogether vnmind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of their duty. So that none can bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter reprehende ſuch then they, whiche haue ſéene the thinges whereof they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treate. It is profitable alſo to traueill a broade into ſtrange Regions, were it but to ſaue charges of Houſhoulde at <note place="margin">Charge of houſhould.</note> home. For many there bée whiche vſe ſundry meanes and waies to increaſe their wealth. And if there be any thinge in the world that wyll bring a man in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conſideration of his owne ſtate: ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly traueill wyll do it, wherein hée ſhall ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e all chaunces that maye happen to man, and the mutabilitye of fickle For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:19307:28"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>Of the Properties of the foure principal</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Europe, and how a <hi>man shall know whether he haue</hi> profited by traueill or not.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> 4. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BVt foraſmuch as wee are fallen into diſcourſe of the varietie of maners, and diuerſitie of natures in men: I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it were not done a mis, to declare the properties of ſome nacions. Not of all, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> were a great labour &amp; peculy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly béelonginge vnto them that haue written of the ſituation of the Worlde: or of the lyfe and maners of ſundry na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, as <hi>Strabo, Bohemus</hi> with others: but only of thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are chief in <hi>Europe,</hi> that is to ſay, Germans, Frenchmen, Italians, and Spaniardes. Theſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions differ ſundrye wayes one from another, as, in geſture, gate, voyce, ſinginge, talke, meanynge, humanytie, conuerſation, loue, hatred, affaires,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19307:29"/> warfare, and other things. Wherefore, breifly to ſet down the effect of the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to come to the purpoſe: the <hi>Germane</hi> hath y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> geſture of a Cutter or <note place="margin">The Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane.</note> Ruffian, the gate of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cock, a firce looke, a manlyvoyce, rude behauiour, variable apparell, and nothinge hanſome. The <hi>Frenchman</hi> hath a ſoft gate, a moderate <note place="margin">The Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch man.</note> pace, a milde countenaunce, a pleaſaunt voyce, a redy toongue, modeſt demea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure, immoderate apparell. The <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> hath a ſlow gate, a graue geſture, <note place="margin">The Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian.</note> an inconſtance countenaunce, a lowe voyce, an haſty ſpeache, magnificall bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, vndecent and vnſéemlye ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parell. The <hi>Spaniard,</hi> a commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <note place="margin">The Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iard.</note> gate, maners, and geſture, a proude looke, a flexible voyce, a fine ſpeach, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite apparel. The <hi>Germans</hi> howle in their ſinginge except the <hi>Dutchmen,</hi> who of them all doo ſinge ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ede, the <hi>Frenchmen</hi> doo recorde, the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes</hi> grone, and the <hi>Italians</hi> bleat lyke ſhéep. The <hi>Germans</hi> are harſhe and harde in their ſpeach, and ſimple. The <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> quicke, and proude: the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19307:29"/> Spaniardes fine and glorious, the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians graue, and craftie: the Germans are coumpted good in counſel, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men raſhe, Spaniardes crafty, and Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians clenly. Towardes ſtraungers the Germans are roughe and inhoſpitable, the Frenchmen gentle, the Spaniardes curteous, and the Italians diligent. In conuerſation the Germanes are impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and intollerable, the Frenchmen milde, the Spaniardes warie, the Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans prudent. In loue the Germanes be ambitious, the Frenchmen inconſtant, the Spaniardes impacient, the Italians ielous. In hatred the Germans are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uengers, the Frenchmen threatners, the Spanyardes continuing in their purpoſe, and the Italians ſecret. In af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires the Germanes are painefull, the Frenchmen carefull, the Spanyardes wakefull, the Italians circumſpect. In Religion and handicraftes the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes are excellent aboue other, the Frenchmen in ciuilitie, the Spaniardes in Nauigation, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Italians in lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. And to bée ſhort, and not to touche
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19307:30"/> euerie perticular poynte in theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Italians and Spanyardes are wyſe béefore the déede, French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the déede, and Germans after the déede. There is alſo great difference béetwéene theſe Nations in the loue of wéemen, for:</p>
               <l>The Frenchman loues the nimble wenche<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that trippes and treades apace,</l>
               <l>And aptly footes the meaſures fine, to daunce with comly grace.</l>
               <l>The Spaniarde doth more his minde in bewtie braue delight,</l>
               <l>And ioyes withall to pleaſe his lust euen with his ladies ſight.</l>
               <l>Th' Italian, with a fearfull wen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches loue is best content,</l>
               <l>That often shunnes the pleaſant game of loue, leaſt shee be shent.</l>
               <l>But shee that with a braſen face her maiſter can prouoke:</l>
               <l>Shee is the loue that in the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans hart beares greateſt ſtroke.</l>
               <p>Theſe properties, as they are by iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of many aſcribed vnto the men of <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ties of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>weeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> thoſe nations, ſo are there alſo peculiar qualities in the wéemen wherein they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19307:30"/> differ one from another, whether you ſpeake of their ſtature and forme of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, geſture, courage, gate, diuerſe ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, loue, faith towards their huſbands, diligence towardes theyr Children, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie towardes all men: or whether you talke of theyr wittes and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. For the Italian wéemen for the more parte apply the ſtudye of good learning, eſpecially if they bée of any noble familie, which the Spaniſh wéemen doe not, and the Frenchwée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men doe more ſtudye the knowledge of forreyne toongues, then of learnyng. The Germane wéemen doe ſcarce knowe anye other language then their owne whiche they ſucked from theyr mothers breaſtes, much leſſe any good learnyng. So the Spaniſh wéemen are proude in theyr apparell and goyng, the Italian wéemen graue and neate, the Frenchwéemen lyght, the Germane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wéeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> variable and fooliſh. And vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that I ſpeake héere of the higher Germanie, for the Dutche wéemen are more ciuile, more graue in goyng, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19307:31"/> more giuen to learne ſtraunge tongues then of any other nation, by reaſon of the traficque of Mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dize which much flouriſheth among them, hauing Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland, Fraunce, and the higher Germany neare neighbors vnto them, and are gouerned by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King of Spaine. The Italian wéemen are paſſing wiſe, the Spaniſh wéemen for the more part are dull of wit and vnderſtanding, the Frenchwéemen are ſimple rather by nature then cuſtome, the German wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men aplie all their wittes rather vppon houſhould affaires, then any thing elſe. The Spaniſhe wéemen vſe painting to exceſſiuely to commende their beautie with all, the Italian wéemen vſe the ſame ſomewhat leſſe, the Frenchwée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men verie little, and the Germane wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men painte their faces béefore they bée maried onely, but not all of them, &amp; that which they doe is the to th' intent to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue their louers. But as touchinge their honeſtie: that I commit to other mens iudgement. There is moreouer a certen difference béetwene theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19307:31"/> and all other, in thoſe things which wée haue béefore ſpecified, wherby they are diſcerned from all other Nations, which profiteth very muche to the fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of a mans iudgement, as the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry nations of Italians are: <hi>Ligurians, Tuſcanes, Spoletanes, Latines, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panians, Lucans, Calabrians, Salentines Apulia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Samnites, Marca Anconitans, Flaminians, Aemilians, Lumbards, Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians, Forli,</hi> and <hi>Slauonians,</hi> &amp; theſe differ al not only in ſpéech, proprietie of language, &amp; pronunciacion: but in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners alſo, &amp; many other wayes. Which thing, how true it is: <hi>Fortian</hi> queſtions <note place="margin">Fortian queſtions.</note> do declare, whervnto whoſo ioyneth the booke that was written by one <hi>Landus Horte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſius,</hi> ſet foorth without any name, hée may bée conuerſant among the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians with great profit and honour.</p>
               <p>Hetherto haue I ſhewen the cauſes and effectes of Traueill, and noted the diuerſitie of the principall Nations of <hi>Europe.</hi> Hereafter I meane to declare how to know whether a man haue got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten any profit by his traueill or not. And
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19307:32"/> although it bée harde to iudge of euery perticular, ſince diuerſe traueill for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe cauſes, &amp; ſome ſtudie one art ſome another: neuertheleſſe who ſo weigheth diligently the meanes whereby euerie Art is learned, hee may gather it, by ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie playne and euident argumentes. For as no man accoumpteth hym to bée experte in Phyſicke that hath no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in ſimples: or that hée is a good Carpenter or Caruer, that cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne a <hi>Doricke</hi> Picture or ſtatue, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a <hi>Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> ſo nether can it be thought that hée hath well employed hys tyme and labour in traueill which hath not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended and encreaſed by his traueill, the knowledge and ſkill which hee had béefore. As for example, if there bée <note place="margin">Preceptes to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued.</note> one that is a politicke perſon, and bée a Counſeller to any Prince, or in ſome frée ſtate, and ſay that hée hath continued ſome ſpace in Fraunce: &amp; it bée demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of him how many miles Fraunce, or Spaine is in length or breadth? what fortifications it hath? At what ſyde it is eaſie or harde to bée aſſaulted? Howe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19307:32"/> manie great Riuers it hath that cannot bee waded? What is the chiefe force and vertue of the Spanyardes, and what of the Frenchmen? what is the greateſt vice in both nacions? wherin doth the one or the other moſte repaſt themſelues, or take greateſt delight? In what thinge the nobilitie of Fraunce doth differ from the nobilitie of Spain? wherein alſo the commons doe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer of both nacions, what are theire ſtudies, and maners? what diuerſitie is béetwéene the buildinges of both thoſe cuntreys? which kinge of ether cuntrie is of greater power? After what maner the ſubiectes in both cuntreies ſhewe their obedience to their prince, or oppoſe themſelues againſt him? How mutch the bondage of Fraunce is vnlike to the bondage of Spaine? How in thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions the ſcarcitie of corne and vitaill maye bée eſchued? what is the guiſe of Court in doth Realmes? and what prouiſion is made that in time of warre the Huſbandmen ſuſtaine no iniurie? If therfore hée can ſufficiently
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19307:33"/> anſwere theſe demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, then it is wel: if not, it is a great preſumption that hée hath beſtowed his time in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters rather then by his traueill to know theſe things which it héehooueth a poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke perſon, or a Counſeller to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, although ther withall he know al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo what kind of Dauncing the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or Spaniardes do vſe. For thoſe things are chiefly to bée obſerued which tende to the principall ende, not toyes and trifles or ſuch things as appertaine not to the direct ende, although we may alſo haue ſome vſe of them in other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. In fine, to conclude much matter in fewe woordes, the moſt certeine rule to knowe whether a man haue profited by traueiling, is, whether beſides the things that I haue recited in this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Chapter, you diligently obſerue what hée iudgeth in his familiar talke of the landes wherin hée hath traueiled. For hée that vnaduiſedly derogateth anye thing from the dignitie and excellencie of forreine regions, without iuſt cauſe preferring his natiue Cuntrey béefore
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19307:33"/> thoſe places: the ſame is ether ruled by affection, or of himſelf rude and fooliſhe, not beinge able to iudge of thinges ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. And where diſcretion lacketh there wanteth alſo choice: and where choice wanteth there wiſdome is foorth a towne, wherwith all other thinges faill, and waxe woorth nothinge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ <hi>What thinges are to be conſidered in</hi> tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilinge.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 5. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALthough it may bée ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by thoſe thinges which wee haue ſet downe in the Chapters goyng béefore, what it béehooueth him to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue that meaneth to Traueyll with profite: notwithſtanding I purpoſe to proſecute euerie thing more exactlye, imitating the example of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> who moſt diligentlye diſcerned the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19307:34"/> béetwéene Mountaynes, Hilles, Landes, Peoples, Townes, fieldes and Foreſtes, adding moreouer what is to bée conſidered in them all. For thus hee ſayde to them whom hee ſent to viewe the lande of <hi>Chanaan.</hi> When yée ſhall come vnto the Hilles, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the lande what maner one it is, and conſyder the people that dwell there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, whether they bée ſtronge or weake: manye or fewe: the Lande good or bad: what Cyties there bee? Walled or not Walled: the ſoyle fertile or bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine: wooddie or champion? So that there bee fiue principall poyntes too <note place="margin">Fiue poi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered.</note> bee conſidered in euerie Cuntrey: the Name, Figure, Bigneſſe, Iuriſdiction, and ſituation. To the Name belongeth <note place="margin">The Nmae</note> howe it was called of olde, and howe at this preſent, for oftentimes the names of Regions ar changed according to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of time, and inhabitauntes. So <hi>Italy</hi> was firſt called <hi>Ianicula</hi> of <hi>Ianus,</hi> or of <hi>Noa</hi> who was called <hi>Oenotrius</hi> wherof the ſame was alſo called <hi>Oeno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tria:</hi> after that it was named <hi>Cameſena,</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:19307:34"/> 
                  <hi>Saturnia, Appennina, Taurina,</hi> &amp; <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullia, Heſperia</hi> alſo, and <hi>Auſonia,</hi> vntil at length it was tearmed by the name of <hi>Italia, Italie,</hi> whych remayneth to this preſente, the occaſions of all which names are partlye noted by <hi>Cato,</hi> and <hi>Beroſus,</hi> and partly by ſuche as haue written the Hiſtorie, and deſcribed the antiquityes of the ſame Cuntrey, as <hi>Polybius, Halicarnaſseus,</hi> and others. By the Figure I meane the fourme <note place="margin">The Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.</note> and faſhion of the Cuntry. So <hi>Sicile,</hi> is ſayde to bée of a three ſquare fourme and <hi>Critias</hi> in <hi>Plato</hi> reporteth of a certeyne <hi>Egiptian</hi> Prieſt, of whom <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> demaunded certeine queſtions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng antiquitie, to whom hée an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that Countrey to bée of a thrée ſquare fourme, out of whoſe toppe the Streames of <hi>Nilus</hi> are deuided. &amp;c. There is alſo another diſtinction of Cuntries, and places. For euery lande, is eyther an Ilande, as <hi>Sicile:</hi> or <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninſula,</hi> that is to ſay, almoſt an Ilande called alſo <hi>Cherſoneſus,</hi> as <hi>Taurica Cherſoneſus,</hi> now called the leſſe <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taria</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:19307:35"/> or <hi>Iſthmus,</hi> that is to ſay, a narow land béetwéene two Seas, as <hi>Iſthmus Corinthiacus, Corinthe</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> or elſe a mayne and continent lande, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s <hi>Saxonie, Miſnia, Thuring,</hi> as Coſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers teache. By Bigneſſe I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande <note place="margin">Signes.</note> the capacitie and wideneſſe, which is diſcerned in length and bredth of a Cuntrey: likewiſe in the compaſſe, boundes, and buttes, wherwith it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uironed in reſpect of the Coaſtes of the world, and Peoples, Riuers, or Hilles wherevpon it bordereth. By Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction <note place="margin">Iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion.</note> vnderſtande, the rule, and maner of gouernment which is in that Lande which being diuerſe amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g diuerſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and belonging rather to euery pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate prouince or peculiar citie, then vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whole regions: I meane to entreate of the differences of them hereafter in this Chapter. The ſituation of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey is eyther hillie or plaine, and the ſame againe either coaſting, or inlande. Which diuerſitie tooke beginning euen from verie nature, and bringeth with it ſundry great commodities. For as the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19307:35"/> ſame Prieſt in <hi>Plato</hi> teacheth: they that dwell vppon the toppes of the hilles are ſafe from fluddes, and drowning: and there is alſo an auncient conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion béetwéene the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and <hi>Scythians</hi> concerning antiquitie, for that the <hi>Scythians</hi> ſaye they were firſt made, who dwelling in the higher places: are beſt able to abide the Colde, and ſtande not in feare that the Sunne ſet them on fiere, nor dreade the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng in of the Sea vppon them, bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neuer able to riſe vp vnto them to theyr anoyance. In the former Bookes <hi>De Republica,</hi> a certen <hi>Athenian</hi> aſked a man of <hi>Crete</hi> (who had ſaide that the greater parte of the <hi>Cretens,</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termyned to make a <hi>Colonie</hi> abroade, and had commited the charge thereof to the <hi>Gnoſij)</hi> whether that <hi>Colonie</hi> ſhoulde lye vpon the Sea ſide, or not. &amp;c. There bée alſo other diuerſyties bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene Regions, or ſoyle, and earth, all whyche <hi>Leuinus Lemnius</hi> the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <note place="margin">Leuinus Lemnius</note> hath lately vttred in his woorke which he hath ſet foorth of the ſecret mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19307:36"/> of nature. And thoſe thynges whiche wée haue hetherto admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in this Chapter to bée obſerued by Traueilers, hath <hi>Franciſcus Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Senenſis</hi> alſo noted in his woorke, of the Inſtitution of a Kinge and a Kingdome. But wée muſt vnderſtand, that it is not ſufficient to haue mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked the differences of the letters, and woordes: vnleſſe wée note alſo the ground or ſoile, Hilles, Riuers, Lakes, Ponds, woods, &amp; the cities alſo in them. For ſome ground is barrein ſome fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, which <hi>Moſes</hi> willed his Surueiers to marke, which alſo the <hi>Athenian</hi> in <hi>Plato</hi> teacheth. So likewiſe ſome hilles brynge foorthe trees and ſome doe not, ſome ryuers abounde with fiſhe &amp; ſome not. And moſt ſure it is, that the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noans</hi> are muche deſtitute of theſe two thinges. The like alſo is to bée iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of wooddes, Lakes, and ſtandyng Pondes, who for the diuerſitie of trées and fyſhes that are in them: are accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomably prayſed or diſprayſed of Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricians. The viewing of Cityes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quyreth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19307:36"/> muche more diligence, for in them there are both publique, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate woorkes to bée ſéene. Publique woorkes bée eyther holye, or profane. The holye woorkes are Cathedrall Churches, Minſters, Abbeis, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches, wherof althoughe there bée ſome founde verye fayre manye tymes out of Cities: yet are they more commonlye in Cyties then in Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagies. The profane workes are pallai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Market places, fieldes, Theaters, Courtes, Schooles, Hoſpitals, Spittles for ſick &amp; diſeaſed perſons, Caſtles, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maries, bulwarkes, turrets, &amp; all kinde of municion. Priuate woorkes I call ſuch notable thinges as are ſéene in the houſes of priuate men, and citizens, as Pictures, Gardaines, Fountaynes, or whatſoeuer elſe is worth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeing, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto alſo maye Potecaties Shoppes bée anexed, ſince for the moſt part they are priuate mens goods, as lybraries are the common wealthes, Howbeit it maye bee, that they may bothe bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Princes reuenue, as bathes
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19307:37"/> doe, wyth many other things moe. And like as when we enter into conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any Cuntrey, aboue althing it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooueth vs to know the name thereof, &amp; the cauſe of the name if it bée poſſible to knowe it: ſo muſte wée doe alſo in the viewe of any Citie. So at <hi>Ianua</hi> in a certen Citizens houſe, theſe verſes fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing are written vpon the name, and founder of that Citie.</p>
               <l>I Ianus, of religion, of peace, and God of right,</l>
               <l>Am he of old that built this citie braue that ſtandes in ſight.</l>
               <l>Theſe three shall keepe the towne and (nephues) keepe theſe three in hand,</l>
               <l>Beleeue mee where theſe three shalbe exild, no towne can ſtand.</l>
               <p>And immediatly after: <hi>Phetiton</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phue to <hi>Ianus,</hi> father to <hi>Ligurius,</hi> who brought y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Egiptia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> Colonies fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Attica</hi> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citie of <hi>Ianua,</hi> in the yeare after the fludde 450. Thus when wee haue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode the name and founder of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, wee muſt next haue regarde to the maner of gouernment. For there is one
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19307:37"/> maner of lyuing vnder a Monarchie, as <note place="margin">Diuerſitie of gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> in Spayne, and in Fraunce: another in <hi>Ariſtocratie,</hi> as now in <hi>Venice,</hi> and in old time in <hi>Sparta:</hi> another in <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratie,</hi> wherwith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Switchers</hi> preſerue their lybertie and cuntrey at this daye. And although all Philoſophers and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients of pollice, ſuppoſe that al kinds of gouerment may bee comprehended vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one of theſe thrée, if the abuſe as well as the right vſe of them be weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: yet experience teacheth it to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. For there be certen cuntries, Realmes, and Cities at this preſent, whiche are gouerned by the Kinge and the Nobillitie together, as <hi>Denmarke:</hi> and as it was likewiſe at <hi>Rome</hi> in the time of the Kings vnto the <hi>Tarquines:</hi> ſome by the King and commonaltie, as <hi>Perſia:</hi> ſome by the Nobilitie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty, as <hi>Florence, Siene,</hi> and diuers other Cities of <hi>Italie,</hi> the lyke whereof was practized at <hi>Rome</hi> after the expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Kinges, at <hi>Lacedaemon,</hi> and <hi>Athens:</hi> finally, ſome are gouerned by the Kinge, Nobylitie, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monaltye,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19307:38"/> as Germanie, and Polande. Which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing knowne: wée muſt marke how in euery kinde of gouerment, the Empire is ether continued, or increaſed, or loſt: and with what new lawes, officers, and Maieſtrates, they vſe to furniſhe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues when they perceaue their ſtate to bée in perill. Which poyncte how full of difficultie it is: euery one knoweth, ſéeing as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, it is the part of a ſtraunger not to bee inquiſitiue in a ſtrange place, and not to be curious in a forraine common wealth. But truly he that ſtudieth to doo his Cuntrey good, muſt néedes doo ſo. Laſt of all he muſte bée very well acquainted with the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners <note place="margin">The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> and conditions of the men with whom he lyueth: not to the intent onely to aplye himſelfe vnto them in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte: but alſo in diet and apparell, and all their maner of lyuing, or whatſoeuer perticular thinge there be that may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct him in language, or behauiour, or help his iudgment, or ſerue him enie way y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may be profitable vnto ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kind.</p>
               <p>I knowe there bée ſome that wyll
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19307:38"/> ſay that theſe thinges whiche I gyue in precept, are for the more part friuolous, ſince there is no one man that can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue all thinges, muchleſſe he that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth himſelfe wholy to ſome profeſſion, or ſtudieth ſome other thing, for whiche he hath traueiled. I graunt it is true, nether writte I this to the ende that I woulde haue all men to obſerue all of them, for a man muſt ſpende more time in one thing then in another, whiche I haue noted alſo before: notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, whoſoeuer hath traueiled for ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies ſake or for any other cauſe, maye ſomtime be ſo much at leaſure, as to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue ſome other thinges that are profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and commodius for the ſocietie of men. And albeit diuers things may bée neceſſary for diuers perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end which euery one propoſeth to him ſelf, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frute which he hopeth to reap of his traueil: notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding I thinke this our writing wilbe vnto ſome right pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. For why? our precepts ar gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, &amp; may be applied vnto al trauel, whe therſoeuer, but chefly to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:19307:39"/> in hande for matter of ſtate and polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and which maketh men méete and fit to geue counſell, and to gouerne the common wealth. Who ſo hath propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed himſelfe any other ende, as a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, a Souldiour, or Merchant: hee may omit certen of theſe, &amp; place other in theyr ſtéede. And it ſhalbe more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, that euery one weigh with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the knowledge of what things wil moſt farther hym towardes the attayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that for whiche hee traueileth. For hee that ſo doth, ſhall receiue largeſt commoditie thereof, and ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt hit the marke whereat he ſhooteth, what euer trade of lyfe hée foloweth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:19307:39"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>How wee ought to make a Choyce of ſuche</hi> thinges as wee ſee or learne <hi>in traueilling: and of the</hi> Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueillers Priuileges.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> 6. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOungemen that traueill, muſte bée admoniſhed of this one thinge, that whilſt they bée viewing althing, ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge, and learninge, they bée alſo mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of their retourninge into their owne Cuntreye. For they that doo not ſo, they liue but for one daye, as the Prouerbe ſayeth, and are but litle prouident for their owne welfare. For ſince in all places of the Worlde there are found both good and éeuell men, and there is no Nation ſo relygious and ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile but hath ſome vices alſo adioyned vnto the vertues wherewith it is indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: ſo are the greateſt and moſt hainous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ownde amongeſt them that abounde
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19307:40"/> with moſt commendable vertues. For ſéeinge that good and éeuell ſtande in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and contrarietie one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: it followeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one of them holde vp and ſuſtayne another, and that the one cannot bee without the other, as what place were there for Iuſtice if there were no iniuries? for Magnanimitie if there were no fainthartineſſe? for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencie if there were no luſtinge nor intemperauncie? for health, if ther were no ſickly perſons? for truth if ther wer no lyes? for felicytie if there were no miſerie? That <hi>Socrates</hi> in <hi>Plato</hi> ſayde very well, how he much marueiled that <hi>Eſope</hi> deuiſed neuer a fable, wherein God ioined the extremities of theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries together in ſuch maner that one touched the other, and the ende of one were the beginning of another. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it behoueth a traueiller to bee cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpect that hée embrace not vices in ſtéede of vertues, not onely in that wée bée all more prone by Nature to vice then vertue: but bicauſe vices are often couered with names of the neareſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19307:40"/> and vertues alſo ſtayned with title of next vices. As for example, when wée call a man that vſeth his ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie arregant: a modeſt man ſimple, one of fewe wordes ignoraunt: a good man wicked: a wiſe man craftye: the lyke whereof happeneth alſo in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges. And manytimes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures make a man not thinke on hys returne, wherewith mannie are tought as Fiſhes with a hooke, vnto whiche effecte thoſe Meremaides are of much force, by whoſe ſwéete ſonges ſundrye are intrapped vnleſſe they ſtop their eares well againſte their hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie: there bée alſo infinite other allure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes accordinge to the diuerſitie of the Cuntrey. To theſe alſo this often happneth, that there are ſome forreine People ſo craftie and ſuttle, that when they perceaue a man to bée enamoured with their pleaſures, they leaue no meanes vnaſſaid to detaine him lenger with them: chaunginge themſelues into all fourmes and figures after the maner of <hi>Protheus,</hi> both to coſin hym
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19307:41"/> of his money, and as <hi>Circe</hi> did to <hi>Vlis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> mates, tranſforme him from a man to a beaſt. Wherefore, if therebe neede of wiſdome in any thing: ſurely it née<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in this, which <hi>Homere</hi> alſo ſigny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieth in many places in the <hi>Odiſsea</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the perſon of <hi>Vliſses.</hi> For ſuch is the ignorance of mans vnderſtandinge, the vntowardnes of his corrupt nature ſo great: that hée cannot diſcerne good from éeuel, vertue from vice, with out difficultie. And although wée graunt, that ſome offend wittingly, and deceiue themſelues with the couloure of true pleaſure or payne, as thoſe doo that bée incontinent, whoſe minde and reaſon <note place="margin">Incontine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t perſons.</note> while it ſtriueth with deſire iudgeth that to bée éeuell, which in trueth is ée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell: howbeit they want the perfecte knowledge, not iudginge ſo exquiſitely as they ought, and indéede are caryed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way rather with opinion then iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo ſufferinge their reaſons to bee ruled by affection. For doubtleſſe if they knewe the trueth as it is: they ſhould not erre. Thus deſire ouercum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19307:41"/> reaſon with ignoraunce, and true knowledge is neuer ouercum by affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But howſoeuer the caſe ſtandeth, there is nothing better for a Traueiler then to bridle his luſtes and affection himſelf, if hée be able. If not, the nexte is to vſe the meanes and help of others, followinge the precepte of <hi>Heſiodus.</hi> Which <hi>Homere</hi> lykewiſe expreſſeth in the example of <hi>Vliſses,</hi> feininge that hee ſtopped his mates eares with waxe, that they ſhuld not be entiſed with ſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Sirenes.</hi> But hée that will doo nether of theſe twayne, hee voluntarely ſéeketh his owne harme, &amp; caſteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe headlong into all kind of lewdnes. And as touching repreſſinge his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: he ſhall doo it more eaſely and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, if hée think often of returning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his cuntrey: as <hi>Homere</hi> writeth <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſses</hi> dyd, &amp; by this meanes through his owne diſcretion he may withſtande the allurements of ſundry pleaſures, &amp; get the victory ouer all kind of naughtiues. There is an auntient complaint made by many that our cuntreymen vſually
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19307:42"/> bringe thrée thinges with them out of <hi>Italye:</hi> a naughty conſcience, an empty <note place="margin">Three <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hinges out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f Italie.</note> Purſe, and a weake ſtomacke: and many times it chaunceth ſo indéede. But what is the cauſe thereof? for in thoſe places of <hi>Italie</hi> where the ſtudye of good Artes doth moſte flouriſhe, the Aire is not vnholſome, the dyet ſuch as euery man doth require, the men godly and vngodly, good and bad. There are ſéene alſo dayly many examples of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and vices, in all ſortes of men. It remayneth therfore, that the ſame hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth by our owne voluntarye will and méere motion, that we liue ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> béeinge ſnared in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> toyles of vices wée ſuſtaine los of godlyneſſe, health, &amp; monie, that it is growen into a prouerbe amonge the <hi>Italians, Thedeſco Italionato, Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo incarnato:</hi> that is to ſaye, a Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man become in maners lyke an <hi>Italian</hi> putteth on the nature of the Deuill, and is apt vnto all kinde of wickedneſſe. Euerye Nation hath his peculiare vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which it béehooueth vs to know, but not to followe. To conclude we muſt ſo
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19307:42"/> line among forrein Nacions that when we returne home wée may frequent our owne Cuntrey guiſe if it bée good, not bringe home with vs vices for ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, ignorance for knowledge, naugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines for goodnes, opinion for certentie, ſicknes for health, or whatſoeuer els is wicked &amp; execrable, both w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loſſe of time, and expenſe of money, and ſo to returne home with ſhame, and ſhame enough.</p>
               <p>And foraſmuch as there bée manye and diuers anoia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, wherat traueilers muſt make ſmall curteſie: therfore are there many benefits and priuiledges by both lawes graunted vnto them. For ſtrangers and traueilers a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>compted in the number of the Church and ſpiratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie, and whoſo hurteth them or their goods: are excomunicated, vnleſſe when they be admoniſhed thereof they make ſatiſfaction. Likewiſe they that traueill <note place="margin">Priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> for Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueilers.</note> for religions ſake are frée from payinge ſkot or lot. And all traueilers and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers haue frée lybertye to béequeath their goodes at their pleaſure: and if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny chaunce to die inteſtate, their goodes
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19307:43"/> which they haue brought w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them ſhall not appertayne to hym in whoſe houſe they lie, but they come to the Byſhop of the ſame dioceſſe, either to bée deliuered vnto the next hèires, or to bée employd to godlye purpoſes. But if it chaunce that the Hoſt detayne any of theſe goods <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ertune of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ibited.</note> in his handes fraudulentlye, he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to reſtore thréefold ſo much to the Byſhop, enie cuſtome to the contrarye notwithſtandinge, or elſe he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſeth the lybertie to make a teſtament, yea, who ſoeuer kéepeth away any parte of the ſtraungers goodes that die, hée ſinneth mortally, vnleſſe he doo it to th' intent to deliuer them to the true heire, and is not to be excuſed by any ſtatute, cuſtome, or commaundement, as <hi>Hoſtienſis</hi> proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth at large. Moreouer, ſuch as traueil for relligio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſake, ought not to be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled or ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d for det in any place through which they traueil, nor to bée take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion or meanes of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which Lawiers call ſtoppinge or re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h. Likewiſe, along iourny, take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hand for matter of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceſſitie, may defer mariage. Laſt of all,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19307:43"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law hath alſo prouided for thoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueil for ſtudie ſake. There is extant al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a conſtitution made by <hi>Frederick</hi> the Emperour, in <hi>Iuſtinians Code,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hée graunteth vnto all that traueill to ſtudy: ſafecondit to traueill, and frée ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie to tary in any place, forbiddinge that in no wiſe they be troubled for the offence or det of another: permittinge them to chooſe béefore what iudge they wilbée conuented, ſhewing alſo the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes why it ought to be ſo. Wee muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <note place="margin">Friendly Priuileges.</note> vnderſtand that Schollars goods are exempted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> payments and exactions. Which point although it bée not expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in this conſtitution: yet by theſe words <hi>(Let them freely come and dwell)</hi> and by many other argumentes moe interpretours do gather the ſame. And this whole conſtitution is to bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoode of ſuch Scholers as ſtudye, and not of thoſe whoſe ſkill and minde is more on their diſhes then their Books, although their names be written in the Matricular bookes of ſtudients, as they tearme it, by the teſtimony of publique
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19307:44"/> Notaries, and Apparitours. But this conſtitution is not written concerninge all Schooles, but only of ſuch as are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by thaucthoritie of great Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or longe continuance, as <hi>Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olus</hi> hath noted. There are extant alſo many titles of priuiledges belonging to Scol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Code</hi> writen in the time of the auntient Lawiers, as of the Priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Schooles in the x. Booke. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, of the profeſſours of the Citie of <hi>Conſtantinople:</hi> in the xii. Booke. And at this preſent there bée ſundrye noble Vniuerſities of ſtudentes, endued with many goodly Priuiledges giuen by the Byſhoppes of <hi>Rome,</hi> Emperours and other Princes, with <hi>Franciſcus Bolog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninus</hi> hath gathered together.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:19307:44"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>Examples of Nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men that haue</hi> traueilled.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> 7. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEtherto wée haue ſufficientlye in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of ſuch things as apperteine to the declaration of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> definition of Tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueill: let vs nowe therefore recite ſome examples of ſuch men, as haue gotten themſelues great commendacion &amp; glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie by traueill. And although this place bée more copious then that it may bee compriſed in fewe wordes, for who is able to examine all men of all ſtates and condicion whatſoeuer? not withſtanding I wyll bringe foorth the moſt notable examples of the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t men in ſundrie kinds of life. And <note place="margin">Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hers.</note> to begin with Philoſophers, it is well knowne, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Pythagoras</hi> went firſt into <hi>Egipt,</hi> there to learne of the prieſtes of that cuntry the vertu of numbers, &amp; the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19307:45"/> moſte exquiſite figures of <hi>Geometrie.</hi> From thence to <hi>Babilon,</hi> where of the <hi>Chaldes</hi> hée learned the courſe of the Planets, their ſtations, circuit, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, ouer theſe inferiour bodies. Then goynge backe into <hi>Crete</hi> how he came to <hi>Lacedaemon,</hi> to vnderſtand the moſt famous lawes which flouriſhed at that time, made by <hi>Lycurgus</hi> and <hi>Minos.</hi> Laſtlye, arriuinge in <hi>Italie:</hi> how hee remayned at the citie of <hi>Croton</hi> the ſpace of twenty yéeres, where by hys aucthoryty he reclaymed the people that were woont to lyue in all diſſolutneſſe, bringing them to a frugale trade of life the Matrones to chaſtitie, the youth to modeſty, inſomuch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the wéemen being mooued with his holyneſſe and vertue: left of their golden Garmentes, &amp; other exceſſe of furniture and Ornamentes which they were woont to were conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crating the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto <hi>Iuno.</hi> At the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth how hée ſayled to <hi>Metapentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> and there died where hee was had in ſuch admiration: that they made a Church of his houſe, and offered Diuine Sacrifice vnto
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19307:45"/> him. And whether traueiled not alſo <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollonius</hi> his Scholer? Beyng a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and a Philoſopher? he paſſed ouer <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> he went through the <hi>Albani, Scythians, Maſsagetes</hi> the moſt weal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt Realmes of <hi>India,</hi> and paſſyng ouer the broade ryuer <hi>Phiſon,</hi> came to the <hi>Brachmannj</hi> to heare <hi>Hiarchas</hi> ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in his throne of Golde, and drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of <hi>Tantalus</hi> well, amonge a few<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Schollers, diſpute of the Nature and motions of the Planetes, and of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equalitie of the dayes. From the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce how hée traueiling by the <hi>Elamites, Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Chaldees, Medes, Aſſyrians, Parthians, Syrians, Phoenicians, Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians, Iewes,</hi> returning to <hi>Alexandria:</hi> departed into <hi>Aethiopia</hi> to heare the <hi>Gymnoſophiſtes,</hi> and to béehold y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſt renoumed table of the Sunne, ſtanding <note place="margin">The tab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> vppon the Sea beache rightly being of opinion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man may learne ſomwhat in euery place, and better himſelf wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he becommeth. So likewiſe, <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> hearde <hi>Architas Tarentinus</hi> in the ſame part of <hi>Italy</hi> which once was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19307:46"/> 
                  <hi>Crateres Aetnae,</hi> nowe common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tearmed <hi>Mongibello,</hi> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge that amonge the <hi>Athenians</hi> it was forbydden by lawe vppon paine of death, that no <hi>Grecian</hi> ſhuld go into that Ilande. Moreouer hée traueilled into <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to learne antiquities of the wiſe men of that lande: from whence there is no doubt, but hée brought all the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and knowledge which hée lefte to poſteritie, &amp; in which he excelled in ſuch fort, that in reſpect therof he was called <hi>Diuine,</hi> &amp; Prince of Philoſophers. It is not neceſſarye to recyte manye moe of this ſort, eyther more auncient the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe or of latter yéeres, béeyng euident that all they haue done the lyke whoſoeuer are commended for renowne, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. And vnleſſe they had done ſo: they could not haue drawne vnto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſuch flockes of ſchollers, nor haue rayſed ſo many S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctes, as <hi>Socrates</hi> the <hi>Socraticke, Plato</hi> the <hi>Academick, Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> the <hi>Peripateticke, Zeno</hi> the <hi>Stoicke, Pythagoras</hi> the <hi>Pythagorick, Antiſtenes</hi> the <hi>Cynicke, Ariſtippus</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:19307:46"/> the <hi>Cyrenaicke,</hi> and other lykewyſe others. The lyke is alſo in Phiſitions, whether wée ſpeake of Greekes or <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabicks.</hi> For that I may ſay nothing of <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> whom in the old tyme they feygned to bée God of Phyſick: it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne that <hi>Hyppocrates</hi> dyd not onely <note place="margin">Hypocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes.</note> practyze his arte at home: but alſo in forreyne Cuntryes For hée dwelt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie yéeres in <hi>Theſſalia,</hi> being borne in <hi>Coos,</hi> &amp; being ſent for to <hi>Abdera,</hi> draue away the peſtilence from that city. And although for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> great loue he bare to his own Cuntrey he wold not go viſite <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texerxes,</hi> being therto prouoked w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> gret rewardes: yet was he naturally deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to traueill, and therfore it is written that hée woare euermore a cloake. <hi>Gale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Galen.</note> the beſt learned of all Phiſitions, hearde <hi>Pelops</hi> and <hi>Satyrus</hi> teach at <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and <hi>Numeſianus</hi> at <hi>Corinthe,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward traueiled through other partes of the world. And firſt he went to <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> where when hee had ſtayed ſome ſpace, and wandred ouer all the lande of <hi>Egypt</hi> lying round about: hee departed
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19307:47"/> vnto <hi>Palaeſtina</hi> in <hi>Syria.</hi> Hée ſayled to <hi>Lemnos</hi> and <hi>Cyprus,</hi> to th'intent to bring ſundrie thinges from thence ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to the vſe of Phiſicke, to doe hys Cuntreymen of <hi>Pergamum</hi> pleaſure withall. Notwithſtanding hée ſtayd not long at home, but vpon occaſion of a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition riſing: hée departed to <hi>Rome.</hi> From whence be returned home again after that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſedicion was quieted, where hée continued ſo long: vntill after a long time hée was ſent for to <hi>Rome</hi> agayne by <hi>Marcus Aurelius,</hi> and <hi>Lucius,</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours of <hi>Rome.</hi> But at the laſt he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned againe into his Cuntrey, &amp; there ended his life. The <hi>Arabian</hi> Phiſitions alſo were no leſſe giuen to traueile, as <hi>Auicen</hi> witneſſeth of himſelfe, that hée had welnigh traueiled ouer all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world. What ſhall I ſpeake of Oratours and Poetes? whoſe nature is properly, to traueill as <hi>Plato</hi> beareth recorde: and their duetie requireth them to doe ſo, to maintaine common tranquilitie, or for any other cauſe, which poinct is alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man vnto all ciuill and politicke perſons
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19307:47"/> with Oratours. For while they traueil abroade, and looke diligently to their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, other Citizens may tarie at home, and the common wealth be in quietnes: which innumerable examples bothe of <hi>Greeke,</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Hiſtories do teach, both in <hi>Thucidides,</hi> and <hi>Liuie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howbeit now at the laſt, let vs exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the auncient lawe makers &amp; firſt founders of ceremonies, as <hi>Moyſes</hi> that brought lawes vnto the <hi>Iewes</hi> written in tables of ſtone with Gods owne fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: lykewiſe <hi>Orpheus</hi> which dyd the like vnto the <hi>Thracians: Minos,</hi> &amp; <hi>Rha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damantus</hi> to the <hi>Cretens: Zamolx</hi> is to the <hi>Scythians: Lycurgus</hi> to the <hi>Lacedae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians:</hi> and <hi>Draco,</hi> with <hi>Solon,</hi> who preſcribed lawes and order of liuing to the people of <hi>Athens.</hi> Surely wee ſhall finde that they had all traueiled. But if wée will weigh the Lawgiuers of one common wealth onely, as namely of the Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> they will bring vs forth example enoughe who haue deſcribed their liues at large: wherein the preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of one onely ſhall ſuffice vs in the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19307:48"/> ſtéede of many, &amp; that is of <hi>P. Seruilius Sulpitius Ruffus.</hi> For it is wel known, <note place="margin">Ser. Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitius.</note> how hée acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panied <hi>Cicero</hi> into <hi>Rhodes</hi> there to apply the ſtudie of Eloquence and Philoſophie, and afterwarde lyued at <hi>Rome</hi> to the great commoditie of the commonwealth, ſo longe, vntyll <hi>Caeſar</hi> ouerthrewe <hi>Pompei</hi> in the <hi>Pharſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call</hi> batteil, and obteined the ſuperiority. For in thoſe troubleſome dayes hée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode ſom ſpace at <hi>Samos,</hi> &amp; in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, diſputing in the Schooles, of the Pontificial lawe. But when <hi>Caeſar</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned into <hi>Italie,</hi> hée was not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citie, but alſo made Liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunt of <hi>Greece</hi> as long as <hi>Caeſar</hi> ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: but when he was ſlain, he returned to <hi>Rome.</hi> Finally, if wée peruſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lyues of interpretours of the Law, both new and olde, wée ſhall finde that there haue bin manie moe ſtrangers haue taught, and profeſſed the Civile Lawe in anye place, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of them that were borne there in the ſame Cuntrey. The truth wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is yet to bée ſéene in <hi>Italie, Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> and <hi>Fraunce,</hi> where the Ciuile law
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19307:48"/> is in price. For there bee many Real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes that vſe theyr owne Municipall or Countrie lawes onely, not the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane,</hi> as <hi>England, Scotland, Polande,</hi> and <hi>Sueueland:</hi> which lawes, none can interprete better then hée that is borne and bred vnder them.</p>
               <p>Yea, noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> likewiſe, &amp; ſuch as haue done worthy and valient déedes, haue alſo bin addicted to trauel. For it is wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that <hi>Iupiter Cretaeus</hi> traueiled ouer <note place="margin">Iup. Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taeus.</note> the whole world fiuetimes. Which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it may haply ſéeme fabulous vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſome: yet it importeth thus muche, wherby we may vnderſtand that at his time he left no part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world vnſought The like whereof alſo was done by his two Sunnes, that is to wit, <hi>Dioniſius</hi> ſurnamed <hi>Bacchus,</hi> and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſt valient <hi>Hercules,</hi> the one of them profiring the whole worlde by his inuention, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching men how to plant vines: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other deliuering the earth from all kinde of wicked men, and tyrannie. For what other were <hi>Procuſtes, Scyron, Cacus, Diomedes, Antaeus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Geryo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> but cruel
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19307:49"/> and wicked tyrantes, who euermore in all places were encountred by <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, Theſeus,</hi> and other valiant perſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges? It is no vnknowne howe <hi>Iaſon,</hi> with other maies of that famous expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, called <hi>Argonautae,</hi> ſayled into <hi>Colchos,</hi> of purpoſe to fetch from thence the Golden fleeſe: which in déede he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiued, getting vnto himſelf therby im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall glory. Like as <hi>Vliſses,</hi> when he had bin twentie yeares away from his Realme of <hi>Ithaca,</hi> it is no merueill if <hi>Homere</hi> tearme him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that is to ſay, one that knoweth many mennes maners, and extoll him with wounder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full commendation. <hi>Virgill</hi> likewiſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie much praiſeth his traueiling <hi>Aene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as:</hi> who both, might well haue lyued in reſt and quietneſſe, <hi>Vliſses</hi> with his lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers <hi>Calypſo</hi> and <hi>Circes,</hi> and <hi>Aeneas</hi> with his <hi>Dido:</hi> if they had bin contented alwayes to haue liued obſcurely. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the excellencie of their courage, and the deſire of greater glory, pricked them for the to forſake no paynes nor daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ſo that they might obtayne that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19307:49"/> which they ſought for.</p>
               <p>Let vs moreouer conſider al the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies of the world, and wée ſhal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue that the Princes that ruled in them, atchieued moſt excellent exployts by traueilling, as <hi>Ninus</hi> &amp; <hi>Nabucadne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zer</hi> in the firſt Monarchie: <hi>Cyrus, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> and <hi>xerxes</hi> in the ſecond: and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the great in the thirde, with whom alſo that Monarchie began and ended. For after his death, the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes which hée left were gouerned by many, howbeit they alſo maintayned great warres in ſundry places. In the fouerth, <hi>Iulius Caeſar, Octauianus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus, Conſtantines, Charleſes, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoes, Conrades, Henries, Fredericks</hi> and other moe, vnto whom all, Lorde <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth was inferiour in no reſpect, ether for trauellynge, or glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye in chiuaulrie. For how often hath he gone to viſite the Realmes that came to hym by diſcent from his auncetours, lying wide among many Nacions, and as it were diſperſed? How often hath he returned conquerour out of France,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19307:50"/> and gone to his owne realmes? Did not hée, leauing the moſt flouriſhinge real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes <note place="margin">Prayſe of Charles the fyfth.</note> of Spaine, appeace all <hi>Italy</hi> with his preſence, that had bin manye yéeres vexed with ciuile war, and alſo preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued <hi>Germanie</hi> beinge ſick almoſt of the ſame diſeaſe? when hée came towardes <hi>Pannonia,</hi> did not <hi>Solyman</hi> emperour of the Turkes, immediatly run away? Did not hée, beinge preſent in perſon, recouer the kingdome of <hi>Tunetz,</hi> a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alme in <hi>Africa,</hi> which <hi>Ariadenus Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baroſsa</hi> had inuaded by commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and with the power of <hi>Solyman?</hi> went not hee to <hi>Aphrodiſium</hi> in hope to ſuccour y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſtian commonwealth. To be ſhort, to what kingdomes or pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces went not hée? what dangers, what labours ſuſtayned he not? wherby as I haue ſhewed, hee might purchaſe peace and tranquilytie to the Empire y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was committed to his charge, a moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent prince, and as <hi>Voerthuſius</hi> ſayth, in al poynts lyke to <hi>Charles</hi> the maine. Hiſtories much commende of <hi>Mithri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dates</hi> Kinge of <hi>Pontus,</hi> for that hée
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19307:50"/> coulde ſpeake fiftie ſeuerall toongues: but who ſuppoſeth that hee learned ſo many for any other intent, but that hee might be able himſelf to talk w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had dealings, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to be conuerſant amonge ſtraungers with leſſe enuie? So likewiſe <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochus</hi> the great, was well traueiled, and <hi>Hannibal, Pompeius,</hi> the <hi>Scipios,</hi> the <hi>Marij, Lentuli,</hi> with other Kinges, Princes, &amp; noble men innumerable of al cuntries: whoſe vertues &amp; moſt vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent déedes, ſhal neuer any obliuion put out of memorie: like as there is no age y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend of thoſe that lye ſleaping at home, giuen to ſlouth and idlenes, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer doing any thing at home or abroad, worthy of praiſe or ſpeach of poſteritie, according to the example of <hi>Ninias,</hi> ſun to <hi>Ninus</hi> and <hi>Semiramis, Sardanapalus</hi> with others.</p>
               <p>But let vs nowe peruſe the holye Scriptures, and in them we ſhal finde infinite examples of godlie men that haue traueilled, partly of their owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, partly at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement of God.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19307:51"/> For in the xii. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> God expreſly commaundeth <hi>Abraham,</hi> that leauyng the Cuntrey where he dwelt, he ſhould go to an other place: and ſhortly after, hée promyſeth to the ſame <hi>Abraham,</hi> the land of his traueill, and to geue hym al the land of <hi>Chanaan</hi> for an euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting inheritance. Likewiſe <hi>Iſaac,</hi> after the death of his father departed into <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine</hi> and dwelt there, being comaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by God ſo to doe. <hi>Iacob,</hi> his father being a liue: traueiled into <hi>Meſopota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> and after many yéeres returned thence into his natiue cuntrey. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng well ſtroken in yéeres, he traueiled into <hi>Aegipt</hi> to ſée his ſunne <hi>Ioſeph:</hi> and in ſundry places of the Scripture wee reade, how the holy Patriarches, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, and other godly men, tooke long viogies in hand, namely, <hi>Moyſes, Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> and <hi>Ioſua.</hi> Yea, our ſauiour Chriſt himſelfe, traueilled abroade very often, appearyng many times in ſemblant of a Pilgrim and Traueiller, to th'intent hée might gather his Churche from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery place. The lyke whereof hee
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19307:51"/> wrought alſo by his Apoſtles, whom he ſent ouer the whole worlde to preache the Goſpell. To whiche purpoſe it is writen, that <hi>Thomas</hi> traueilled into <hi>Parthia</hi> and preached vnto the inhaby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants there, alſo to the <hi>Medes, Perſians, Hircanes, Bactrianes,</hi> and other nacions of the inner <hi>India Mathew,</hi> to the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonians,</hi> and <hi>Thracians. Bartelmew,</hi> to the <hi>Lycaonians</hi> &amp; thoſe that inhabite the farther <hi>India. Andrew,</hi> to the <hi>Acha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ians,</hi> and <hi>Scythians. Iohn</hi> after the death of <hi>Mary,</hi> to the people of <hi>Aſia. Iames</hi> the elder, to the Spaniards. <hi>Phillip</hi> to the Frenchmen. <hi>Simon Zelotes</hi> to the <hi>Egiptians. Peter</hi> into <hi>Pontus, Gallicia, Bythinia, Cappadocia, Italye,</hi> and at length preached Chriſt at <hi>Rome.</hi> Saint <hi>Paules</hi> peregrinacions are knowne out of the Actes of the Apoſtles, and out of his owne writinges. Hée declareth how after that hee was conuerted vnto the faith, hée traueiled into <hi>Arabia,</hi> &amp; from thence returned to <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> and went to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to ſée <hi>Peter.</hi> After that, hée departed into <hi>Syria,</hi> and <hi>Cilicia,</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:19307:52"/> and when fourtéene yéeres were expy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: went agayne to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> to preach the Goſpell. It is well knowne moreouer that hee was in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and in <hi>Hiſpania Narbonenſis</hi> conuerted many ſoules to the faith of Chriſt, as he alſo did in other places, vntill at laſt hee was beheaded at <hi>Rome</hi> vnder the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Nero.</hi> Duringe all this time of traueill, the Euangeliſt S. Luke, was companion to Paule, a Syrian borne, in the Citie of <hi>Antioche,</hi> and wrat his Goſpell in <hi>Achaia,</hi> and died in the ſame cuntry. Likewiſe S. Marke the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt was borne in the citie of <hi>Antioch</hi> ſayled to <hi>Rome,</hi> from whence traueil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng to <hi>Alexandria</hi> to teach the goſpell there: hée conuerted the inhabitantes of <hi>Aquileia</hi> now called <hi>Algar</hi> neare bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers, vnto the faith of Chriſt, and was enſtauled their Byſhop. Touchinge the other two Euangeliſts, the matter is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident enough to bée ſéene in the liues of the Apoſtles. No les alſo the fathers, that is to ſaye, the interpretours of the holy Scripture, were affectioned to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueill
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:19307:52"/> as well as other men, which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo apparant by their liues, as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liues of <hi>Ierome,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> For <hi>Ierome</hi> being borne at <hi>Stridon</hi> a Citie in <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonia,</hi> learned ſtraunge toongues at <hi>Rome:</hi> and went afterward into <hi>Syria,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Bethlaëm,</hi> wher hée died in the 91. yeare of his age, as ſome haue writen. To conclude, it is moſt certenlye knowne, that all that euer were of any great aucthoritie, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, learning, or wiſedom ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world vnto this preſent: haue geuen themſelues to traueill, and that there was neuer man that perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med any great thinge, or atchieued any notable exploit, vnleſſe hée had traueil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:19307:53"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>Of ſuch matter as is commonly obiected</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Traueilers, with <hi>a confutation thereof.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 8. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt there are ſome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> much embaſe traueilling, deterring men fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waies. Theſe holde opinion that the name of Traueillyng is not only infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, but alſo the thing it ſelfe: which they proue out of certen places of <hi>Tully,</hi> and of <hi>Vlpian</hi> the Lawyer. For in the <hi>Thuſculane Queſtions, Tullie</hi> compareth baniſhment with Traueill, and in an Epiſtle to <hi>Caelius,</hi> hée emba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth Traueill, terminge it reprochfull, and filthy. And <hi>Vlpain</hi> calleth it <hi>Depor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation,</hi> a tearme of the law, being a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wherin a man both looſeth his goodes, is diſfrauched his citie, and is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed certen limits within which hée ſhall dwell and abide. After this maner
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19307:53"/> the Poet <hi>Ouid,</hi> was exiled vnto the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Tomos</hi> in <hi>Pontus,</hi> léeſing the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the citie, and all his goods being excheated. Quer this, they obiect that Traueillers are in hatred amonge good men, reguarded none otherwiſe but as Rogues and Vacaboundes that can ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie in no place, although indéede they haue verie iuſt cauſe to goe abroad. And therfore they call them wandring Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets and Vacaboundes, as if they were forced thereto for ſome puniſhment, or were in ſuch wiſe by God puniſhed. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> example of <hi>Cain</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God curſed, ſaying that he ſhould be a Vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde vpon the earth: béeinge alſo an accuſtomable maner of curſing among the ancient people in foretime, as <hi>Odei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> did among the Tragidies writers. Whervpon hath growne the Prouerbe <hi>Oedipus curſe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Laertius</hi> writeth that <hi>Diogenis</hi> the Ethnick was wont to ſay that he had met w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome tragicall curſe. For hee (ſaide he) was without houſe, without Citie, depriued of his cuntrey, hauinge no certentie of his lyfe.</p>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:19307:54"/>
               <p> Thirdly, they crie out againſt trauei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers as iniurious to their Parentes, friendes, wyues, and children, whylſt they ſeperate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues after a maner, voluntarely from them. Like as <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertius</hi> inueieth againſt one <hi>Poſthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> that through an vnſatiable deſire of warfare: ſuffred himſelfe to be caried away from the moſt pleaſaunt compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of his wife, whoſe curſe is this.</p>
               <l>If I may wishe: would God yee gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die wretches all were dead,</l>
               <l>Or who ſo elſe loues warres aboue his faithfull ſpouſes bed.</l>
               <p>And no leſſe they wiſh vnto him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly, who hath more delight to wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der abrood, and neuer bide in one place, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tariyng in their owne natiue cuntrey, enioy the moſt acceptable companie &amp; conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of their friends &amp; kinſfolks, whervpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was written by the Poet.</p>
               <l>Him I accuſe, and much accompt vnwiſe,</l>
               <l>Abandoning his natiue Cuntrey ſoile:</l>
               <l>Who ſo the ſame ſo lightly doth diſpiſe,</l>
               <l>And loues abrod in foreine land to toile.</l>
               <p>Fourthly, they complaine that Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilers muſt indure infinite labours
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19307:54"/> and troubles, &amp; not only ſtand in daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of their goods: but often of their life alſo. Which thing ſurely ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as it is prooued by the examples of <hi>Vliſses,</hi> and <hi>Aeneas.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, this ſaying is vſually obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt them, that is to ſay: <hi>They which run ouerſea, chaunge the aire &amp; not their minde,</hi> and reprochfully they allege thoſe verſes which are written againſt ſuch, who, traueiling abroad to ſtudie: returne home againe neuer a whit better learned then when they went foorth.</p>
               <l>Whoſo to Paris to his booke doth ſend a foolish Aſse:</l>
               <l>Shall there be made no horſe, but bide as erſt before he was.</l>
               <p>By theſe &amp; ſuch like prouerbes, &amp; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, they ſéeme to auouch thrée things. Firſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the exchaunge of place doth not change the perſons nature. Secondly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vertues &amp; vices, are borne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vs, and not firſt grow in vs. Thirdly, that ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues cannot bée learned, nor vices for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Al which allegacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of theirs are falſe, as hereafter we meane to declare.</p>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:19307:55"/>
               <p> Sixtly, the cite <hi>Lycurgus</hi> lawe out of <hi>Plato,</hi> wherein hée forbad his Citizens the <hi>Lacedaemonians</hi> to traueill, alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge for a cauſe, that then they ſhall not bring ſtraunge orders and faſhions into the Commonwealth, which is a reaſon verie plauſible, and alledged alſo by <hi>Plato.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seuenthly, they bring foorth <hi>Claudia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> verſes againſt them.</p>
               <l>O happie hee that ſpent his daies in natiue Soyles delight,</l>
               <l>Whom one ſelf houſe hath ſeene a child, and eke an aged wight.</l>
               <l>Who limping with his ſtaffe wher once he playd the litle Mouſe:</l>
               <l>Can count the manie yeeres which hee hath paſt in one poore houſe.</l>
               <p>And alſo the verſes of <hi>Horace</hi> writen in the ij <hi>Ode,</hi> with <hi>Ouid</hi> likewiſe wher he ſayth.</p>
               <l>Who leaſt hath liu'd in light: beleeue mee beſt his dayes hath ſpent,</l>
               <l>And eche man ought to liue within his boundes, and be content.</l>
               <p>Al which teſtimonies i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inctly confirm,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19307:55"/> that the happie lyfe conſiſteth in Idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. But Traueilers may not liue idly if they be carefull of their affaires, and meane to looke well to their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: wherby they cannot bée thought to leade the happy lyfe, ſince they mete with ſo many miſcheifes, and dangers, with ſundrye caſualities of Fortune that béefall in traueillinge. Let vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore examine theſe argumentes, and anſwer to theſe obiections, being mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame definition which we haue ſet downe at the béeginning, and of ſuch matter as we haue declared in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer chapter touching y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> declaracio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of it.</p>
               <p>And as touchinge the firſt two argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. For that which they call <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation</hi> or exile is one thing, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueill an other, and that by conſent of all Gramarianes. And although the antique Writers haue frequented one of theſe wordes for an other: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ech of them haue begon now to haue their proper and diſtinct ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification which the cuſtume of ſuch as ſpeake properly hath obtayned. And
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19307:56"/> therefore, although <hi>Cicero</hi> do compare exile w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> traueill: yet is exile one thing, and traueill another. Againe, it is one thing perpetually to traueill, of which kind of trauel <hi>Cicero</hi> ſpeketh in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place alledged: another thing to traueill for a time, wherof we intreate in this place: and therfore it is no merueill if <hi>Cicero</hi> terme the firſt, filthie, and much emba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it. For he that traueyleth perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and neuer returneth into his cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey from which hée hath been long ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or ſéeketh not ſome other place where to abide there to enioy the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities which he hath gathered by his long traueill: nothing differeth from a baniſhed ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſheweth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf iniurious to his Cuntrey and kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folkes, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he might helpe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell and aduiſe, or otherwiſe: he is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely accoumpted an infamous perſon. So <hi>Vlpian</hi> likewiſe ſpeaketh of perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall traueil, which is reſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled to death. For hée that is puniſhed with <hi>Depor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> looſeth the benefite of the Citie, and his fréedome, as is accoumpted a
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19307:56"/> dead perſon. And truly the word Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiler or Straunger, ſignified by the Latine <hi>Peregrinus</hi> in many places in the law is taken in the better part, and vſed in the proper ſignification, as I haue béefore declared where I ſpake of traueillers Priuiledges, highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> traueiling of <hi>Cicero, Plato,</hi> and <hi>Pythagoras.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And by this diſtinction alſo wée may ſhape an anſwer to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third argument. For like as we ſpeake not of perpetual traueiling: ſo doe we not excuſe them that traueill for intent to bée frée from ſuch burdens &amp; charges, as they ſhoulde beare at home: or y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they might looſe the reines vnto al licentiouſnes which they might not be ſuffred to doe at home: or elſe by right or wrong by falſe mercha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, or other ſiniſter meanes: purloyne mony fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſtrange nations, béeyng ignorant of their deceitful dealing. And like as the lawes haue prouided y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> there ſhall none ſuch bée ſuffred in any place, yea, if there bée any that ſelleth vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Wares for lawfull is not put
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19307:57"/> to his fine nor amerſed, but ether is ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed or put to death: ſo they that doo altogether miſlyke of traueill agrée with vs in this poynct: that wée wiſh ſuch diſſemblers and vacabundes ſhuld not only not be ſuffred in eny place, but alſo vtterly bée rooted out, and expelled from euery place.</p>
               <p>Vnto the third argument it may bée anſwered out of the ſecond, and third chapters. For there wée haue put a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinction béetwéene thoſe that are méete to traueill, &amp; thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ar not méete. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe béetwéene them that traueill with frute and ſuch as take that labour vpon them for pleaſure only, if ſo it bée, that labour may bee called a pleaſure. But perhaps ſome man wil demaund, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuch as be maried bée méete to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueill? For ouer that, that wéemen are forbidden, as it were of honeſtie and womanhoode, not to take long or often iourneis in hand: it is the lawe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie that thoſe whiche bee coupled therin ſhall dwell euermore together, and the one to bée a comforte vnto the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:19307:57"/> other. Howbéeit this matter, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteyning to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wéeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dependeth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cuſtome of the Cuntrey, as I haue touched before, in reſpect whereof Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonie is not hindred. Yea, what if a man take ſuch a viage in hand whiche would be profitable to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wife and all the houſhold affaires, ſuch as are the iourneis of Merchants, &amp; other that traueil for vertue ſake? Moreouer, ther may be mutuall frindſhip and affection ſhewed eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in traueiling, &amp; one minde, and one ſoule remaine in two bodies, although the two bodies be diſtant far a ſunder. And the Ciuile lawes alſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte men to traueill after they haue contracted mariage, if they haue a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full cauſe: wherefore it ſuffreth them lykewiſe that are maryed, ſince agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together, not lying together, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Maryage. And ſo farre of are traueylers from hurting their parents, and friendes: that if they had ſtayde at home oftentimes they helpe them but little, but hauing traueyled, doe aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage them very much.</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:19307:58"/>
               <p> Fourthly, that which they alledge cannot bée denied, as I haue ſhewed. But there hence it followeth not that traueill is to be neglected, ſince there be other meanes alſo wherby a man may come to caſualtie and loſſe of goods, or bée in daunger of his lyfe. And payne which is annexed vnto traueill, is lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe common vnto all other affayres that are of any accoumpt, and whereof wée ſéeke praiſe and renoume, that I may ſpeake nothing of the commoditie that enſueth theron.</p>
               <p>To thinke on this may pleaſure bée perhaps another day. As <hi>Aeneas</hi> ſayde in <hi>Virgill:</hi> and manie moe ſuch morall ſentences <hi>Vliſses</hi> reciteth in <hi>Homere,</hi> for that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remembrance of paines paſt, is woont to be pleaſant vnto vs. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, how much the more praiſe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie, or honour groweth to a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his traueill: ſo much y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> more is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and acceptable, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained without ſweate, labour, or daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, is not ſo much eſtéemed of vs, as y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which wée obtaine with great labour,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19307:58"/> and daunger, wherevppon ſprange the prouerb among the Gréekes: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: that is to ſay: Euery notable thing, is hard and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to be attained.</p>
               <p>The fifth argument is plauſible, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring experience w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it for witneſſe. For we ſée manie returne home, no leſſe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to vice then they were before they traueiled, in ſo muche as it is growen into a prouerbe among Dutch folk, <hi>No ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was euer the better after a long ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or a long traueill.</hi> And although it fall out ſo: yet is not traueill in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fault, but the men themſelues. For béeſides that mans nature is corrupt through y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> offence of our firſt gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dfather <hi>Adam,</hi> &amp; ſome ar ſo prone vnto al kind of vice, as though thei were borne to exerciſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: notwithſtanding euil bringing vp, and conuerſacion w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euil men, augmenteth this naughty diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in them, &amp; of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maketh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beaſts. Hereunto alſo come the ſnares and temptacions of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, enemy vnto al vertue, euil nurture of the minde, &amp; negligence of deuocion &amp;
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19307:59"/> godlyneſſe, which ought aboue althing to bée frequented. Wherefore, it is no merueill at all, if ſuch men continue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies like themſelues, nothing amen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their manners: for they neuer ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues therto. But if they would diligently obſerue thoſe thinges which we haue noted before in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they ſhuld become the better, &amp; haue a more erneſt care to furniſh, and decke their minde. This diſcommoditie alſo enſueth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> returning fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtrang lands: they ioyne the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to the ſame or like companions as they were delighted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all before, or elſe forgetting al dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues ouer vnto all leudneſſe, and ſenſualitie. For ſo then:</p>
               <l>Kinde once corrupt, to wonted maners vile doth run and raunge,</l>
               <l>Though much miſliked, and deepely fixt in fleshe: will neuer chaunge.</l>
               <p>As ſaith y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Satyrical Poet. Otherwiſe their ſaying is falſe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> affirme how the cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place, changeth not a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nature. Since experience vppon which they reaſon, teacheth the contrarie, and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19307:59"/> therfore many are ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t into forrein cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trys, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by their conuerſation &amp; training there, they myght confirme their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners neglecting vices: and learne to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelues to other mens maners, which no man will deny but that they may do. For if fields by dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t huſban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding maye bee amended: what impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is there, but a rude perſon &amp; prone to vice may bee made better by dayly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſation w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good men? For: <hi>Wrath may be aſwaged by perſuaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſaith <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch:</hi> ſo great is the force of company, and dayly conuerſation. And like as hearbes &amp; fruites planted in one grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, if they be remooued into another or that is of ſome other qualitie, they grow out of kind, in ſo much that they léeſe either their colour, or taſte, and naturall qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, by reaſon of the nature of the ſoile, influence of the heauens, and goodneſſe of the aire, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diuerſe maner of nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment: ſo hapneth alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> like in men according to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of nouriſhment, and the aire that compaſſeth them chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging them into another conſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19307:60"/> temperature of body, &amp; enclining them to enſue other maners, and ſtudies. By this means a Dane is tranſformed into a Spaniard a Germane into a french<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man or <hi>Italian,</hi> namely by dayly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation, vſe of life, &amp; cuſtome. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we muſt diligently take héede that we imitate the vertues and not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vices of other, of which point I haue admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed before. For this which thei affirm, that vertues cannot bée learned nor vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces forgotten: is falſe, for there is lefte vnto man a free will in ſuche externall matters, and there are ſéene euerie day examples of vertues and vices, which a man, if hée liſte, may no leſſe imitate then he maye the woorke of ſome cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning woorkman, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he haue ſome na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural inclination to that art and knowe the principles of it, as of Painting, or grauing. Nether is that abſolutely true which they thinke to bée, that vertues and vices are borne wyth vs, not grow in vs: but of vertues, ſome be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, ſome moral. And theſe laſt may be learned, which the lawes do declare,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:19307:60"/> which puniſh not offenders for faultes that are already doone and paſt, being a thing impoſſible y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> that which is doone, ſhoulde bée vndoone againe: but they haue reſpecte to the time to come, and that he that hath once offended, offende no more, nor giue others occaſion to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend by his exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. And truly men wer very vnfortunate and in euil caſe, if ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing found a meanes whereby to tame wild beaſts, &amp; ſo to inſtruct the ſauadge diſpoſition of Beares, Lions, Wolfes, and to teache the little birdes to flie at their pleaſure, to returne home from the woods, and from their natural liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to come into theyr priſon and bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, to hoppe into the cage, of theyr owne accorde: they coulde not lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe deuyſe ſome art whereby to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter themſelues, and through labor and diligence to furniſhe, and adorne their owne mindes.</p>
               <p>Concerning that which they alledge out of <hi>Plato,</hi> of <hi>Lycurgus</hi> lawes: it maye bée aunſwered by a rule of the lawiers, which ſaith, that the abuſe of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19307:61"/> a thing ought not to take away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of the ſame. And <hi>Plato</hi> teacheth in that place, that diligent héede muſt be taken in a common wealth, that there bée no euill tatches nor vices brought into it, he diſputeth not whether a man ought to traueill or not. For what if a man profite the common wealth by hys tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyling as <hi>Timaeus</hi> dyd in <hi>Plato,</hi> and <hi>Plato</hi> hymſelfe with other innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of whom I haue made mention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore? Moreouer, who ſo peruſeth the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of <hi>Thucydides and xenophon,</hi> ſhall perceaue that the Lacedemoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans were verie ciuile men of béehaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, better liking of ſimple then ſubtile vertue, for the more parte borowing all their lawes of the <hi>Cretens</hi> by mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of <hi>Lycurgus.</hi> The <hi>Athenians,</hi> were very famous for varietie of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and learning, by meanes wherof were verie more diligent in ſearche of ſuch thinges as were apperteining to the weale publiques commoditie, and not leauing them vpon any abuſe. And moſte ſure it is, that aſwell the <hi>Lace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demonians</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:19307:61"/> as <hi>Athenians,</hi> borrowed their lawes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Egiptians.</hi> For <hi>Lycur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi> had bene in <hi>Aegipt:</hi> and the <hi>Egip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> tooke their lawes of the <hi>Hebrues</hi> if wée credit <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and it is well knowne, that they receaued their laws from God himſelfe. And God lykewiſe hath bin cauſe vnto manie that they ſhould take far iournies in hand, which wée haue declared in the chapter goynge next béefore: and Poets feigne, that <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi> was mooued to traueill by <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. Vliſses</hi> by <hi>Somnus,</hi> and other noble and valyent men by other Gods alſo, And <hi>Plato</hi> alſo doth the lyke. For in his booke <hi>De vniuerſitate</hi> tranſlated (as I ſuppoſe) by <hi>Tully,</hi> vnder the perſon of of the <hi>Egiptian</hi> Prieſte, hee ſharply re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proouethe the <hi>Greekes</hi> for neglectinge antiquitie, and for lingringe idlely at home, and calleth them Children, caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge them in the téeth with their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce. For to bée ignoraunt of ſuch thinges as are done béefore our tyme, whereof there are markes and tokens to this day remayning: what is it other
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:19307:62"/> (as the ſame <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith) then alwaies to be a childe.</p>
               <p>Laſt of all, the aſſertions whiche are alledged out of the Poetes of the happie lyfe, ought to bée no impediment or hindrance to traueillers, or what ſoeuer lyke thinge there is that may deterre a man from traueillynge, if hée bée other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe diſpoſed thereto of himſelfe. For <hi>Ouid</hi> had iuſte cauſe to complayne of Fortune, which hée abuſed, ſo that hée was againſt his wyll conſtrayned to go into baniſhment among the <hi>Getes,</hi> and not to traueill. And as for <hi>Claudianus,</hi> hée ſpake in the perſon of another, as it appeareth by the tytle of that Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gramme, which was an ould man and wealthy, and (as the frugalytie of the auncient time required) content with his owne eſtate, miſtykyng ſuperfluitie and varietie in all thinges. Moreouer both of them in thoſe their verſes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende the rurall and Cuntrey lyfe, preferringe it before all affaires &amp; dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings in the citie, and caſes of iudgment and buſineſſe in manie matters. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19307:62"/> it appeareth alſo by their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges, that the ſame men doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne traueill and experience gotten that way, but in ſundrie places deteſte ſluggiſh idleneſſe, eſpeciallye beinge e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident that they themſelues haue tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilled. For <hi>Horace</hi> beynge an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulian</hi> by birth, ſtudied Philoſophye at <hi>Athens:</hi> and <hi>Claudianus</hi> lyued vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> beinge borne in <hi>Alexandria</hi> a Citie in <hi>Egipt.</hi> And if wée ſhould graunt that they had an éeuell opinion of traueillinge, which indéede is otherwiſe: truely they had erred in this reſpect, ſince moſt euident it is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ther was yet neuer any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that atchiued any ſingular and notable thing vnleſſe hee had traueilled, as wee haue prooued by example of ſundrye in the former Chapter. For great and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table déedes, are not perfourmed but through wiſdome and ſkyll of thinges and men: whiche beinge not ſhut vp in ſome one corner of the Worlde, but diſperſed ouer the whole earth, it is no marueill, if to the attaynmente
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19307:63"/> thereof, it bée neceſſarye to traueill into ſundrye Landes, and ouer manie parts of the Worlde.</p>
               <p>The laſte Argument, and quite bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the matter, is alle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dged by ſome man of his owne experience or opinion againſte Traueile. For ſuch pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> are ſeldome commended, and manie tymes it engendreth Para<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>res, and ſtraunge poſitions, from whence ſpring Schiſmes and Hereſies in religion, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions in Commonwealthes, opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Philoſophie and Phyſick, with other miſcheiues and diſcommodities in other Artes and thinges, nouriſhyng a certen ſelfe loue in all men, and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time bringinge deſtruction vnto whole Commonwealthes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:19307:63"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>An Anſwere to the principall queſtion, with</hi> a notable commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>of Traueill therto</hi> annexed.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 9. <hi>Chapter</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw therfore it is no hard matter, to anſwer vnto the queſtion which wée mooued at the beginninge, and to determine, whether Traueill do a man more good or éeuell. For who ſo dily<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently weigheth what ſo euer wée haue ſayde hetherto: ſhall perceaue that in time of peace or War, it is moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto all that are deſirous to attain vnto vertue, or take any great matter in hand. Neither is their opinion and iudgement to bée liked of, which deſire rather to liue obſcurelye at home then with commendacion, as the Clowne in <hi>Claudianus</hi> and <hi>Polyphemus</hi> in <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere.</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:19307:64"/> And what other doo the Poetes meane by the Goddeſſes <hi>Calipſo</hi> and <hi>Circe,</hi> whom I haue me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>irned, then to reprehende the deſire of filthy luſtes and obſcure Idleneſſe, and to ſhew how <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> and whoſoeuer elſe is deſirous of praiſe and glorye: is nothinge de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted in idleneſſe and pleaſures, but by all meanes endeuoureth to attaine to vertu, although he muſt endure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> M. dangers. So haue <hi>Chriſtophorus Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumbarius,</hi> and <hi>Veſpuſius,</hi> aſſaid infinit perilles, who were the finders out of that part of the World whiche they call <hi>America.</hi> Howbeit they haue thereby purchaſed to themſelues euerlaſtinge memorie, leauing behind them to poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie the trueth of ſuch matter, whereof ther was neuer thought to be any ſuch. Theſe Philoſophers, Phiſicions, Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iers, Iuriſtes, Kinges, warriours, and Diuines, what praiſe haue thei not got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by traueillyng? That whoſo is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented with theſe: let hym adde more<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer vnto them ſundrye other excellent me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Franciſcus Senenſis</hi> reporteth
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:19307:64"/> to haue taken often and longe traueilles in hande, whiche they accompliſhed for vertue, and glory ſake. There haue bene ſome alſo, whom not ſo much their owne as others vertue, power, &amp; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, hath moued to traueill. Like as the holy Scripture witneſſeth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, and wiſdome of <hi>Salomon</hi> was ſo great: that the kinges of <hi>Tharſus,</hi> and Quéenes of <hi>Arabia,</hi> came thither to ſée and heare hym, and wée reade alſo, how certen noble men came from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt partes of France and Spaine, to <hi>Titus Liuius</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fownteine of eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, not mooued ſo muche with the power &amp; ſame of the Citie of <hi>Rome:</hi> as with the report of that one man. I my ſelfe haue ſéene a Moonke in <hi>Bononie,</hi> who in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilling ouer his owne cuntrey of <hi>Italy</hi> ſpent 9. whole yéeres: ſo ſurueyinge and diſcribing it, that no man coulde ſet it foorth more lyuely with pen, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe it w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> penſill, inſomuch that there is not the leaſt thing left out vntouched And yet he was but a Monk, whoſe life ought to be ſolitarie, &amp; as <hi>Gratian</hi> ſaith,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:19307:65"/> none vnles it bée in Cloiſter, as nether the Fiſhes out of the Water.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, neither hypocriſie, nor any holyneſſe of lyfe, forbiddeth a man to Traueill, ſo that hée doe it to any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt vſe, or commoditie, redoundinge to himſelfe or others. Neither are they to bée lyked of, who if they would: might traueill, but had rather liue at home lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinge an obſcure lyfe, then to wynne praiſe by traueilyng. For ſuch not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, offend againſt their friends, and the whole commonwealth: but alſo againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. For it is the peculier nature of mankind to be euermore deſirous of knowlege, and neuer to bée contented w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one thing only, whether that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge come by hearinge or ſéeinge, for man hath theſe ſences whereby he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth ſkill, as ſayth <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> But as <hi>Horace</hi> witneſſeth:</p>
               <l>The things we heare, les cauſe the minde and ſences to ariſe:</l>
               <l>Then doe the thinges in preſence whiche are ſubiect to the eies.</l>
               <p>Yea they are of greater force and effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacie,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19307:65"/> and are more firmely reteyned in memorie which wée ſe before our eies: then the report or only heareſay of any thinge, although there come of it no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, no pleaſure, nor honeſtye. And I haue ſhewed that by traueilynge there enſueth verie great commoditie in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie kind of lyfe, and as for the honeſtie thereof: no man can doubt, being enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by many examples. And if wée meaſure honeſtie by paines, not raſhly but vpon iuſt cauſe taken in hand: then truely traueill, of whiche wée intreat in this place, ſhall yéeld to none. For tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueillers are enforced to abyde all labors and ſuſteine al troubles. Moreouer, like as theſe men whiche may and ought to traueill and yet doo not traueill, commit a ſhamefull deede: ſo they that are giuen to traueilling, perfourme a moſt honeſt exployt. For theſe doo rightly vſe their féet, the other abuſe them. For nature &amp; God the maker of all thinge, hath not giuen vs féete for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tent wee ſhoulde walke vp and downe in our owne Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or Cuntrey only, but that if occaſion
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:19307:66"/> ſerue wée ſhuld alſo go ſée and frequent forreine nacions alſo: for elſe doubtleſſe God and Nature woulde haue ſhut vp the wayes and forbidden the paſſedge to ſtraunge Cuntries. And what can be more delectable, then to béeholde the things wherof thou haſt read ſumthing or heard of other, and againe to béeholde in minde and contemplatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe things which thou haſt ſomtime ſéene, and to applie them to thy vſe. Wherein I wyl ſpeake nothinge of the profite or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie? For it much aueileth vnto the getting of perfect and ſownd know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or learninge of any Art, to trauell vnto ſuch places where ſuch Artes doe moſt flouriſh, and are faithfully taught. So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they deſerue none excuſe, whoſe lyfe is only to think, as <hi>Cicero</hi> writeth of certen Philoſophers, and ſuch as get all their wiſdome at home, being much affeard leſt if they traueilled: the ſkie woulde fall on their heades, or the earth ſinke vnder them: when as they might learne that which they ſéeke for, better and with greater profite of ſtraungers,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:19307:66"/> and alliens, eſpeciallye if they haue money to beare their charges abroade as well as at home. And it hapneth manie times, that they that kéepe themſelues at home vpon this perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that there is no lyfe pleaſant out of a mans owne Cuntrey, or elſe do feare that by change of place they ſhoulde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo change their maners: let them then be wyfe only in theyr owne conceites, and contempne others in reſpecte of themſelues, beynge puffed vp with an opinion of knowledge, a thinge ſo éeuell, that a more woorſe or more daungerous in all the Worlde can bée none deuiſed.</p>
               <l>Eche Land vnto a valient man his cuntrey is, right ſo</l>
               <l>As is eche ſea vnto the ſellie fish where ere shee go.</l>
               <p>A man ſhall euerie where finde ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinge that hee may learne, and that another time may doe hym good. Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely the knowledge &amp; ſearch of forrein Realmes, hath alwaies bin accompted
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:19307:67"/> ſo pleaſant profitable and glorious that certen it is, that many for none other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe then a loue and deſire thereof, and that they might ſée experience of things haue forſaken their natiue Cuntreys, deare Parentes, Wiues, Children, Freindes, and that more is, leauynge the reguarde of their owne health, haue ſumtimes vndertake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very far <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ies with great difficultie, perill, care, and anguiſhe.</p>
               <p>Since therefore, traueill is honeſte, pleaſant, profitable, and commodious: what man withée aſhamed to take it in hand, that is prouided, and méet thereto and that by example of ſo many Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, kings, wiſemen, warriours, and other worthy perſonages that haue tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueilled, to ſée ſtraunge and far Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, &amp; to wander wide abroad? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by are knowne the peculyar behauiors of euery cuntrey, their diſpoſition, diet, appareill, maner of buildinge, ſituation of places, tillage, moreouer Lawes, all doctrines &amp; opinious, holy and profane, and finally the nature of all things. But
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:19307:67"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> before admoniſhed: it beh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him that ſhal doſe, to be wary, and to expreſſe the perſon of <hi>Vliſses</hi> or <hi>Ane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as:</hi> or if hée cannot ſo doo, haue <hi>Achates</hi> and <hi>Neſtors</hi> with him, that is to ſay, faithfull and louing companions, whoſe counſel hée may follow, liue wel and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne ſafe into his cuntrey: vnto which wée all are bound, and borne, and which wée may and ought alſo to gouerne and that with praiſe, after the knowledge and experience of ſo many thinges: ſo that wee follow godlyneſſe, enſue vert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and neuer waxe wéerie, whatſoeuer paines or difficultie of perils affault vs.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>Thus endeth the firſt Booke.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <pb n="118" facs="tcp:19307:68"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The ſecond Booke o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Traueiller of Ierome</hi> Turler, of compre hending <hi>an excellent deſcription</hi> of the moſte delicious Realme of <hi>Naples.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 1. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the firſte Booke I</hi> haue anſwered to the queſtion which was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the beginning by ſuche preceptes as I haue thought ſufficient towardes the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayninge of a well ordred, happie, and proſperous traueill. Whiche if they bee dilligently obſerued and in ſuch or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der as wee haue delyuered them doe ſhewe that what ſoeuer ſtraunge or dangerous accide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts befall vs in traueil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, it chaunceth not ſo much by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane negligence, as it is to bee aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnto to the prouidence of eternall
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:19307:68"/> God For the condicion of our lyfe is ſuche, that it is expoſed, and lyeth open vnto infinite miſeries, and there was yet neuer man bleſſed in all reſpectes, or that could eſcape death. Whereby all changes and chaunces of Fortune, are more indifferently to be borne, and wee muſt ſuppoſe that nothinge can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall vnto vs, that hath not alſo hapned vnto others. And for as much as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples bringe lyght to preceptes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter more euide. it, as the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wier ſayth: I thinke it worthe the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueill, to declare that by ſome example, whiche I admoniſhed generally to bée conſidered in all traueill. Whiche thinge that I ſhoulde more wyllyngly accompliſhe, partlye the remembrance of ſuche thinges as ether I my ſelfe haue ſéene in ſundrie places, or haue heard of others, hath mooued mee part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the very maieſtie of Antiquitie and knowledge, whiche is woont of it ſelfe to delight, and is exceptable vnto all men. Beeſides the profite which it bringeth vnto the expoſition of good Aucthours,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:19307:69"/> whether wée ſpeake of Poetrie, or of Hiſtories. Wherfore I meane to touch in this ſecond B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke ſuch thinges as are in the Realme of <hi>Naples</hi> worthy to bee ſéene, ſince there is ſcarce no other place in all Chriſtendome, in my opinion, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within the compaſſe of <hi>Europe,</hi> for holſomneſſe of aire, ſituation, pleaſant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, abundance, or ciuilitie, match vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it. Moreouer it is very famous by the writinges of excellent Aucthours, <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gill,</hi> and <hi>Liuie:</hi> beſides that, perhaps I think I may doe pleaſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ereby vnto them that meane heareafter themſeues to traueill in that part of <hi>Italie.</hi> For when they ſhal haue read this diſcourſe being put in minde they may more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitely, and dylygently ſearche eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thinge, and they ſhall finde them to bee ſoe. Howbeit I purpoſe not by this demonſtration, as it were by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moſt certen diſcription of the place, to ſet foorth at full the whole Countrey of <hi>Naples,</hi> which by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proper name is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Happy Campania,</hi> for that belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the dutie of a Coſmographer:
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:19307:69"/> but ſuch thinges will I note onely, as taſt of Antiquitie, and are woorthie ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myration aboue the reſt. Wherefore I will not deuide them into anye pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyſe order of recytall, but for the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt renuyng of the aunciente re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of them, I will declare them in ſuche order as I ſawe them, without all gloſe of woordes, or falſefy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the trueth in anye thing: both for that it behooueth the diſputation of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and trueth to bée ſimple, and alſo the manner of telling requireth the ſame, and trueth is the foundation of an Hiſtorie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:19307:70"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>Portus Baianus, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called La Peſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Mirabile,</hi> A wonderfull Fiſheponde.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 2. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen therfore wée had taken our iourney, comming out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs and lybertie of <hi>Rome,</hi> and were approched vnto the fixte ſtone from the Citie of <hi>Naples:</hi> wee ſawe a place whiche the <hi>Italians</hi> tearme <hi>La Peſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Mirabile,</hi> wee paſſed throughe an hugie and waſte place into a greate buildyng, long, foureſquare, and as a man ſhoulde ſay made vault wiſe, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblyng the ſhewe of a Churche. Longewyſe it contayned foure cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of ſquare Pillers, whereby the Archeis were borne vp, euery courſe conteyning. xij. Pillers, ſo that in all
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:19307:70"/> there were in number. xlviii. of diuerſe bygneſſe, and fourme. Which when it ſeemed ſtraunge vnto thoſe that bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>héelde theſe antiquities with mée: this is no ſtraunge thinge, quod I, ſince moſt graue authours haue writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that the Temple of <hi>Diana</hi> at <hi>Epheſus</hi> had in it Cxxiii. Pyllers, whereof euery one was lx. foote longe. Then wée ſtepte downe three ſteppes on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye ſyde. But there were no wyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes nor tooken of any, howbeit the Sunne ſhyned in in ſundrye places by chinkes and riftes, otherwyſe the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng was whole and ſounde enoughe. So that a man cannot well gheſſe, to what purpoſe it was in olde time buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, muchleſſe pronounce any certen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thereof. Some are of opinion that it was a fiſheponde, whyche they gather bothe by the lykelyhoode of the place, and alſo out of <hi>Plinie,</hi> who wryteth, that <hi>Hortenſius</hi> the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour had a Ponde for Lampreis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Bauli</hi> in the coaſt of <hi>Baie,</hi> of whych hys Lampreis, hée loued one ſo
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:19307:71"/> entirely: that as it is reported, hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wepte for her when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hee was deade, <hi>Blondus</hi> iudgeth that this place was <hi>Lucullus</hi> houſe. Others affirme that <hi>Antonia</hi> wyſe to <hi>Druſus</hi> buylded that place to kéepe Lampreis in. And in what pryce fiſhepondes, and chiefely of Lampreis were had in olde tyme: maye well bée gathered out of appr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued wryters, wherein this increaſed my coniecture, that vppon that moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne or rather hill, thoſe thinges are yet to bee ſéene which are reade in <hi>Plinie</hi> where hée ſayth: that the people in olde tyme as <hi>Lucullus</hi> and <hi>Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſius,</hi> beſtowed muche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> channelles through Hilles and Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, to bring in the Sea.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:19307:71"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>Centum Cellae, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called Cento Camerelle,</hi> an hundred Chambers.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 3. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen wée were departed forthe of this hugie and waſte mole and building: we came to <hi>Alle Cento ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merelle,</hi> lying directly oueragainſt the other, beyng ſo called for that it contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth nothing but Chambers and Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, leadyng one to another. At this preſent it is ſituate vppon a Hill, but whether it were ſo in olde tyme or not. I doubt, by reaſon of downefalles and valtes, whereof ſome and deuided from the reſidew of the buildyng, whereby it ſhould ſéeme that it had bin ſumtime <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yder and trimmer. When we were entred into theſe ruines, wée came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain vnto a great building fourſquare, ſtanding vpon foureſquare pillers, and
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:19307:72"/> beyng of a foureſquare forme: nears vnto one of which pillers there was a hole, into which our hoſte that conduc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs to the ſighte of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe antiquities, deſcended to receaue vs, and helpe vs as wée went downe. Then came wée into a great wyde place full of Celles and little rowmes, euerie one foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquare, but ſome bygger then other. From thence there laye open a waye to other wyde places and Celles, for the whole buildyng was deuided by ſundrye crookes and turnynges. And it was ſo intricate and diffuſe, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the lykeneſſe of the Celles, that ſome not without cauſe iudged that it had béene ſometyme a <hi>Labyrinthe,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge whom is <hi>Antonius de Ruſsis</hi> a <hi>Calabrian,</hi> whom I ſuppoſe rather to haue thoughte ſo in reſpecte of the fourme, then for anye other circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances. <hi>Leander</hi> of <hi>Bononie,</hi> thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that it was a Ceſterne, or place wherein water was kepte in the olde tyme. But I coulde ſée no tooken or argument whereby I mighte coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:19307:72"/> the vſe thereof, no ſignes of hookes or i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes in the Celle doores, which are narowe and lowe, there were no win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes any where, nor anye thinge in ſtéede of them. Within euery place gliſtered white with plaiſter of <hi>Paris,</hi> and in ſundrye places the earthe lay to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in heapes the hight of halfe a cubit, as in <hi>Sibylles</hi> den, whereof wée will ſpeake hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ <hi>Mons Canita, the</hi> Hill <hi>Canita.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 4. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THus leauyng the forenamed place, wee entred into a boate which wée had there in a redineſſe for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> purpoſe &amp; wée ſhared alonge by an hill which the <hi>Italians</hi> terme <hi>Canita,</hi> neare vnto which vpon a rocke lying not far of as big as the Hill, whyche notwythſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge was deuided from it: ſtoode a caſtle wonderfull ſtrangely builded, of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:19307:73"/> a rare kynde of ſituation, at the foote whereof were ſéene verie ample and large buildinges, but for the more part fallen downe wyth age. The reporte goeth that <hi>Tullia</hi> ſometime dwelte in the ſame place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Lacus Auerni, the</hi> lake <hi>Auernus.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 5. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FRom thence wée arriued at the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian</hi> ſhoare, and goyng out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boate, wée walked along the ruines &amp; down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falles of houſes, which were there thick to bée ſéene, ouergrowne wyth bram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and bryars, vnto the Laque <hi>Auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi> The ſame lyeth, as it were, in a blynde corner out of the way, enuiro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned rounde wyth certeine ridges and bankes rather then hilles, béeynge in fourme perfecte roun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e as any circles, wherin Maryners ſay, can bée founde no bottome. It was ſo called by reaſon
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:19307:73"/> of a moſt ſtronge and lothſome ſmell of exhalations, riſinge out of it, and is moſt pernicious vnto birdes, as <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gill</hi> hath noted, ſaying:</p>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then when againſt Auerna mouth they came, that ſtinking lake,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>They lift themſelues aloft. &amp;c.</hi> And ſhortly after he addeth,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Dungeon darke there is that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore wide open gapes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Full rough of rockie ſtones, and loth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome lake there flowes about:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Therouer dare no birde attempt to flie, for deadly doubt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such poiſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> breath out breaks, &amp; through the throat with ſtifling ſtink,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Such ſmolthring vapour ſmokes, and vp to ſkies is borne from brinke.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wherby the Greekes by name Auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na mouth that place do call.</hi>
               </l>
               <p>Vpon the hilles lying thereby, ſtand certein buildinges almoſt of our tyme faire, and pleaſant, but they are almoſt hoat Bathes. <hi>Plinie</hi> hath noted that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne of <hi>Cimmerij</hi> ſtoode néere to this Laque, whoſe labour was to dig Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:19307:74"/> out of caues and mines in the earth and neuer to bée ſéene of the Sunne, as witneſſeth <hi>Homer:</hi> I dare not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſely anouch that the ruines which are ſéene to remaine vpon thys ſhoare are anye parte of that, althoughe no man doubteth, but that ſomtime there ſtoode a towne in that place. There is neare to <hi>Auernus,</hi> and as <hi>Virgill</hi> ſayeth, at the left hand of thoſe ruines neare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lake:</p>
               <l>A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue there is cut out in rocke, euen through the Temple walles'</l>
               <l>Both huge and broade at mouth, a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred vautes, a hundred doores,</l>
               <l>A hundred roarings ſound, when Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byls anſweres beates the floores.</l>
               <p>We muſt goe downe to the foote of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hill, whereas there is a darke entraunce into the caue, into which we went with Torchelight, following our guid. The entraunce at the firſt was broade and high enough, waxing afterward naro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer &amp; narower, and at length openeth it ſelfe into a plaine in length almoſt lx. paces, &amp;. x. in breadth. From the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce there
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:19307:74"/> was a way which lead into certein cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, ſtraunge to beholde, and altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnlike to thoſe hundred aboue me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioned. For they be larger, and higher. Moreouer they ſtand in another order, &amp; they differ in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> inequalitie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> floores one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, the goings in are ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time vphill ſometime downe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> walles are foule &amp; defaced with age, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> all the place is lothſom, to behold. Amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theſe celles or chambers, there is one wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ſay, <hi>Sibilla</hi> dwelt, in form four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquare ſomtime adorned with point de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe &amp; checker worke like to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple of <hi>Bacchus</hi> nigh <hi>Rome.</hi> And althoughe the carued pieces of the ſtories be al ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away for the more part, by ſuch as haue traueyled thither vppon deſire to knowe and ſee antiquities: notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng are ſéene there in ſundry pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces certeine tookens and monumentes of the auncient furniture, which argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath mooued ſome to thinke, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>billa</hi> dwelt there, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hanſomſt of all the other and neareſt vnto <hi>Auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> ioyning to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other Celles, hauing but one doore only. Directly ouer agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:19307:75"/> the doore is an Arch in the wall like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a chimney, &amp; yet there could be none in that place. Moreouer, foorthe of this chamber wée go into another parlour, or as it were into ſome hall, in breadth viij. paces, and in length about. xxij. In which finding ſuch a number of flinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or Rattelmiſe that they ſtucke in heapes vpon the walles, and by reaſon of the torchlight much troubled vs: we were enforced to retire, and to go foorth through the ſame Celles or chambers that wee came in at. It is ſtraunge to heare, howe much thoſe Celles do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found the iudgement of the beholders, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a man is not able to conceaue or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine any forme or repreſentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this building in his minde. In ſome places you ſhall finde in them, middle walles, open aboue and not cloſed to the rough, and within ſome of them ſomewhere, there is found earth caſt vp on a heape, like as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hundred Celles wherof I ſpake before. I noted alſo, howe this way where as we entred in into theſe celles, and chambers, was but lately
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:19307:75"/> found out, yet could I ſée none other y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> had bin vſed before, and al theſe Celles were builded in the midſt of the hill, &amp; haue no light from heauen. Wherefore we could not gheſſe by any coniecture, or by any arguments, what all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding had bin heretofore, or to what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it was firſt deuiſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ <hi>Ciceroes Academie,</hi> Village, and hoat Bathes.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 6. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WIthout the compaſſe of theſe hils, whiche enuiron the place called <hi>Auernus</hi> rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d about, towards <hi>Puteoli,</hi> there ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth <hi>Tullies Academie,</hi> which was ſometime his village, a place for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> galleries &amp; thicknes of ſhadowed wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes very famous, where nowe are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten hoat Bathes, called by name of <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceroes</hi> Bathes. Theſe Bathes béegan firſt toſpring vp after his death, in the dayes of one <hi>Antiſtius</hi> which was hys
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:19307:76"/> ſucceſſour in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame vilage: which <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi> one who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Tullie</hi> had made frée hath celebrated in verſes in the honor of his maiſter, as <hi>Plinie</hi> writeth. The <hi>Itali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> call that place <hi>Ibagni di Tritoli.</hi> The ſituation of them is moſt pleaſant and at the foote of the hill ſtand certeyn houſes, ſome faierer then other, builded but lowe and after a ſimple maner, and for the more part forlorne. Howbeit in the moneth of May they bée all inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, bycauſe at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of the yéere there reſort great multitudes of peoples vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Baines, ſome to preſerue, ſome to recouer health, being very holſome and aueilable thereto by reaſon of the varietie of Metalles in them, as <hi>Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, Nitre, Salt,</hi> and <hi>Bitumen,</hi> in which reſpect <hi>Plinie</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendeth them, adding moreouer that ſome of them do much good only by their vapour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:19307:76"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>Cumae, The Citie Cumae.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 7. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CVmae</hi> ſtandeth welnigh at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thirde ſtone from theſe Bathes, of which Citie the prouerbe is truely verified, <hi>Cuma hath bin.</hi> For of ſo great and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowmed a Citie as this hath bin, there remaineth now almoſt nothing, beſides a fewe ruines and downfalles, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a few poore fiſherme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are now dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, with certeine Monumentes very auncient, and worthy to bée conſidered, eſpecially in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place which they tearme <hi>Locauallo.</hi> There is alſo yet remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning there, a Triumphant Ark, whole and ſound, and the Temple of <hi>Apollo,</hi> wherof <hi>Virgill</hi> writeth in this maner.</p>
               <l>But good Aeneas to Apollos Church, and temple towers,</l>
               <l>Hee went to ſeeke the ſecrete caue of sibyls dread full howers &amp;c.</l>
               <p>
                  <hi>Liuius</hi> writeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this citie was builded by the <hi>Cumaei,</hi> a people of <hi>Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> &amp; by
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:19307:77"/> the <hi>Chalcidenſes. Strabo</hi> commendeth it not ſo much for the time wherein it was builded, or for thoſe that built it as he doth for the monuments &amp; antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. For he writeth, how that for their ſumptuouſnes &amp; ſtore thereof, they ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed al the other Cities of <hi>Italy</hi> So y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is leſſe falſe which <hi>Blo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dus</hi> reporteth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in no place in all <hi>Europe</hi> are ſo many downfals &amp; ruines of moſt ſumptuous buildings to be ſéene <hi>(Rome</hi> onely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) as are betwéene <hi>Cuma</hi> &amp; <hi>Baias:</hi> being no doubt therof, but that this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie hath bin in foretimes moſt wealthy and populous. For it is certein, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Naples</hi> called in old time <hi>Parthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nope,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The olde ame of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aples,</hi> was <hi>arthenope.</hi>
                  </note> tooke beginning of that: the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants being ſent from <hi>Cuma</hi> thither. Which afterward was ouerthrown by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſam people of <hi>Cuma,</hi> bicauſe thei ſaw y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wealth therof dayly increaſe. Which being done, ſome write y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there befell a fore plague of peſtilence throughout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole territory and confines of <hi>Cuma,</hi> wherof whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there was no end neyther could y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inhabitantes finde any remedie
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:19307:77"/> to driue away that miſchiefe: report go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that they aſked counſel of the Oria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, which anſwered, that <hi>Naples</hi> was the cauſe of that plague, and that it ſhould neuer ceaſe vnleſſe they buylded that citie agayne, and reſtored it to the former ſtate. Whiche when they had done: the plague immediatly ceaſed, but the Citie afterwarde beinge troubled with ſedition of the people, and manye Earthquakes, loſt the naturall ſtrength like an olde mother, leauing behinde her a daughter, to wit, the Citie of <hi>Naples,</hi> which indéede lyueth and flouriſhe that this day.</p>
               <p>Now were wée come to the Hauen <hi>Baianum,</hi> which was made by <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa,</hi> as <hi>Dion Caſsius</hi> writeth, where wée forſooke our Boat, and prepared to ſayle to <hi>Puteoli.</hi> And as we were ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng, wée behéelde alonge in our courſe ſundry high Hilles and Mountaynes, at the féete of whiche were continuall rankes of downe fallen Houſes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we might eaſly coniecture that there ſtoode ſome great Towne in ould time,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:19307:78"/> but that it was caſt downe by Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaks that often times are ſéene there, and for that cauſe were forſaken of the inhabitants. For ther appéere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> expres tokens of a waſted citie or towne now all ouer growne with buſhes &amp; briers, and a few houſes are inhabited by pore Mariners and Fiſhermen, becauſe the harbor is indifferent ſafe. Which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I béeheld: it came into my minde what <hi>Seruius Sulpitius</hi> wrate vnto <hi>Cicero</hi> in a certen place, how when hée retourned vpon a time out of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and was ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge from <hi>Aegina</hi> towardes <hi>Megara,</hi> hée was incompaſſed round about (as he ſayde) with carcaſes of townes. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs there lay the remnauntes of the Citie whereof wée ſpake euen now, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind vs <hi>Cuma,</hi> on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one ſide <hi>Baiae,</hi> and on the other <hi>Puteoli</hi> was not farre of, which townes hauing bin in ould times moſt flouriſhing, now they lie aground flat before our eies. Wherfore I fel into wondring at the ſtate and fortune of all worldly thinges, and thus I thought within my ſelf, good Lord, what ſhal on
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:19307:78"/> day become of our cuntreis whiche are neither ſo pleaſant, nether ſo well tilled, nether ſo wealthy, nether ſo famous as theſe haue bin in times paſt? &amp; therefore doubtles thei ſhal y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſooner decay. I called to minde alſo that I had ſéene beefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge the <hi>Hollenders</hi> in the <hi>German</hi> Ocean, and in the Ilandes of <hi>Selande,</hi> that there are certen whole villages and townes drowned, whereof the ſléeples, towers, and higheſt buildings, ſtand vp and are ſéene in the Sea, like as they were certen wachtowers &amp; ſpying pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, an euident argument of the frailtie of earthly things, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is nothing ſtable or permanent in this life. In lyke ſort the Sea carried away the cities of <hi>Pyrrha</hi> and <hi>Antiſſa</hi> about <hi>Meotis,</hi> and lykewiſe <hi>Elice</hi> &amp; <hi>Buris</hi> in the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> boſome, called <hi>Sinus Corinthiacus,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tokens wherof apeare aboue the water at this day as <hi>Plinie</hi> writeth: &amp; the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Ouid</hi> are well knowne, where he writeth of them ſaying.</p>
               <l>If yee goe to ſeeke for Helicee</l>
               <l>And Burie which were cities of Achaia you shal ſee</l>
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:19307:79"/>
               <l> Them hidden vnder water, and the Shipmen yet do show:</l>
               <l>The walles and Steeples of the to w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es drownd vnder as they row.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>Baines.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> 8 <hi>Chapter</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THus forſakinge theſe downefalles, followinge the Coaſt alonge in the Shoare of thoſe hilles, continually kée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng on our courſe: wée came to a hyll where agayne were Baynes. The ſame beynge doubtleſſe burninge heat within, yet it reſembleth no ſuch things in apparance. At the firſt entrance we came into a large and high chamber, whoſe wals and vault of the gate were ſumtime finely trimmed with checke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red poynct deuiſe, which the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>tes that yet remain do ſufficiently witnes. The entrance into this chamber is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different wide, and within by the ſide of ech wall ſtand bedſtedes made of ſtone
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:19307:79"/> walled about, whereon are Beddes and Pyllowes caſte, where they that haue waſhed themſelues may lye downe and take their reſt. Moreouer, at the fyrſte comming in, ſtande two Lauers foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquare, two foote déepe, directlye ouer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Baynes, which ar very tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, retayning no ſtrong ſmell at all, neither of Brimſtone or any thing elſe, but conſiſting only of <hi>Niter</hi> and <hi>Alume.</hi> But the hole where out the water iſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth is wide and large, and ſo hanſomely hollowed: that many may waſh them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in it together, but the farther that a man goeth into it, the hotter is the water. They ſay that theſe Baynes are verie healthſome, béeſids y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they be alſo paſſing pleaſant, by reaſon of the Sea which is nigh at hand, whoſe waues in toſſinge and woorkynge, doo engender a delectable noyſe and murmuringe. Without the Caue there ſtandeth Lad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conteininge about twenty ſtales, by whiche wée aſcend ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opewiſe into Heat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, commonly tearmed a ſweatynge Houſe. The way which lyeth open in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:19307:80"/> it is high enough for any man, made lyke the entrance of a Den, but ſcarce wide enough receiuinge into it the light at certen Chinkes and cre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſes, ſo that a man may goe in a pretie way with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Torch or fire light. Then come we vnto two wayes, whereof that whiche lyeth on the left hand leadeth to a great many of Bedſtéedes ſtonewalled about ſeruing to the purpoſe of the aboue na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſtretchinge ouer all the ſide of the hyll, and endinge at certen broken and cragged places of the ſame. The other inclineth towards the hart of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hill, and it is lyke enough that it endeth in the moſt hotteſt and burninge hollow caues thereof. Into whiche wée entred with Torche light, and went ſo far vntill we coulde abide to goo no farther for heate. And at our firſt entrance wée felt onely a litle warmth, and procéedinge a litle farther wee felte a great heate, whiche alwayes ſtriking vpwarde: did woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully annoy our heades, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more, the farther wée went, ſo that wee were ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times enforced for a while to créep on
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:19307:80"/> the ground. Thus being almoſt milted with ſweat, although wée had put of all our clothes beefore, and our Torche beinge diſſolued with heate: wée were conſtrained to tourne back agayne, and comminge foorth the ſame way that wée went in, wee waſhed our ſelues in the bathes whiche were in the lower<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt part of the Hill, whereof we ſpake a litle before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Well or Fowntaine in the Sea, and the</hi> way called <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellana.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> 9. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOreouer, betwéene this place and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citi <hi>Puteoli</hi> (now called <hi>Pozolo)</hi> we ſaw two other things worth the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. The one is a fowntaine or well in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſea, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> way which they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cal <hi>Attellana.</hi> Ther ariſeth out of the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:19307:81"/> Sea a paſſing running cléere, and ſwéet Fowntayne of freſh water, pleaſant in taſte two foote déepe, as big as a mans head. I ſuppoſe the cauſes thereof are certen ſecret paſſages vnder the ground, which conueie the water thyther from the ſhoare adioining, where it breaketh foorth. Of the ſame opinion is <hi>Lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Bononienſis</hi> a Moonke very well learned, who hath deſcribed <hi>Italy,</hi> no man more dilligently in my iudgment. Howbeit it mai be, that when this place was the maine land: the Inhabitantes had conueied the freſh water by conduit pipes through the ruines and Aſhes of the citie <hi>Puteoli,</hi> which thei vſed in ſtéed of a Well or Fowntayne, and that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward the ſea brake in and ouerflow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all that land, wheras y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſpring yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayneth. It yéeldeth foorth water ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly, that a man may diſcerne the ſtreame thereof agreat way runninge along, from the ſea water, being cleerer &amp; more lyke to wel water. But I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that I haue ſéene the lyke of this béefore at <hi>Dordracu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> a Towne in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:19307:81" rendition="simple:additions"/> where the riuer <hi>Moſa</hi> called the Maze (vnleſſe I bee deceaued) floweth with no leſſe force into the <hi>Germane</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceane in a ſtreame almoſte thrée Pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches or Poles broade. <hi>Plinie</hi> hath noted that in the ſhoare <hi>Baian,</hi> in ſome places there riſeth hoat runninge water out of the Sea, whereof I am able to ſaye nothing.</p>
               <p>And as touchinge the way called <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellana,</hi> you muſt vnderſtande, that the ſame on both ſides lyeth thick of Cotta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and ſmall houſes fallen downe, the fourme of which are ſome rounde, ſome foureſquare: and in theſe litle tabernes, are certen vautes and arches, in whiche are ſéene Coffins and Pottes with the bones and aſhes of dead men in them, whereby wée coniectured that the ſame was apointed in ould time for a place of buriall. Howbeit, they whiche dwell neare vnto it, ſay that it was builded for a place to kéepe wares in to bée ſoulde, and vpon that perſwaſion they call it in the vulgare toongue, <hi>Il mercato di Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bato.</hi> Sure it is, that in the ould time
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:19307:82"/> the bodies of dead men were w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nte to be brent, and the aſhes layd vp in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts. This is moreouer to bee wondered at that one of our companions tooke out of one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pots a péece of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſkull of a mans heade of a wonderful thicknes. For this is an argument, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> not only the aſhes of dead men were incloſed in theſe pottes: but alſo the bones after that the fleſhe was conſumed away in the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fines. This piece of ſkull, at the firſt was hard to féele to, but ſo ſoone as it had lien a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while in the open aier it waxed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te, and at length fell to ponder. But let vs now leane the dead, and not fight with bones.</p>
               <p>Beefore wée came to <hi>Puteoli,</hi> wee chaunced to light vpon them that make Alume. Theſe he winge litle ſtones out of the hilles harde by, burne them in a Kill, then layinge them on heapes the ſpace of certen dayes: caſt water vpon them whith they draw out of Pittes, that they may ſake in it after the mai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er of lime, and fall the more eaſely into ponder. Then make they lye of theſe
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:19307:82"/> aſhes, whiche they powre into tubbes and veſſels of woode, and there gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to an hardineſſe in the toppe about the brimme of the veſſell, ſticking faſte and congeling to the ſides after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of yſe: then gather they it out with certen inſtruments made for the nonce, &amp; kéepe it to their vſe. Not far from that place are certen hoat Baines, which the <hi>Italians</hi> tearme <hi>Ibagni di agnano,</hi> which although they haue very ſimple and lowe cottagies: notwithſtandinge they are much commended for holſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and ſure it is, that the <hi>Vicere</hi> of <hi>Naples,</hi> with all the reſidue of the nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of that Realme, doo vſe cuſtomably once euery yéere at the Spring time, to goe thither. In the ſame hilles and ſhore nere vnto theſe baines, is a place which the <hi>Italians</hi> call <hi>La grotta del can,</hi> wee may very well turne it Dogges Den, a Caue repleniſhed with filthye deadlye aire, wherein no lyuinge thinge may abide aliue. The deapth thereof is eight or nine foote, the breadeth aboute ſixe and reacheth into the Hyll not
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:19307:83"/> paſte foure paces longe, and bendeth downe ſumwhat ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>opewiſe, breathinge foorth an hoat and moiſte breath, whiche a man may ſoone perceaue by puttinge in his hand. It tooke the name hereof in that ſuch as come thither for trials ſake are woont to thruſt in ſome Dog: whom when they drawe foorth, immediatelye for dead: preſently they caſt ſome of the water of the lake there by vpon hym, and ſo reſtore him to his former cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and lyfe agayne. We, beſids a dog, threw in many very great frogs, which becauſe they leaped not foorth preſently agayne, were killed with that peſtilent breath. <hi>Plinie</hi> ſaith, that the territorie of <hi>Sueſſum</hi> and <hi>Puteoli,</hi> are certen Caues and hollow places vnder ground, which they call <hi>Spiracula,</hi> breathing places, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers terme them <hi>Cheroneae</hi> pits, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halynge foorth a mortall and deadly ſpirite, whereof this may be one.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:19307:83"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Forum Vulcani. Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canes Market</hi> place.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 10. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOt farre from this place is ſéene a great plain, of figure rounde, al ye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe with Brimſtone, hauinge alſo a peculier lake belonging vnto it which is not great. And for as much as the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of that ground conſiſteth of mere Sulfur or Brimſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which being ſet on fire, boyleth vp, therefore <hi>Strabo</hi> calleth that place <hi>Vulcanes</hi> Court: others haue tearmed it the féeld of <hi>Phlegrus,</hi> as doth <hi>Virgill.</hi> Neere to the lake are ſeene a fewe litle Cottages made of boughes, and néere to them are Killes wherein they boyle Brimſton. From theſe who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo walketh alonge by the ſmall guttes, (for they deſerue ſcarce to bée called by the name of Lakes) hée ſhall perceiue that they ſend foorth a very thick ſmoke, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the water boileth very hoat. The
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:19307:84"/> report goeth, and it is lyke enough to be true, that if a man caſt any lyuing thing into them, and after a litle while pluck it foorth agayne, hée ſhall finde nothinge left but bare bones: the lyke they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port alſo of egges, I wot not what. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute theſe ſmall guttes, whereof wee nowe ſpeake, are founde litle wodden croſſes innuerable, which ſome bold and ventrous fellowes haue ſtucke into the brinks, as it were, for certen bowndes and tokens, after the maner of <hi>Hercules</hi> pillers, for as much as the paſſedge vnto them is very daungerous. For whiche way ſoeuer you goe, you may perceiue by the ſownd that the ground is hollow vnderneth, out of whiche ſomtimes ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly breake vp flames of Brimſtone, and pay home theſe venterous fellowes with deſerued puniſhment for their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. For why, the vppermoſt part of the ground is light, and drie, neither may a man walk ouer eueri part of it. I know it well that <hi>Plinie</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> writer of the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral hiſtorie, is ſuſpected of many to haue intermedled lies with trueth, after the
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:19307:84"/> maner of the Grecians. Howbeit wee our ſelues haue ſéene theſe things alſo, and therfore credit him the rather when hée writeth of theſe things, or of ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lyke. For it is moſt true which hée ſaith very woorthely in ſome place, that nature which is diffuſed throughout all earthlye thinges, breaketh foorth often ſhewinge it ſelfe diuerſlye, as it were ſome God, or celeſtiall power.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>Puteoli, the Citie of Pozolo.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> 11. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHen from this large and lowe plaine we returne vnto the Hill, you ſhall ſee at the foote thereof a moſte pleſant place, at the ſhoare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Puteola<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> ſea. It is thought, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the name <hi>Puteolis</hi> was deriued of this woorde <hi>Puteus,</hi> which ſignifieth a Well or ſole, becauſe in oulde time there was woonte to bee great ſtore in that place, if yée lyſte therein to followe the deriuacion
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:19307:85"/> of the Latine or of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Italyan,</hi> wherin the <hi>Italians</hi> cal a pit or Sole by the name of <hi>Poreo:</hi> or elſe that it is ſo called of the horible ſauour and ſtench whiche brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theth out of the nigh Mines, to wyt, of Brimſtone and Alume. The aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient writers doe call this Towne <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caearchium.</hi> And although there bee many that cannot agrée aboute the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation thereof, ſuppoſinge that it ſtood ſometime in the place where thoſe ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ines and downefalles are ſéene, namely at the Hilles Foote or ſomewhat far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of: notwithſtandinge the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whiche is ſet downe by the ould writers, declareth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to be falſe: &amp; more credible it is, that it ſtood vpon the litle Hill in whiche place at this tyme there ſtande certen principall Buildinges: how bee it, it maye bée alſo, that all thoſe other ruines might be part therof, as the Suburbes, or ſome other place adioyninge to the Suburbes. In the Towne it ſelfe is nothinge almoſte woorthe the ſight, béeſides the Churche
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:19307:85"/> which is very auncient, and buylded af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch maner and faſhion, that a man may eaſely perceaue that it was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time an Heatheniſh or Ethnick Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Moreouer, there are ingrauen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it the names of the workemen that builded it, and his name alſo, in honour of whom it was buylded. There are alſo to bée ſéene the bones of a mans bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes of monſtrous bygneſſe, vppon which <hi>Pomponius Laetus</hi> a moſt dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſearcher out of Antiquities, wrote this inſcription:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Who ſo thou art that heere amazd doſt ſtand,</l>
                  <l>To ſee the hugie bones of Giantes fell:</l>
                  <l>Come vnderſtand why in Hetrurie lande</l>
                  <l>They do abide. This doth the ſtorie tell,</l>
                  <l>When in this place Alcides once did dwell,</l>
                  <l>And from th'Iberi, conquerour came away,</l>
                  <l>His beaſts he draue along theſe fields, they ſay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then from this hill that Dicarchëum hight,</l>
                  <l>With bended Bow &amp; weightie Club in hand:</l>
                  <l>Theſe Typhons tall, &amp; Giants maine of might</l>
                  <l>He draue away, &amp; quite expulſt the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</l>
                  <l>This wicked broode could not the God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</l>
                  <l>But part anon to Hydrus forth them ſped,</l>
                  <l>And part for ſuccour to the Tuskans fled.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:19307:86"/>
                  <l>Howbeit yet this cauſe of wofull dread,</l>
                  <l>That might vnto ech place by them enſue:</l>
                  <l>Was ſone extinct whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all theſe ſends wer dead,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe blood the ground in ech place did im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue.</l>
                  <l>Poſteritie, to ſhew that this was true:</l>
                  <l>Their bodies keepe of mighty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im &amp; bones.</l>
                  <l>To ſhew the world ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there liued ones.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>The inhabitantes of this towne are all for the more parte Fiſhermen, and they rayſe a great gayne yéerely, of ſutche as traueyll thither of purpoſe to ſee theſe Antiquities. For they em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy theyr traueyll and diligence in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng theyr att<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dance vpon them, and in ſhewynge them the Antiquities all alonge that Seacaoſte. Without the Towne are certeine Monaſteries and houſes of Religion, and manye ſumptuous Pallaices béelongyng vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to noble men. There are alſo ſéene the Monumentes and Fowndacions of verye auncient <hi>Romane</hi> buildyngs, béeynge a thynge moſte certeyne, that the Senatours and Noblemen of <hi>Rome,</hi> had all theyr delyght and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:19307:86"/> of pleaſure there, and in the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders there to neare adioyning, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I haue hetherto intreated, whych maye bée gathered as well oute of <hi>Tullies</hi> Epyſtles, as out of <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius, Dionyſius Halicarnaſsaeus,</hi> and <hi>Liuie.</hi> In the Garden of the Frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars <hi>Franciſcanes,</hi> there is a lymite or bounde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> woorthie to bee viewed: and harde by the Towne are certeyne Vaultes, and Chambers ſtandynge togyther, whiche men thinke were ſometyme Bathes. In goyng vp to the Monaſterie you ſhall ſee three ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye beawtyfull Pyllers: and in go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng downe from it you ſhall ſee a paſſynge large and wyde Amphitea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, buylded wyde in the myddle and narrower towarde eche ende, to the repreſentacion of an Egge, on the outſyde more decayed and defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced then the Amphiteater of <hi>Rome</hi> is, but wythinſyde more tyghte and whole. For it is full of Seates, and all benched about, although in ſome places
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:19307:87"/> the ſeates bée couered with earthe and ouergrowne with buſhes, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of the wall is whole and ſounde which reacheth vp a great height. In my iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t this Amphithetre is one of the moſt auncient <hi>Romane</hi> Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that remayne at this day. Not far from this ſtandeth another building ful of chambers, of a wounderful &amp; ſtrange Arte and Workemanſhip, diuided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to many Celles, the one leadyng vnto the other. Euerie Cell hath four doores to paſſe through to the next adioyning, whereby I ſuſpecte that it was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time a Labyrinth, the <hi>Italians</hi> call it, <hi>Le Camerelle.</hi> Moreouer in the hauen and Boſome, wherin <hi>Puteoli</hi> ſtandeth are ſéene hugie Pyles and Péeres in the maine Sea, builded a longe croſſe the Sea from the ſhoare of <hi>Puteoli,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lande on the other ſide, by <hi>Cali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula</hi> the Emperour, as <hi>Suetonius,</hi> and <hi>Dion Caſsius</hi> do write. Likwiſe there lyeth the Ilande <hi>Crape,</hi> or rather as <hi>Dion</hi> tearmeth it <hi>Caprea,</hi> into which, <hi>Tiberius</hi> the Emperour withdrewe
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:19307:87"/> himſelfe, when hée ſoughte a ſolitarie place, auoiding the ſight of the people.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ <hi>An hill ariſing out of</hi> the grounde.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 12. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis thing moreouer is not to bée o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerpaſſed with ſilence, that in the ſame place of the Realme of <hi>Naples,</hi> which they call <hi>Tripergula,</hi> and neare vnto the village which wée ſhewed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was ſomtime <hi>Ciceroes</hi> Academie: not many yéeres agoe, that is to ſay, in the yéere of our Lorde. M. D. xxxviij. there ſuddeinly aroſe an hill out of the grounde, which remaineth vnto thys day, conteining in compaſſe about foure myles. Béefore this Hill aroſe, there were continually Earthquakes in that place the ſpace of certein dayes without intermiſſion, and fiers of Brimſtonie ſubſtaunce, and of that liquour whych commonlye is called <hi>Oleum Petrae,</hi>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:19307:88"/> Oyle of the Rocke. But anone, when thys fier béegan to growe to a great flame, and when the matter of the fyer was ſome deale ſpent, there inſued ſuche tumbling out of ſtones, and ſuch flying vp of Aſhes, fierce windes, and horrible perturbacion of the ayre: that it was feared that all the whole frame of the worlde would fall. All whyche accidentes <hi>Leander Bononienſis</hi> hath diligently noted, and béefore him a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne <hi>Salernitane</hi> wryting in the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> tongue, one that béehelde that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and terrible Tragedie. <hi>Simon Portius</hi> lykewyſe wroate of the ſame matter, in a Booke intituled, <hi>Of the burnyng of the Realme of Naples.</hi> And although thys wonderfull and ſtrange ſpectacle, was the handye woorke of God, who ruleth the inferiour courſe of Nature: yet are the cauſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to bée weyghed, if there bée any to bée founde to depende vppon naturall reaſon. It is lyke, that the cauſes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of procéeded from ſpirites, and exha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacions of qualitie fierce and ſharpe,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:19307:88"/> and verie myghtye, included in the Earthe, ſo that it was able to lift it vp, and when the Earthe by reaſon of the weyght thereof ſtoutely reſiſted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halacions: it was by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great force ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of mightily driuen out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place where it was before. For the flying out of ſo great abundance of ſtones and aſhes: declareth that there was great abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſuch exhalacions, ſhewing that the earthe was for the more part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, and reſolued into ayre. After this maner, and by eruption of ſpirites out of the earthe, the Poet <hi>Ouid</hi> wyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth that there riſe an Hillocke out of a plain field, néere to the Citie <hi>Troi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zena,</hi> in theſe wordes:</p>
               <l>Not far from Pythei Troizene is a certen high ground found</l>
               <l>All voyd of trees, which heretofore was plain and leuell ground,</l>
               <l>But now a mountaine.</l>
               <p>It is poſſible alſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there may bée new Ilandes found in waters, howbeit not inſuing vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſame cauſe which <hi>Seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra</hi> allegeth to haue hapned in his time,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:19307:89"/> when the Ilands <hi>Theron</hi> and <hi>Therea</hi> grewe in the Sea, not by any allunion or breaking in, as in times paſt the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landes <hi>Echinades</hi> came, of whom <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie</hi> hath noted ſomewhat, or elſe as <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi> which <hi>Herodotus</hi> tearmeth the gifte of the Ryuer: but by abreaking foorth and riſing vp of the Earth, whilſt many men looked vpon it. For the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halations and windes are many times ſo vehement and ſharpe: that they lifte vp the Earth quight aboue the water. Semblably <hi>Ouid</hi> writeth, that by caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of twigges and boughes into the water, there grew an Iland in the ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Tyber.</hi> And verely all this change and alteration is not deuoyd of naturall reaſon, howbeit no man hath euer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the cauſes of them more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancially then hath <hi>Strabo,</hi> where hée ſayth: <hi>Foraſmuch as all things do conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually mooue and are chaunged, we muſt ſuppoſe that the earth remaineth not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes one, ſo that nothing is put to it, or taken from it: nor yet the water: whoſe tranſmutacion &amp; alteration is naturall</hi>
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:19307:89"/> 
                  <hi>and well knowne.</hi> This much <hi>Strabo.</hi> But let vs nowe come to the Citie of <hi>Naples.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>The hill Pauſilypus.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 13. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THus traueiling from the Countrey and Territoryes of <hi>Puteolis</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Citie of <hi>Naples,</hi> at the laſte ſtone from the Citie wée paſſe ouer an hill which they call <hi>Pauſilypus.</hi> The ſame being hollowed through at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> foot, hath a plaine &amp; a direct paſſage through it: in length béeynge halfe an <hi>Italian</hi> myle or ſomewhat more, and ſo wyde: that two Cartes lade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may eaſely paſſe one by an other, but in height it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnéeuen. For at the entrance at both ends (which are like two great gates) it is ſo wyde that a man on horſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe holdyng vp a ſpeare in his hande may enter into it, &amp; not touch y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> top: but within, the height diminiſheth by litle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:19307:90"/> litle, and in no place excéedeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> height of three men. This Hill was in thys ſorte by great induſtrie made hollow, and leuelled, and made ſmoothe on both ſides, méeting togither va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>twiſe in the top. At eche entrance at both ſides are holes, at eche hande one, wherby there commeth in the Sun light, but in the mydle it hath no lyght at al. By reaſon whereof it commeth to paſſe, that when two horſes, or Cartes, or mo, do méete in that place: then they cry aloude <hi>alla Montagna,</hi> or, <hi>alla Marina,</hi> that is to ſay, hold of to the hilward, or to the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that therby ech of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may know on which ſide hee ſhall goe. And it is thought among the common people, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any kill a man in this caue: he can by no meanes get out of it, &amp; this they ſay, is found to be true by experience. Now when you paſſe foorthe of this caue to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Citie of <hi>Naples:</hi> there of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer themſelues to bée ſéene two Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches dedicated vnto our Lady, whereof the one, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is new &amp; lately built, begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to be inritched &amp; largely indowed,
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:19307:90"/> by reaſon of Notable miracles which, they ſaye, the Virgin Mary, hath doone there: the other is almoſt deſolate and forlorne, which in times paſt was very famous. Which thing, as I was infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, cam to paſſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this occaſion, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſtaires wherby folkes vſed to goe vp to the hill neare by, are at this preſent broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away beneath, which in foretime were wont to bée co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modious vnto manye Matrones and auncient Dames, in this reſpect, that by meanes of them they might ſtep aſide into the thickets and buſhes which growe vpon the hill, where vnder colour of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thei worſhipped <hi>Venus</hi> rather, then the Virgin <hi>Marie.</hi> Néere vnto the firſt Chappell or Church, wherof wée now ſpeake, is ſéene the graue of <hi>Virgill Maro,</hi> but ſome ſay that it lyeth in the Gardein of the Monaſterie vppon the hill, hauing this ſuperſcription:</p>
               <l>Mee Mantua bred, Calabres tooke, Parthenop now doth hold,</l>
               <l>Of paſtures I haue ſung, of fieldes, likewiſe of captaines bold.</l>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:19307:91"/>
               <p> Howbeit it is credible enough, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gill</hi> was buried there in a certen Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell which is yet remaining, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes are ſo defaced: y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> here and there a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can ſcarce diſcerne one whole letter, &amp; ther is no Monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be ſéen wherby a man may vnderſtand the truth. The Munks y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> are there, ſay, that there was an I mage of Braſſe vpon the Tumbe, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citizens of <hi>Mantua</hi> tooke away by ſtealth, and dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly kéepe it to this preſent day. Which thyng whether it be true or no, I knowe not. But I my ſelfe among many things mo, ſaw in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame Citie a very auntient ſtatu or I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, vnder which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aboue write ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were ingraue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame were brought fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other place thy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or not: y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> could we not vnderſtand. Likewiſe ſome doe write that the Poet <hi>Ennius</hi> had a picture or Image laid vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his tumbe by the <hi>Scipioes.</hi> And not far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this place wher is ſaid to be <hi>Maroes</hi> graue, lieth alſo the Tumbe of <hi>Iacobus Sannazarius,</hi> whoſe learned works are abroade in the world, vpon which theſe
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:19307:91"/> verſes following are ingrauen, made, as it is iudged, by <hi>Bembus.</hi>
               </p>
               <l>Caſt flowers on this ſacred duſt, as next to Maroes ſchrine:</l>
               <l>So next this Poet comes in gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den gift, and veine diuine.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ <hi>The Citie of Naples.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 14. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANd now when we haue paſſed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hill <hi>Pauſilypus,</hi> the noble citie of <hi>Naples</hi> aduaunceth it ſelfe to ſight, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kynges Sea, &amp; the Metropolitane citie of all that Realme. The ſame was firſt named <hi>Parthenope</hi> when the Citizens of <hi>Cumae</hi> builded it, after the accidents which befell there, wherof we haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed more at large in conuenient place béefore. Of the beginning and foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this Citie, <hi>Silius</hi> the Poet hath thus written:</p>
               <l>One of the Sirenes firſt did giue to thee thy noble name,</l>
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:19307:92"/>
               <l> And to thy walles, that Achelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ia hight, of worthy fame,</l>
               <l>O Naples braue, whoſe dulcet ſonges woont on the ſeas to ring,</l>
               <l>And long ere that her hearers to their fatall end to bring.</l>
               <l>While on the waues shee ſate, and charmd her tunes of woful lay:</l>
               <l>And to the haples Seamen ſange their greeuous great decay.</l>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ <hi>Gardeines.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 15. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FRom the hill towards the Citie, are fermes &amp; cuntrey houſes belonging vnto Noble men, whoſe Gardeins are ſurpaſſing and moſt excellent. Firſt and foremoſt, they abound with plentie of water, deuiſed to runne by ſutche workmanſhip, induſtrie and cunning: that in many places you ſhall ſée wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter run out of a tree, and to fall down into certeyne veſſelles of Marble. In
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:19307:92"/> which veſſelles, you may perceaue by cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning wrought, how <hi>Neptune</hi> ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vpon the water beating the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wyth his thréeforked ſcepter, as it were the waues of the Sea. In ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place you ſhall ſée the <hi>Naiades</hi> and Nymphes of the Sea, or <hi>Aeolus</hi> Kinge of the wyndes. There maye you alſo béeholde the <hi>Faunes,</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres,</hi> made of certein ſhelles that are gathered in the Sea, framed ſo feately: that they ſéeme rather to be grauen or painted, then to bée ſet together of litle ſmall péeces, they do ſo liuely reſemble a naturall and lyuing colour. There bee moreouer Labirinthes, throughe which there runneth water w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> ſundrie crokes &amp; windings, turning ſometime this way, ſomtime that. There be alſo Springes and Welles in theſe Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deines, faſhioned like caues hellow vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the grounde, builded with ſtones y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> are eaten and fretten by ſal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſſe of the Sea water, ſo that the water drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth through them, which is very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to behold. For the ſtones reſemble
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:19307:93"/> the colour of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or Yee, then are thei alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with other fine carued and Checkered péeces ſet in, as Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, Moother of Pearle, and certeyne Herbes whoſe ſéedes béeyng prycked in, and nouriſhed by the moyſture: doe ſpryng and burgein vp in the midſt of the ſtones. The water alſo runneth out of the Welles into the Gardeines, by certen pypes and gutters in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> paue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whiche pauement for the moſte part, is made of Marble, or elſe of faire pauynge tiles, and neuer hurteth the pauement. Theſe pypes and gutters are large and wide, ſeruyng as well to kéepe fiſhe in, as to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le their drink béeynge ſet into them. Neare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe welles or fountaine bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>es, ſtand Cagies of Birds, into which out of the pypes there leapeth water ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie arteficially, and the birdes receaue it verye commodiouſlye. In the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies are merueilous faire and goodly ſinging birdes, brought out of ſtraunge Countreyes. Nexte vnto theſe wée paſſe into very pleaſant and delectable
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:19307:93"/> walks, wherin theſe ar, Arbours, ſhips, Houſes, Centaures, with many other likeneſſes of ſundrye ſtraunge beaſtes, &amp; lyuing creatures. And when ye go out of theſe: there be diuers ſorts of herbs ſet many times after the maner of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brinth or Maze, with thickets of Bay-trées, of Cipres trées, and of Vines. And many times there are ſéene Labi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthes and Mazes of Box trée, Iui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, and Mirtles, moreouer there grow in theſe Gardens Palme trées, the fruite wherof are Dates, with other ſtraung and rare Trées And to be ſhort, (for I wyll now ſpeake nothinge of Images, and Monuments) there is ſuch plentie of moſt delicate and choice fruites, ſuch ſwéet ſmelles, and ſuch pleaſure: that it is not poſſible ther ſhuld be any greater or more delectable in the Gardens of <hi>Heſperides,</hi> that are termed the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deins of all delight.</p>
               <p>Thus from the Monaſterie of Munks whereof I ſpake a litle before, vnto the Citie all the way alonge, are nothinge els but Noble mens Fermes, and gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deiues.
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:19307:94"/> The Citie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in a reache or crooke of the Sea called <hi>Mare Tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhenum,</hi> beinge builded in thrée ſquare fourme, whereof two corners looke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Sea, and the thirde to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the Hilles whiche are not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye farre of from it. It ſtandeth vpon a ground or foundacion not equall or le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, but as it were forked, and riſinge vp on both ſides. The Merchantes and common multitude for the moſte part, inhabite the lower parte of the Citie, and the Noble men the higher. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, there are ſéene moſte ſumptious and bewtifull Pallaces, amonge whiche as chiefe is the Pallace of <hi>Vrſine</hi> prince of <hi>Salerne,</hi> of the Prince of <hi>Sulmo,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Cambius,</hi> adorned &amp; ſet forth with many pictures and Statues, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lioneſſe ſtandinge ouer the gate with this inſcription. <hi>To Iubiter xenius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:19307:94"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>Welles and Streetes.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> 16. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOreouer, I ſuppoſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> this is to bée reckned among the principall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of this Citie, that euery houſe, almoſt, hath a Well or twayne aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly flowing with moſt holſome wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nether is there any other citie in all <hi>Italy</hi> (as concerning ſtore of water) that may be compared with this. The ſtrets of the citie are narow, except thrée only, which as they are ſufficient broade e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough: ſo are they of a merueilous length. The higher Stréete of theſe is called <hi>La vicaria,</hi> another <hi>Capuana,</hi> the thirde lyeth right againſte the Caſtle, and ſtretcheth open alonge to the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place. The Stréet <hi>Capuana</hi> leadeth towardes <hi>Capua,</hi> whiche Citie is very famous &amp; renowmed for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ciuile law, eſpecially in mater of contracte. For the firſte <hi>Prator</hi> or Maiour thereof was
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:19307:95"/> a ſtraunger, and in oulde time it muche flouriſhed with trade of Merchandize. Wherby returnes of paymentes vpon billes, and exchaunges, were woonte to bée diſcharged ether there or at <hi>Rome,</hi> or at <hi>Bithynia,</hi> a citie of <hi>Aſia.</hi> Vpon the Gate of this Stréete are manie Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be ſéene. whiche was made at what time <hi>Charles</hi> the fift Emperours of <hi>Rome,</hi> and King of <hi>Naples,</hi> firſt of a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> creatures entred in at the ſame, the like wherof alſo the Citizens of <hi>Andwarpe</hi> did imitate in a gate of theirs afterward Beefore the Gate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Images of <hi>Oceanus,</hi> and <hi>Tethis,</hi> and alſo in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tréete in conuenient places, were er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected the Statues of <hi>Hercules, Athlas, Perpetuitie, Religion,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, whiche <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re ſet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph of <hi>Naples.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:19307:95"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>The Merket place, and Churches.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> 17. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe chiefeſt Merket place of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is fourſquare, and verye broade, and large, but not paued, in the midſte wherof ſtande a paire of Gallowes, and a ſcaffold ſet vp for the nonce to put treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſers to death vpon: alſo a Chappell, rightouer againſte whiche, is a Well with a very large Ceſterne or Lauer. In the Merket place are many Innes, but they bée of the meane and common ſorte, and the greateſt want in <hi>Naples,</hi> is of clenly and ſoote lodgings, although that be an infinite number of Tauerns and vittling houſes in it.</p>
               <p>It hath not manie Churches, but thoſe whiche it hath are verye faier, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which the Cathedrall Churche of Sainct <hi>Clare</hi> is paſſing bewtyfull, and ſo is y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> alſo which is dedicated vnto
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:19307:96"/> Sainct <hi>Luio,</hi> ſauing that it is ouer dark. Sainct <hi>Maries</hi> of the Preachinge Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, is a verie proper Churche, for it ſtandeth vpon one of the moſte pleaſant and loftyeſt places of the Citie, and within, it is almoſte made al of Marble without any periettinge or plaſtering: but it is ſumwhat of the naroweſt. Sainct <hi>Marie</hi> Churche <hi>Di Carbona,</hi> is very mutch frequented for deuocion ſake, whiche is a Houſe of Religion not farre from the Merket place, by reaſon whereof it hath in it a number of vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed Tables, and two Chappels all of Marble faſte béeſide the higher Altare. Within the Altare is a Tumbe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in reſte the bodies of <hi>Robert</hi> Kinge of <hi>Naples</hi> and his Wyfe, verye ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous: inſomutch that the report goeth, that there is neuer a péece of woorke to be found in all <hi>Europe,</hi> of greater ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie then that is. Howbeit, if not fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erer then this, yet in my opinion, match vnto it is that, wherein lyeth the bodie of <hi>William Croius</hi> and his Wife
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:19307:96"/> in <hi>Belgicum</hi> or Dutchlande, not farre from <hi>Louane;</hi> at the Caſtle of <hi>Heffria.</hi> Likewiſe the Tumbe of <hi>Mauritius</hi> of <hi>Saxonie</hi> one of the Dukes Electours, at <hi>Friburge</hi> in <hi>Hermonduris,</hi> and that alſo wherein his Wyfe lieth at <hi>Vima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> in <hi>Thuringe,</hi> and moreouer the ſame which is builded at <hi>Heidelburge,</hi> in the memorie of Duke <hi>Palatine,</hi> Duke Electour. Truly theſe 4. Tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bes whiche I haue nowe named, are the moſt principall of all that euer I ſawe, ether in <hi>Italye,</hi> or <hi>Fraunce,</hi> or <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie,</hi> or in <hi>England,</hi> for, as for <hi>Spayne:</hi> I was neuer there. But amongſt al that are ſéene in any of theſe aboue named Regions, made of Braſſe or Copper, in my iudgement, the Tumbe of Kinge <hi>Henrie</hi> the ſeuenth King of <hi>Englande,</hi> ſurpaſſeth the reſidew, whiche ſtandeth in the Abbey of Weſtminſter nigh to the Citie of London, with an inſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Latine verſes, which may thus bée Engliſhed.</p>
               <lg>
                  <pb n="176" facs="tcp:19307:97"/>
                  <l>Kinge Henrie the ſeuenth heere lieth in this place,</l>
                  <l>The glorie of all Kinges that liued at his age</l>
                  <l>In wit, and wealth, and deedes of noble grace.</l>
                  <l>To whom befell the gifts of nature for vauntage.</l>
                  <l>A princelie countenaunce, a fauour graue and ſage</l>
                  <l>A comly perſonage, and bewtie heroicall:</l>
                  <l>And ech poinct of venuſtie ioyned therwithall.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Vnto him was coupled in wedlocks pleaſant band</l>
                  <l>An amiable Spouſe in beautie right diuine,</l>
                  <l>Bashfull and verteous, and like a frutefull land</l>
                  <l>Plentifull of children, ſprong forth of princely line.</l>
                  <l>Right happie parentes their iſsue ſo doth shine.</l>
                  <l>To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, o Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, theſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks thou oweſt of right</l>
                  <l>That euer Henrie the 8. was borne into thy ſight.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>All the whole Toumbe is gilten ouer, and it ſhineth faire, being round beſet with precious Stones but of the meaneſt ſorte, it hath in it alſo many turned and carued pillers, and very lyke vnto this: are the mounmentes of the Kinges of Fraunce in Sainct <hi>Deniſe</hi> Churche.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:19307:97"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>Granetes and Stoare Houſes, Caſtles, and Armaries.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> 18. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOreouer, there are at <hi>Naples</hi> foure Storehouſes, and as the Grecians term them <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, euery one fourſquare benched rounde aboute mutch lyke the place at <hi>Andwarp</hi> whiche they call the Burſe, or at London the Roiall Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, and at <hi>Venice la piazza del ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo alto.</hi> In theſe Store houſes at certen times of the yéere are generall aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, and counſelles holden. And Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes alſo méete dayly in them, to bargein and deale in Merchandize.</p>
               <p>There are thrée Caſtles, whereof twayne ſtande faſte by the Sea ſide, to wit: the new and the ould, the thirde is ſituate vppon the high Hill that lyeth ouer the Towne. And it is ſo ſtronge,
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:19307:98"/> and ſo well fortified: that hée that haſt poſſeſſion of that Caſtle may eaſely ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Citi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, yea although it were ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed by the enemie. A litle beneth this caſtle is a houſe of <hi>Carthuſians,</hi> wherof the Church is dedicated to Sainct <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi> from whence there is a merueil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous pleaſaunt proſpect, both ouer the Citie, and the ſea. But in the ould Caſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle which ſtandeth by the way <hi>Capuana</hi> are very auntient buildinges and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerie to bée ſéene, and there is alſo an Armarie wherein is kept the complete armour of <hi>Fraunces</hi> Kinge of France, whiche hée woare vpon hym when hee was taken priſoner at the Citie <hi>Tici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> now termed <hi>Pauia</hi> in <hi>Lumbardie</hi> very faire, made of pure ſtéel, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any furniture of Golde. Foorth of the Caſtle you may goe into excéedinge large, and goodly Gardeines: and within the Caſtle is an hangynge Gardeine, but the ſame, beſids a pleaſant proſpect, hath nothinge elſe in it.</p>
               <p>The newe Caſtle is builded at the entrance into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citie of <hi>Tiburtine</hi> ſtone
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:19307:98"/> foureſquare. In the ſame place in ould time ſtoode a Religious Houſe of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching Friers, whiche is now conuerted to another vſe. It is fortified on that ſide whiche lyeth to the Citie with a verie déepe ditch, lyke as it were double tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. For when you be paſt the firſte Ditch: anone you ſhall ſée the Caſtle, which lykewiſe is fenced with a trench, Walles, and Turretes, and it ſtandeth vpon a ſtéepe downefall of an hyll. It hath a verie faire gate in the innerſyde made all of Marble, openinge vpon a large Courte foureſquare, ſumewhat long. At the left hande when you enter in, there is is a litle Hal likewiſe foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſquare, wherein the méetinges and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of the Eſtates of the whole Realme, are kept euery yéere: &amp; the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere</hi> of the cuntrey vſeth to kéepe court, and ſit in iudgment there euery wéeke. But not far from this Hall in a verye great Tower, ar kept theſe ornaments of the kings. A Scepter of gold beſet w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> veryie great Pearles at the toppe. A Sword with the Hilt and ſcabbarde of
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:19307:99"/> Golde very ritchly garniſhed with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Stones. A Crowne or Diademe for a Kinge, glittringe with precious and orient Stones of incredible big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. A Croſſe of cleane Golde, one ſpanne longe. A mightye Pot of Gold rounde aboute adorned with precious Stones of great valew, mightye bigge Pearles called <hi>Vniones,</hi> and principall ſorts of moſt precious Stones, in great number. To bée ſhorte, there is a Treaſure whoſe eſtimation and price is ineſtimable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="181" facs="tcp:19307:99"/>
               <head>¶ <hi>Antiquities, the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, and peculiar</hi> properties of the Citie <hi>and People of Naples.</hi>
               </head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The</hi> 19. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IT is wounderfull to ſée, what plentie of moſt auntient Images are to bee ſéene in the Citie of <hi>Naples,</hi> yea in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate mens houſes, namely of <hi>Bacchus, Mercurie, Hercules, Brutus,</hi> and the whole patterne of the auntient maner of warfare. There bée alſo Statues made wearinge on them gownes, and a mightye horſehead made of Bras very cunningly wrought, the lyke wherof is ſéene at <hi>Rome</hi> in the pallace of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>De valle.</hi> Howbeit one <hi>Cyriacus Anconitanus,</hi> hath writen verye dilly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentlye of all theſe matters, for that which <hi>Apianus</hi> and <hi>Amantius</hi> haue ſet
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:19307:100"/> foorth in this argument touchinge an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities: is for the more part taken out of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fredirick</hi> the ſeconde Emperoure of <hi>Rome,</hi> founded the Vniuerſitie in this Citie, whiche flouriſheth at this daye. While I abode there, <hi>Simon Portus,</hi> a famous Philoſopher and Phyſition, departed this lyfe. The ſame, béeſides the Booke whiche hée wroat of the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninge of the cuntrie of, <hi>Puteolis,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I made mencion béefore, wroat a Booke of the Soule, of the Senſes, of Coulers, of the <hi>Germain</hi> Mayden, and many other moe. One <hi>Mercellus</hi> of <hi>Siene</hi> was of great renowme amonge the <hi>Icti,</hi> a man very well learned and eloquent: as for Diuinitie that was in thoſe daies ſent to the Monaſteries and Abbeies, as it was likewiſe in the more part of all <hi>Italie. Naples</hi> féeleth winter ſcarſelye the ſpace of two Monthes, to wit, <hi>Ianuarie</hi> &amp; <hi>Februarie.</hi> They haue raine often, but without ſnowe, and in Summer ſeaſon extreame heat, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whereof they ſeldome haue anye
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:19307:100"/> ſtéepe couerings and rouffes vpon their Houſen as are in other Cuntries, that in the night time they may walke vpon the top of the Houſes in the Leades, to coole their bodies. In the vulgare toonge this Citie is termed by the name of <hi>Gentiles,</hi> which is to ſay Noble, lyke as <hi>Rome</hi> is called Great, <hi>Venice</hi> Ritch, <hi>Florence</hi> Faire, as I coniecture to the imitation of the Gréekes, whiche vſed alſo to commende their chiefe Cities by ſome notable Title. For <hi>Athenaeus</hi> comparinge certen Cities together: cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it Golden <hi>Alexandria,</hi> Bewtifull <hi>Antiochia,</hi> very bewtifull <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> and the Citie of <hi>Athens</hi> moſt glorious, the mightie Citie, and Breuiarie, as it were, of al the whole Worlde. And I think, that <hi>Naples</hi> was called Noble by reaſon of the great number of Noble men that dwell in it, &amp; the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ceſſe which is vſed there. And a man ſhall not finde in any other place of all <hi>Italie,</hi> ſo great plenty of moſt excellent and couragious Horſes, as hée ſhall there: But if a man would bringe a Horſe of that Cuntrey
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:19307:101"/> out of the Realme: hée muſt pay ſome cuſtome or tolledge for hym, and they ſell there not only Horſes, and all other kindes of Merchandize: but alſo ſlaues, as wel men as women. There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Théeues, and in ſundrye places the Neapolitanes are euill ſpoken of, not ſo mutch for that themſelues be of an euill Nature: but bicauſe they harbour ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne naughty perſons, and haue naughtie neighbours. Thoſe are the <hi>Apuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>Calabrians,</hi> and <hi>Sicilians,</hi> of whom, that is to ſaye, the laſte, that may truely bée ſayde whiche <hi>Cicero</hi> wroat of them: <hi>All Iland dwellers are naught, but the Sicilians are woorſt of all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But now, as concerninge the proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the the People of <hi>Naples:</hi> they are not ſo mutche delighted with the Gréeke: and Latine: as with the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſcan</hi> tongue, and they mocke the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labrians</hi> with their language, and lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the <hi>Calabrians</hi> ſcorne at the <hi>Apu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians.</hi> Their talke is full of brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginge and boaſtinge, inſomutche that
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:19307:101"/> they deſpiſe the counſell of othermen, and prefer their owne wittes before al others. It ſufficeth their merchantes if you giue them your woorde, but if you breake promiſe, they be very ſharp re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uengers of the iniurie done vnto them, like as they be very mindfull of a good turne receaued. They fare paſſing ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſly, and ſometime they ſpend more Sugar at a meale then they do breade, imitating therein the <hi>Sicilians.</hi> In ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairell they bée proude, and therin they beſtow ouer much coſt both in tyme of Warre, and Peace. They aſſault their enemy with notable courage and opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitie, &amp; they haue horſes verie méete for the warres, wheron they be erpert in riding, and guide the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with meruey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous dexteritie of body. They are too too much giuen to loue and ouer amarous, but eſpecially of ſuche wéemen as are painted in face, and proud of hart, vnto which two thinges their wéemen doe principally apply themſelues. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they bee very good huſwyues, and bée moſt preciſe, and as it were, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:19307:102"/> in honouring their louers. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, the people of <hi>Naples</hi> are verye curteous and friendly to ſtraungers, and loue them in whom they ſée anye notable or ſingular qualitie, but if they ſée no ſuch thing: they litle eſtéeme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And this much of the Citie of <hi>Naples.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ <hi>The Kings Pittes or Pondes, and the hill <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuuius</hi> called nowe <hi>Summi,</hi> and of others.</head>
               <head>
                  <hi>The.</hi> 20. <hi>Chapter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WIthout the Citie, on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſide which is contrarie or oueragainſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hill <hi>Pauſilipus:</hi> are ſéene the kinges Pittes or Pondes commonly called <hi>Pozzi reali,</hi> truely verie fayre, and worthie to bée throughly viewed. And vnleſſe I bée deceaued, there is the lyke place at <hi>Rome,</hi> and at <hi>Ferraria Ilbel Veder,</hi> which is to ſaye, as I interprete it, A
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:19307:102"/> place for Summer conſiſting of hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Gardeines, and Riuers: likewyſe moſt excellent for proſpecte, and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſituation. This goodly building or rather Pallaice, was erected by <hi>Ferdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nand</hi> of <hi>Arrago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> firſt, king of <hi>Naples</hi> in fourme foureſquare, but ſomewhat long, in whoſe walles ſtand very aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Pictures to be ſéene. The middle court was made to waſhe in, wythout couert in the open aire, from whence we mount vp thrée ſteppes into a place lyke a Lauer or Ceſterne, into which you may let in the water at your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and that great Courte is round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute compaſſed with a beautifull, and verie gorgeous gallerie. But in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt ſiege of the Citie of <hi>Naples,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſpoyled not onely this Gallerie: but welnighe all the whole Pallaice. While this waſhing place was whole, I ſuppoſe there was none more mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificall or pleaſaunter in al <hi>Italy.</hi> Ouer againſt this Pallaice, ſtandeth another Princely buildynge, or Pallaice, and a place alſo from whence Water is
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:19307:103"/> conueid in pypes vnto the citie. From the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wée paſſe into Gardeins in which there is another gallerie, before whom lieth a large and wide plot, but waſte and forlorne, alouergrowne w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> réedes, buſhes, and briars. From hence againe wée goe into other gardeines: at length wée come vnto a fountaine or conduite head paſſing faire and cleare, and full of holſome ſwéete water. Hard by this conduite head ſtoode certen Cagies and Couppes, wherein were kepte ſundry kindes of beaſts, and liuing things, but they were alſo broken by the French<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from this place we may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne again to the firſt, through offices and places apperteining to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſhold, where are many ſpoutes and Welles, and many pleaſant murmurings cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by falling and flowing of the water, likewiſe groues, and the pleaſant fight of varitie of fruites.</p>
               <p>From this place wée maye goo too ſée the remainder and monumentes of the citie <hi>Palaeopolis,</hi> whereof <hi>Liuius</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth mencion. There is alſo another
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:19307:103"/> place not far from <hi>Naples</hi> of noleſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light then anye of the aboue recited, at the fourthe ſtone from the Citie, at the foote of the hill <hi>Veſuuius</hi> or <hi>Summi,</hi> in which hill <hi>Plinius</hi> the writer of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall hiſtorie, and Lieutenant ouer the fléete to <hi>Auguſtus:</hi> periſhed among the aſhes, which <hi>Plinius</hi> the ſecond teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in an Epiſtle, and the ſame hil not long before had burned lyke the hill of <hi>Aetna</hi> in <hi>Sicil.</hi> At the foote of this Hill ther groweth Greekiſh wine or Sack, which ſome call <hi>Vinum Pompeianum</hi> or <hi>Pompeius</hi> wine, which is very good and perfecte, and much commended of by the writings of ſundry men. The Pallace whiche ſtandeth there taketh name of the village which is néere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, and is called <hi>Pietra biancha,</hi> wee may call it in Engliſhe <hi>White ſtone, or whiterocke,</hi> builded all within of white Marble, and bewtified in the lodgings with checkred work of point deuiſe. In this Pallace is made the Image of a Nymphe ſléeping, and leaning vppon a water veſſell, out of which there run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:19307:104"/> abundance of pure criſtall water, which afterward paſſeth along in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghes or gutters of Marble ſtone, &amp; hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth no part of the pauement, the ſame gutters ſeruing alſo to kéepe fiſhe in, like as it were little fiſhpondes. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I am of opinion, that aſwell the auncient <hi>Romanes</hi> as <hi>Greekes,</hi> tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in oulde time ſutche buildinges <hi>Nymphaea,</hi> howbéeit this is but newe, and builded by one that was a councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fifte, about the yéere of our Lorde, as ſome ſay, 1530. It hath on the one ſide the ſea harde by, rounde aboute on the other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides a goodly plaine and open cuntrey, the plentifulneſſe wherof is wounder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full both of Corne, Oile, Wine, and all maner other good fruites. This which I will ſpeake is hard to bée credited, &amp; yet it is true, that there bée ſome Vines found there the grapes whereof beyng preſſed doo yéelde x. or xij. meaſures of wine, euerie meaſure contayning iiij. gallons and a halfe or rather more of oure Meaſures. And thys thynge
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:19307:104"/> alſo may ſéeme ſtraunge, which one hath reported in writing for a trueth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when the Northeaſt wind bloweth, there are brought into the Cuntrey of <hi>Naples</hi> out of <hi>Africa</hi> ſutche abundance of Quailes, that they fall by heapes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon houſes that bée néere to the Sea ſide, that men may eaſely take them in their hands. Yea, while they be in their courſe of flying, and bée wéeryed either wyth contrarie wyndes, or tempeſte, or lengthe of the iourney, they lyght many times vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome ſhippe, or gally. And laſte of all to conclude, ſuche is the deliciouſnes of the Realme of <hi>Naples,</hi> ſuche the magnificencie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> buildings, ſutche the holſomeneſſe of the welles and water, ſutche plentie of all thinges whiche nature bryngeth foorthe into the worlde myraculous and ſtraunge, ſutche Monuments of Antiquities, and finally ſuche ſtore of fruites, and other things wherwith mans life is ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: it is that not only truly named to bee aa parte of the happye <hi>Campania,</hi> but is indéede the Wombe, as they ſaye, of fertilitie, and the fatte of
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:19307:105"/> 
                  <hi>Italie</hi> and the verie horne of plentie, as is in the prouerbe. All which thinges when wée had viewed verie diligently, béeing not ſo muche wéeried with our labour and traueyll, as that wee iudged it time to retourne to our ſtudies: (for the deſire whiche wée had to ſée theſe things, and the moſt delectable behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of them tooke away all wéeriſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) we departed from <hi>Naples,</hi> &amp; paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing along by the moſt auncient Citie <hi>Caieta:</hi> wee came to <hi>Rome,</hi> and from thence we traueiled by the <hi>Tuſkans</hi> to <hi>Padua.</hi> And when I had there arriued, I ſoiourned there a ſeaſon, and afterwarde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted into my natiue Cuntrey.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprinted at London by VVilliam How, for Abraham Veale</hi> dwelling in Paules Church-yarde at the ſigne of the La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19307:105"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
